<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Security on Facile.it Engineering</title>
    <link>https://engineering.facile.it/categories/security/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Security on Facile.it Engineering</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://engineering.facile.it/categories/security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Json Web Token</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/json-web-tokens/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/json-web-tokens/</guid>
      <description>When I started my study about JWT, I was searching for a smart method to authenticate a request, without querying the database each time to check the applicant reliability. I needed a token or something similar with the ability to validate itself and flexible enough to customize the validation strategy. Imagine for example a web application where a user can login and obtain a &amp;ldquo;pass&amp;rdquo; with his name and an expiration time, and this pass will let him ask for resources until the pass expires, and only if the issuer is trusted.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Protection of sensitive data using encryption</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/protection-of-sensitive-data-using-encryption/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/protection-of-sensitive-data-using-encryption/</guid>
      <description>Data protection is one of the major and recurrent problems in recent years: whether it is private information of users, or the company for which we work, the problem is always the same.
How to protect such data from any attackers who would - and could (!!) - be able to gain possession?
Before arriving at the solution of this problem, however, is right to split the series in at least two branches.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Protezione di dati sensibili usando la crittografia</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/protezione-di-dati-sensibili-usando-la-crittografia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/protezione-di-dati-sensibili-usando-la-crittografia/</guid>
      <description>La protezione dei dati è uno dei problemi più sentiti e ricorrenti degli ultimi anni: che si tratti di informazioni private di utenti, o dell&amp;rsquo;azienda per cui lavoriamo, il problema è sempre lo stesso.
Come proteggere questi dati da eventuali malintenzionati che vorrebbero - e potrebbero(!!) - riuscire a entrarne in possesso ?
Prima di arrivare alla soluzione di questo problema però, è doveroso suddividere la casistica in almeno due rami.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>