<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Security on Facile.it Engineering</title>
    <link>https://engineering.facile.it/categories/security/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Security on Facile.it Engineering</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 17:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://engineering.facile.it/categories/security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hack the Box Experience</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/hack-the-box-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/hack-the-box-experience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;After the successful experience of &lt;a href=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/v-protetto8-3-2024/&#34; title=&#34;Previously, on Venerdì Protetto... a code challenge!&#34;&gt;having a code challenge in March 2024&lt;/a&gt;, we decided to go further in delivering experiences to our colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Scouting around, I turned to Alessio Giorgianni, a developer with a passion for white hat hacking competition. We agree to try an experience using a platform called &lt;a href=&#34;https://academy.hackthebox.com/&#34;&gt;Hack the Box&lt;/a&gt;. Hack the Box Academy offers lots of information and training about IT Security and, in our case, some exercises we can use for hacking dummy applications, with a whitebox example (i.e., an example where all the code is undisclosed to us. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eccouncil.org/cybersecurity-exchange/penetration-testing/black-box-gray-box-and-white-box-penetration-testing-importance-and-uses/#:~:text=Objectives%3A%20Black%2Dbox%20testers%20seek,somewhere%20between%20these%20two%20extremes&#34;&gt;There are also different kind of pentest&lt;/a&gt;). We agreed upon using a non-trivial quest, called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hackthebox.com/achievement/challenge/48545/638&#34;&gt;Jerrytok&lt;/a&gt;. Jerrytok is a WAPT (Web App Penetration Testing) whitebox challenge. We got a simple web-application, written in PHP, which disclose the harm of using template engines in a not-proper way. It&amp;rsquo;s a good introduction to SSTI, &lt;a href=&#34;https://portswigger.net/web-security/server-side-template-injection&#34;&gt;Server Side Template Injection&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Json Web Token</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/json-web-tokens/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/json-web-tokens/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/json-web-tokens/logo.svg&#34; alt=&#34;JWT&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When I started my study about JWT, I was searching for a smart method to authenticate a request, without querying the database each time to check the applicant reliability.&#xA;I needed a token or something similar with the ability to validate itself and flexible enough to customize the validation strategy.&#xA;Imagine for example a web application where a user can login and obtain a &amp;ldquo;pass&amp;rdquo; with his name and an expiration time, and this pass will let him ask for resources until the pass expires, and only if the issuer is trusted.&#xA;Thanks to JWT&amp;rsquo;s self verification capabilities, I could discard every request where the token is invalid (a fake token not signed by my application) or expired.&#xA;Beyond this specific use case, JWT can be also useful to securely transmit data to other applications.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protection of sensitive data using encryption</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/protection-of-sensitive-data-using-encryption/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/protection-of-sensitive-data-using-encryption/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Data protection is one of the major and recurrent problems in recent years: whether it is private information of users, or the company for which we work, the problem is always the same.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to protect such data from any attackers who would - and could (!!) - be able to gain possession?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Before arriving at the solution of this problem, however, is right to split the series in at least two branches. In the wwww data can be &amp;ldquo;obtained&amp;rdquo; in two different moments: 1) as they pass over the network in packets, or 2) after their storing (eg. database or file) in one or more servers.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protezione di dati sensibili usando la crittografia</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/protezione-di-dati-sensibili-usando-la-crittografia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/protezione-di-dati-sensibili-usando-la-crittografia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;La protezione dei dati è uno dei problemi più sentiti e ricorrenti degli ultimi anni: che si tratti di informazioni private di utenti, o dell&amp;rsquo;azienda per cui lavoriamo, il problema è sempre lo stesso.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Come proteggere questi dati da eventuali malintenzionati che vorrebbero -  e potrebbero(!!) -  riuscire a entrarne in possesso ?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Prima di arrivare alla soluzione di questo problema però, è doveroso suddividere la casistica in almeno due rami. Nel mondo del web i dati possono essere &amp;ldquo;ottenuti&amp;rdquo; in due momenti differenti: 1) mentre transitano sulla rete sotto forma di pacchetti, oppure 2) successivamente al loro immagazzinamento (es. database o file) all&amp;rsquo;interno di uno o più server.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
