<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kotlin on Facile.it Engineering</title>
    <link>https://engineering.facile.it/categories/kotlin/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Kotlin on Facile.it Engineering</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://engineering.facile.it/categories/kotlin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Using Kotlin type-safe builders to create a DSL for Forms</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/kotlin-dsl/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/kotlin-dsl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here at Facile.it we are constantly dealing with a lot of &lt;strong&gt;forms&lt;/strong&gt;: we use them to collect various information and data needed to feed our in-house comparing algorithms. These forms could be &lt;strong&gt;really complex&lt;/strong&gt;, having multiple rules and dependencies between fields, and they are likely to be &lt;strong&gt;changed and tuned frequently&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When I joined Facile.it, a lot of forms within the Android app needed to be updated or modified and sticking with the existing strategy would have required me to do &lt;strong&gt;a lot of work&lt;/strong&gt; just to add or remove a simple field. So I took a step back and I started thinking about a strategy that would have allowed me to define and structure a form in a more &lt;em&gt;flexible&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;declarative&lt;/em&gt; way. I wanted to be able to declare the &lt;strong&gt;relationships&lt;/strong&gt; between fields, their &lt;strong&gt;validation rules&lt;/strong&gt; and their &lt;strong&gt;serialized representation&lt;/strong&gt; (how they are sent to the server).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new hope for the JVM: Kotlin</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/kotlin-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/kotlin-intro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/kotlin-intro/logo_Kotlin.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Kotlin&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;premise&#34;&gt;Premise&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Java is an &lt;strong&gt;old&lt;/strong&gt; programming language. Version 1.0 was released in 1996 by Sun Microsystems and  even though it has evolved and grown a lot over the past twenty years it is still carrying on some bad design choices such as &lt;em&gt;null&lt;/em&gt; (ask &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Hoare?section=3#Apologies_and_retractions&#34;&gt;Tony Hoare&lt;/a&gt;), primitive types or lack of a proper function type. With the last version of the language (Java 8) Java tried to address some of these problems introducing concepts such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/Optional.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/java/javaOO/lambdaexpressions.html&#34;&gt;lambda expression&lt;/a&gt;. Although these additions clearly represent a step forward for the language I still have the feeling that they are just &lt;em&gt;patches&lt;/em&gt; applied to &lt;strong&gt;mitigate problems&lt;/strong&gt; and not to solve them at their very source. For example &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; could be used to reduce NPE (Null Pointer Exception) but it is clearly not designed for &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mariofusco/status/780770300178956289&#34;&gt;this purpose&lt;/a&gt; and lambda expressions, implemented in Java 8 with SAM types, still force you to write an interface only to define a &lt;em&gt;function&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
