<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Software Complexity on Facile.it Engineering</title>
    <link>https://engineering.facile.it/categories/software-complexity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Software Complexity on Facile.it Engineering</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://engineering.facile.it/categories/software-complexity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>No Country For If Else</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/no-country-for-if-else/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/no-country-for-if-else/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is an &lt;strong&gt;unwanted guest&lt;/strong&gt; with us as we write code and build software projects: it&amp;rsquo;s the code that&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;already written&lt;/strong&gt;, and we must take into account its complexity as the code base increases in size. High complexity of the existing code can make the following activities particularly difficult:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;understanding the meaning of old code, written by others or ourselves;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;tracing the causes of bugs, i.e. errors, in code;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;making changes to a certain procedure;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;adding features to existing structures;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Even if we approach the development of new software with &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agile_software_development&#34;&gt;agile methodologies&lt;/a&gt;, we always have to deal with the existing code, and to do that we must at least be able to &lt;strong&gt;understand it without overexertion&lt;/strong&gt;. So when I talk about &lt;em&gt;complexity&lt;/em&gt; I am referring in particular to the difficulty with which a programmer can &lt;em&gt;reason about&lt;/em&gt; the existing code: the preface of the well-known academic textbook &lt;a href=&#34;http://deptinfo.unice.fr/~roy/sicp.pdf&#34;&gt;Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs&lt;/a&gt; contains the following sentence:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No Country For If Else</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/no-country-for-if-else/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/no-country-for-if-else/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;C&amp;rsquo;è un &lt;strong&gt;ospite indesiderato&lt;/strong&gt; che ci accompagna sempre mentre scriviamo codice e realizziamo progetti software: si tratta del &lt;strong&gt;codice già esistente&lt;/strong&gt;, e dobbiamo tener conto della sua complessità man mano che la &lt;em&gt;code base&lt;/em&gt; aumenta di dimensioni. Un&amp;rsquo;elevata complessità del codice può rendere le seguenti attività particolarmente difficili:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;comprendere il significato di codice vecchio, scritto da altri o da se stessi;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;tracciare le cause di bug, cioè errori, nel codice;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;eseguire modifiche a una certa procedura;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;aggiungere funzionalità a strutture già esistenti;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Anche approcciando lo sviluppo di nuovo software con &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agile_software_development&#34;&gt;metodologie agili&lt;/a&gt;, dobbiamo comunque fare i conti con il codice esistente, e per farlo dobbiamo almeno essere in grado di &lt;strong&gt;comprenderlo senza sforzi eccessivi&lt;/strong&gt;. Dunque quando parlo di &lt;em&gt;complessità&lt;/em&gt; mi riferisco in particolare alla difficoltà con la quale una programmatore è in grado di &lt;em&gt;ragionare&lt;/em&gt; sul codice. La prefazione del noto testo accademico &lt;a href=&#34;http://deptinfo.unice.fr/~roy/sicp.pdf&#34;&gt;Structure and interpretation of computer programs&lt;/a&gt; contiene la seguente frase:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
