<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Protected Fridays on Facile.it Engineering</title>
    <link>https://engineering.facile.it/categories/protected-fridays/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Protected Fridays on Facile.it Engineering</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 17:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://engineering.facile.it/categories/protected-fridays/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Venerdì Protetto - May 12th 2023</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/v-protetto12-5-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/v-protetto12-5-2023/</guid>
      <description>This page contains the abstracts of the talks held during the latest Venerdì Protetto on May 12, 2023.
Topics:
 API testing by Domenico Buttafarro &amp;amp; Vincenzo Gasparo Morticella (Facile.it) ChatGPT and React by Alessio Monesi (Facile.it) Mental health at work by Francesco Di Muro (Lobby Frontali)  API testing API testing with Prism and Playwright by Domenico Buttafarro &amp;amp; Vincenzo Gasparo Morticella
Today&amp;rsquo;s software landscape is highly competitive and users are increasingly reluctant to tolerate unreliable applications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Venerdì Protetto - April 14th 2023</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/v-protetto14-4-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 11:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/v-protetto14-4-2023/</guid>
      <description>This page contains the abstracts of the talks held during the latest Venerdì Protetto on April 14, 2023.
Topics:
 Backstage by Lee Mills (Spotify) Code revolution by Mirko Urru &amp;amp; Stefano Giurgiano (Facile.it) Dynamic forms by Giovanni Fiorentino (Facile.it)  Backstage An introduction to Backstage, managing the chaos by Lee Mills, Spotify
At the beginning of this year, our engineering teams adopted a new tool: Backstage, an open-source platform for building developer portals created at Spotify.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Venerdì Protetto, AKA Protected Friday</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/v-protetto/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Apr 2023 11:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/v-protetto/</guid>
      <description>What is it all about? At Facile.it, we strongly believe in sharing knowledge and experiences. Thus, we dedicate one Friday a month to expanding our knowledge and learning among colleagues in the IT department. These Fridays are called Venerdì Protetto. During the so-called Venerdì Protetto, i. e. Protected Friday, we welcome speakers and participate in talks on IT-related topics. Speakers are colleagues or external guests.
Archive of talks The archive of all Venerdì Protetto talks is available here.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>