<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on Facile.it Engineering</title>
    <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on Facile.it Engineering</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://engineering.facile.it/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How to gradually upgrade toward PHPUnit 6 with namespaced classes</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/phpunit-upgrade-namespace/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/phpunit-upgrade-namespace/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In the latest months I wrote multiple times, in different projects, code migrating &lt;strong&gt;PHPUnit&lt;/strong&gt; toward major &lt;strong&gt;version 6&lt;/strong&gt;. This upgrade is harder than the previous one, since in this version it was introduced a big breaking change: &lt;strong&gt;all classes got (finally!) namespaced&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that any usage of those classes in your project needs to be updated. It may seem a simple find &amp;amp; replace job, but since you need to introduce at least one &lt;code&gt;use PHPUnit\Framework\TestCase&lt;/code&gt; line at the top of each one of your test classes, it&amp;rsquo;s a boring and a little more than trivial task; also, &lt;strong&gt;upgrading it in a single big jump may not be feasible or prudent&lt;/strong&gt;, especially in the case of open source or distributed libraries, where backward compatibility and support for old PHP versions must be ensured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article I will explain which steps I applied during those migrations, highlighting the most frequent hiccups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-easy-one-only-tests&#34;&gt;The easy one: only tests&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start with, you have to find all the &lt;strong&gt;usages of PHPUnit classes&lt;/strong&gt; in your project: a simple search for every occurrence of the string &lt;code&gt;PHPUnit_&lt;/code&gt; should be enough at the beginning. You should know that, in some recent versions previous to 6, PHPUnit delivers a &lt;strong&gt;forward compatibility&lt;/strong&gt; layer; this means that some of the most extended classes in the library are present also in the namespaced version, so they can be used before upgrading to the fully namespaced version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to update a simple project, where the only usage of PHPUnit classes is to create tests, you are very lucky. You need to require at &lt;strong&gt;minimum PHPUnit 4.8.35 or 5.4.3&lt;/strong&gt;, which includes the FC class &lt;code&gt;PHPUnit\Framework\TestCase&lt;/code&gt; as an alias for &lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit_Framework_TestCase&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should choose the &lt;strong&gt;newest version as possible&lt;/strong&gt;, and that depends on which minimum version of PHP you want to support: if you work with (at least) PHP 5.6, you can use PHPUnit 5, otherwise you&amp;rsquo;re forced to use version 4.8.35. If you&amp;rsquo;re working on a (open source) library that needs to support both, you can do this in your &lt;code&gt;composer.json&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;{
  &amp;quot;require-dev&amp;quot;: {
    &amp;quot;phpunit/phpunit&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;^4.8.35|^5.4.0&amp;quot;  
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way you can use both, and Composer will choose the most updated one, depending on which PHP version you are using; this is &lt;strong&gt;pretty useful for testing with a CI tool&lt;/strong&gt; like Travis, since you should run your tests at least on the lowest and highest versions of PHP that you want to support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have required and installed the right version, the only modification that you need to do in your code is this one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;?php

class MyTest extends \PHPUnit_Framework_TestCase
{
    // ...
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;?php

use PHPUnit\Framework\TestCase;

class MyTest extends TestCase
{
    // ...
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;deprecations-of-phpunit-4&#34;&gt;Deprecations of PHPUnit 4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on your codebase, you may be forced to do one last step: your tests may be &lt;strong&gt;using deprecated methods from PHPUnit 4&lt;/strong&gt;, so you will need to fix those. Those issues are pretty easy to be found and fixed, because they will make your test fail when executed with PHPUnit 5. The full list of changes that may impact you are in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sebastianbergmann/phpunit/blob/5.7/ChangeLog-5.0.md#500---2015-10-02&#34;&gt;changelog for version 5.0.0&lt;/a&gt;, but the most notable ones are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you need to declare a whitelist in your &lt;code&gt;phpunit.xml&lt;/code&gt; configuration file to collect tests coverage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you must drop any usage of the &lt;code&gt;assertSelectCount()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;assertSelectRegExp()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;assertSelectEquals()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;assertTag()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;assertNotTag()&lt;/code&gt; assertions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bumpy-one-implementing-a-testlistener&#34;&gt;The bumpy one: implementing a TestListener&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If in your project you extend other classes or interfaces from PHPUnit, you need to check which one. If we are talking about one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit_Framework_Assert&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit_Framework_AssertionFailedError&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit_Framework_Test&lt;/code&gt; (interface)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit_Framework_TestSuite&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; then your only requirement is to &lt;strong&gt;use at least PHPUnit 5.7.21&lt;/strong&gt;. This means that you have to drop support to any PHP version older than 5.6, if you still support it (and you should!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, instead, you implement a &lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit_Framework_TestListener&lt;/code&gt;, that may be a little trickier. The FC layer for that class is &lt;strong&gt;problematic&lt;/strong&gt;, since it&amp;rsquo;s an interface that has a lot of types applied to the methods&amp;rsquo; arguments; this, combined with the fact that in PHP you cannot change the type of an argument when extending (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Covariance_and_contravariance_(computer_science)&#34;&gt;covariance and contravariance&lt;/a&gt;), means that the FC class is nearly useless: &lt;strong&gt;you cannot be compatible with both&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit_Framework_TestListener&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit\Framework\TestListener&lt;/code&gt; with the same class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are working on a &lt;strong&gt;single project&lt;/strong&gt;, you may just restrict the supported PHPUnit version and jump to the newest one while upgrading the listener too. But if you are working on a library, and you do not want to apply that restriction to your end users, it gets a little complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, while upgrading &lt;code&gt;facile-it/paraunit&lt;/code&gt;, I preferred &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/issues/54#issuecomment-302906556&#34;&gt;jumping from supporting 4.x/5.x directly to 6.x&lt;/a&gt;; Paraunit works directly on top of PHPUnit, and it works the same before and after this update (apart from new features), so &lt;strong&gt;dropping the old versions altogether&lt;/strong&gt; seemed a good enough approach for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other cases, the listener is just provided as an additional help of the main library, so &lt;strong&gt;forcing the end user&lt;/strong&gt; to update his version of PHPUnit alongside with our library could be &lt;strong&gt;too harsh&lt;/strong&gt; or slow down the adoption of the new release. I tried doing this on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/FriendsOfSymfony/FOSHttpCache/pull/365&#34;&gt;with a pull reques on &lt;code&gt;friendsofsymfony/http-cache&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, where I had to solve this specific issue. The &lt;strong&gt;only feasible solution&lt;/strong&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;ve found is this &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/symfony/phpunit-bridge/blob/3c0efb8609a32890a767bbbd39198a0e92572694/SymfonyTestsListener.php#L19&#34;&gt;specific snippet of code&lt;/a&gt;, that it was used in &lt;code&gt;symfony/phpunit-bridge&lt;/code&gt; to overcome the same problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;if (
    class_exists(&#39;PHPUnit_Runner_Version&#39;) 
    &amp;amp;&amp;amp; version_compare(\PHPUnit_Runner_Version::id(), &#39;6.0.0&#39;, &#39;&amp;lt;&#39;)
) {
    class_alias(&#39;Legacy\MyTestListener&#39;, &#39;MyTestListener&#39;);
// Using an early return instead of a else does not work 
// when using the PHPUnit phar due to some weird PHP behavior 
// (the class gets defined without executing the code before it 
// and so the definition is not properly conditional)
} else {
    class MyTestListener extends BaseTestListener
    {
        // ...
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach is based on writing two versions of the listener, one (inside a &lt;code&gt;legacy&lt;/code&gt; subfolder) which implements the old interface, the other that implements the new, namespaced one. With the above snippet, PHP is tricked into loading the right one, after checking if the loaded version of PHPUnit is lower than 6.0. In this way &lt;strong&gt;the end user can ignore the difference between the two classes&lt;/strong&gt;, use only the new class name and go on, since they will be switched in a hidden and automatic way.
Once support for the old PHP and PHPUnit versions is dropped, this trick can be dropped too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-next-step-from-5-to-6&#34;&gt;The next step: from 5 to 6&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once all this migration is completed, and all the tests are green under all needed conditions, we can plan for the next step, &lt;strong&gt;upgrading to PHPUnit 6&lt;/strong&gt;. In reality, this step depends on a bigger, previous step: &lt;strong&gt;migrate to PHP 7&lt;/strong&gt;, because lower versions are no longer supported with PHPUnit 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When your project is ready for PHP 7, you can require the installation of PHPUnit 6; if you are working on a library that wants to support PHP 5.6 too, you can use the same trick as above in your &lt;code&gt;composer.json&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;{
  &amp;quot;require-dev&amp;quot;: {
    &amp;quot;phpunit/phpunit&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;^5.4.0|^6.0&amp;quot;  
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; so you&amp;rsquo;ll be using PHPUnit 5 under PHP 5.6, and 6 with PHP 7.0+. As before, you need to check that your tests are still passing, and avoid using any functionality that is deprecated in PHPUnit 5. You can find the full list in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sebastianbergmann/phpunit/blob/6.0/ChangeLog-6.0.md#600---2017-02-03&#34;&gt;PHPUnit changelog for 6.0.0&lt;/a&gt;, but the most notable are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;getMock()&lt;/code&gt; must be replaced with &lt;code&gt;createMock()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;usages of &lt;code&gt;getMockWithoutInvokingTheOriginalConstructor()&lt;/code&gt; are no longer needed, it&amp;rsquo;s the default behavior now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if you intervene on global variables, it&amp;rsquo;s better to enable the &lt;code&gt;--globals-backup&lt;/code&gt; option, to save and restore them between tests (previously it was the default behavior)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;setExpectedException()&lt;/code&gt; must be replaced:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;// before
$this-&amp;gt;setExpectedException(Exception::class, $message);
// after
$this-&amp;gt;expectException(Exception::class);
$this-&amp;gt;expectExceptionMessage($message);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s all! I hope to make you save enough time and migraines with this little guide. Happy coding!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why type hints and interfaces are not visual debt</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/visual-debt-typehints/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/visual-debt-typehints/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago I stumbled on a strange tweet that was highlighting a controversy about scalar type hints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;it&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Scalar type hints &amp;amp; return types vs no scalar type hints &amp;amp; return types is &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/PHP?src=hash&#34;&gt;#PHP&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s new spaces vs tabs&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Cees-Jan ðŸ”Š Kiewiet (@WyriHaximus) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/WyriHaximus/status/865524687257862144&#34;&gt;19 maggio 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After asking references about this, someone alluded to this very short video: &lt;a href=&#34;https://laracasts.com/series/php-bits/episodes/1&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;PHP Bits: Visual Debt&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (it&amp;rsquo;s only 3 minutes, please watch it before continue reading). After that, the author of the video was dragged into the conversation, and it blew up into a big tweetstorm in the following few hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core of the controversy was the fact that the author of the video classified as &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;visual debt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; a lot of stuff in his PHP example, like interfaces, scalar type hints and the final keyword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-opinion-on-the-matter&#34;&gt;My opinion on the matter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can agree with the bottom line of the video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am I necessarily getting a benefit [&amp;hellip;] ?  Question everything&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every choice in our line of work is always a &lt;strong&gt;trade-off&lt;/strong&gt; between benefits and cons, and every new introduction in a projects should be evaluated and agreed upon between team members. But my personal preference leans a lot towards the opposite side in this specific matter: as I stated in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/how-php-7-tdd-helped-me-sleep-better/&#34;&gt;previous blog post here&lt;/a&gt;, I love the new additions that PHP 7 brought to us like scalar and return type hints, and I use them as often as I can, because I discovered that &lt;strong&gt;they bring a lot of benefits&lt;/strong&gt; to the code that I write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably this was influenced by the fact that previously I worked with C++, where types are a lot more intrusive compared with PHP 5; but over time and with usage, I learned the great benefits that we can achieve with this addition to our PHP 7 codebases. In general, I think that type hints, and other language features that create a more &amp;ldquo;rigid&amp;rdquo; code, are &lt;strong&gt;helpful during the evolution of a codebase&lt;/strong&gt;, and so they are really needed in long-running projects, where the maintainability of code is crucial. It may be less true in a &amp;ldquo;release and forget&amp;rdquo; type of project, but I think that it would still be like betting againt oneself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post I would like to explain myself and the reasons behind my arguments, recounting them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;scalar-type-hints-as-safeguards&#34;&gt;Scalar type hints as safeguards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the video, the example had all along this class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;class Event implements EventInterface
{
    protected $events = [];
    
    public function listen(string $name, callable $handler): void
    {
        $this-&amp;gt;events[$name][] = $handler;
    }

    public function fire(string $name): bool
    {
        if (! array_key_exists($name, $this-&amp;gt;events)) {
            return false;
        }
        
        foreach($this-&amp;gt;events[$name] as $event) {
            $event();
        }

        return true;
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author suggests to remove all type hints, since the code should still work and you could get rid of a lot of additional, not needed complications. I disagree completely with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type hints are safeguards&lt;/strong&gt; here, because they let you reduce to the bare minimum all the checks that you should do here before accepting the input arguments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;because it&amp;rsquo;s used as a key for an array, &lt;code&gt;$name&lt;/code&gt; can only be a string (or an int, but it would not make sense)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;code&gt;events&lt;/code&gt; property can only accept callables, because its elements are invoked inside the foreach of the &lt;code&gt;fire()&lt;/code&gt; method&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;because we don&amp;rsquo;t need to insert additional &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt;s in our methods, we &lt;strong&gt;reduce the number of possible paths of execution&lt;/strong&gt;, hence reducing the number of cases that we need to check in our tests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;type-hints-and-interfaces-as-contracts&#34;&gt;Type hints and interfaces as contracts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the video, it was suggested to also get rid of the interface:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;interface EventInterface
{
    public function listen(string $name, callable $handler): void;

    public function fire(string $name): bool;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree that &lt;strong&gt;an interface should be written only if needed&lt;/strong&gt;, like if you want to write multiple concrete implementation of it with different inheritance hierarchy. But this doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that we will not have any interface at all: we still have the concrete implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not the same of having a pure interface, but we will still be able to determine a &lt;strong&gt;contract&lt;/strong&gt;, a list of method signatures that tells us what that object will accept as valid method calls. This kind of contracts are a must in object oriented programming, because they dictate how your object will interconnect, communicate and cooperate, and they are especially useful in combination with stricter type hints and &lt;strong&gt;unit testing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we write unit test, we use the real instance of the class which is under test, and everything else should be mocked. That means that we will use some test mocking library (i.e. I prefer &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/phpspec/prophecy&#34;&gt;Prophecy&lt;/a&gt;, which is included in PHPUnit) to mimick the behavior of nearby objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How type hints would help us in this case? If we would have to mock the &lt;code&gt;EventInterface&lt;/code&gt; (or the concrete class, it&amp;rsquo;s unimportant here), having the return type hints for example would help us in &lt;strong&gt;writing good mocks&lt;/strong&gt;, and not wrong ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how? Nearly every mocking library creates a mock extending at runtime the original class, since the mock needs to pass every check and type hint as if it was the original class; this means that it can&amp;rsquo;t change the method signature, hence preserving the original return type hint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will translate in errors and test failures if we would write a mock that doesn&amp;rsquo;t return the proper type, like in this example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;class Person
{
    public function shout(): bool
    {
        $event = new Event();
        if ($event-&amp;gt;fire(&#39;shout&#39;)) {
            // someone was listening!
            return true;
        }
        // ...
    }
}

class PersonTest extends PHPUnit\Framework\TestCase
{
    public function testShout()
    {
        $event = $this-&amp;gt;prophesize(EventInterface::class);
        $event-&amp;gt;fire(&#39;shout&#39;)
            -&amp;gt;shouldBeCalled();
        // ...
        
        $person = new Person();
        $person-&amp;gt;shout();
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34;&gt;$ phpunit
# ...
1) PersonTest::testShout
TypeError: Return value of Double\EventInterface\P2118::fire() must be a string, null returned
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mock, once used, &lt;strong&gt;will make the test fail&lt;/strong&gt;. Why? Because the &lt;code&gt;fire()&lt;/code&gt; method can only return a boolean, and by default (if not instructed differently) Prophecy&amp;rsquo;s mocks will return &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt;. Without the &lt;code&gt;: bool&lt;/code&gt; return type hint, the mock would return &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt; but the test would not fail, and the class under test would silently cast or interpret the return value as &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;, possibly causing an unintended behavior or a false positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that having complete type hints in your interfaces and method signatures only &lt;strong&gt;makes your code more cohesive and your unit test more robust&lt;/strong&gt;; this kind of enforcing helps a lot also with refactoring, since changing a method&amp;rsquo;s signature would cause failures in all the related tests that include a mock of that interface, as it could become inconsistent and unreliable after this change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;use-interfaces-as-behavior-checks&#34;&gt;Use interfaces as behavior checks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the counter example that popped up during the discussion on Twitter was this one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;class Fireman
{
    // ...
}

class Building
{
    public function putOutFire(Fireman $fireman);
}

$building-&amp;gt;putOutFire(new StrongAndAblePerson()); // type error!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was cited to show how sometimes type hints can be a hindrance more that something helpful in your code: why a strong, capable person shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to put out a fire? Who&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;code&gt;Building&lt;/code&gt; class to decide that? Are we maybe violating the Single Responsibility Principle?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that this is misguided for a simple reason: it was &lt;strong&gt;wrong to check against a concrete implementation&lt;/strong&gt; instead of an interface; and that&amp;rsquo;s not evident because, in my opinion, the example was &lt;strong&gt;cut too short&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s speculate on the content of the &lt;code&gt;putOutFire()&lt;/code&gt; method:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;class Building
{
    public function putOutFire(Fireman $fireman)
    {
        $fireman-&amp;gt;wearProtectiveGear();
        $fireman-&amp;gt;shootWaterAtFlames();
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why we have a type hint in the &lt;code&gt;putOutFire()&lt;/code&gt; method? Surely because we want to rely on some method that a &lt;code&gt;Fireman&lt;/code&gt; instance would give to us in the method body (i.e. the &lt;code&gt;wearProtectiveGear()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;shootWaterAtFlames()&lt;/code&gt;); if we remove the type hint, we would have no guarantees that those methods exists on the argument, and we would have to either use a &lt;code&gt;method_exists()&lt;/code&gt; call twice (oh, the horror!) or expose our &lt;code&gt;Building&lt;/code&gt; class to a possible fatal error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take the example further, we can make the &lt;code&gt;StrongAndAblePerson&lt;/code&gt; capable of put out a fire if we &lt;strong&gt;extract the needed methods in an interface&lt;/strong&gt;, defining a contract of what our &lt;code&gt;putOutFire()&lt;/code&gt; needs to know and use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;interface TrainedFireFighter
{
    public function wearProtectiveGear(): void;
    public function shootWaterAtFlames(): void;
}

class StrongAndAblePerson implements TrainedFireFighter { ... }
class Fireman implements TrainedFireFighter { ... }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; now we can have the &lt;code&gt;putOutFire()&lt;/code&gt; method with a broader type hint, that would accept both a &lt;code&gt;Fireman&lt;/code&gt; and any other class that implements the &lt;code&gt;TrainedFireFighter&lt;/code&gt; interface:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;class Building
{
    public function putOutFire(TrainedFireFighter $firefighter)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-final-keyword&#34;&gt;The final keyword&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only point of the video which I find relatable is the remark on the &lt;code&gt;final&lt;/code&gt; keyword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the funny joke (&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m not your daddy!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;), I find the final keyword &lt;strong&gt;not very usable in closed projects&lt;/strong&gt;, since its only usefulness is to impede the extension of some object. When the persons that could work on a codebase are well known and they can be coordinated, I think it&amp;rsquo;s better to leave that liberty to the coders, and just have an agreement on what can and cannot be done with that class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, this keyword becomes useful when we are talking about &lt;strong&gt;open sourced code&lt;/strong&gt;: using it is a clear statement that reduces the surface of the API that the library is exposing to end users, in the same way &lt;code&gt;private&lt;/code&gt; is limiting access to properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Straightforwardly, the maintainer of the code is saying that this class is not extensible, because it may change internally without notice; this concept is also well explained by Marco Pivetta in his signature &amp;ldquo;Extremely defensive PHP&amp;rdquo; talk (which we cited also in our &lt;a href=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/php-day-2017/&#34;&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ocramius.github.io/extremely-defensive-php/#/90&#34;&gt;see related slide here&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://ocramius.github.io/blog/when-to-declare-classes-final/&#34;&gt;in his blog post about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-practical-example&#34;&gt;A practical example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to conclude this blog post with a practical example. I maintain &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/&#34;&gt;facile-it/paraunit&lt;/a&gt;, a parallelization tool that works on top of PHPUnit. In the past few days I was working on supporting PHPUnit v6, and that lead to bumping the minimum PHP supported version of the package to 7.0: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/pull/93&#34;&gt;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/pull/93&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since previously the minimum supported version was PHP 5.3, I took the opportunity to go over the whole codebase and clean it up, using all the new language features that I could now take for granted: &lt;code&gt;::class&lt;/code&gt; shortcuts, array short syntax, but more importantly the aforementioned &lt;strong&gt;scalar and return type hints&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the perfect example to show that adding those type hints on already working code made a &lt;strong&gt;non-trivial difference&lt;/strong&gt; even if I wasn&amp;rsquo;t changing the objects&amp;rsquo; behavior, and it forced me to fix some of this stuff:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it forced me &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/pull/93/files#diff-049f05e192bb0dcb9cf59ad2bbd43ceaR79&#34;&gt;to define more explicitly a default behavior&lt;/a&gt;, since a &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt; was no longer accepted in place of a string&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this also lead me to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/pull/93/commits/6aa9286256ed47c7b4500b990e030588b18b7770&#34;&gt;write an additional test&lt;/a&gt; for an uncovered, very common case&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it made me realize that I had &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/pull/93/files#diff-f3225dfaa1d4e63e21a7e51880c63bbbR40&#34;&gt;a regex silently failing&lt;/a&gt; returning a bad result, and I had to take better care of it, leading to a simpler and more robust approach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this lead to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/pull/93/commits/b5463b122e87f14dbaf6fa2ff78ba53f14ae737a#diff-59b76fc4702a8549daa568e542d71498R42&#34;&gt;additional tests too&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it made me discover a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/pull/93/commits/61c786c6faa0020465abd8243ee1415883193a94#diff-4fd831bf7fb1767a7a49e0954a98fb05R98&#34;&gt;specific behavior of the SPL file iterator classes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;strict-types-enforcing&#34;&gt;Strict types enforcing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last part of this PR, I also added the &lt;code&gt;declare(strict_types=1)&lt;/code&gt; directive everywhere in my code. This directive changes the behavior of type hints: with it, passed values are no longer silently casted (if possible) to the type-hinted, required type, but instead they &lt;strong&gt;trigger an immediate error if the type doesn&amp;rsquo;t match&lt;/strong&gt;; for example, passing a &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;10&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; string into a &lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;float&lt;/code&gt; type hint will no longer trigger an automatic conversion to &lt;code&gt;10&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;10.0&lt;/code&gt;, but trigger an error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would admit that this is a matter of personal preference, and I would not suggest to use this everywhere, especially if there isn&amp;rsquo;t a very thorough test coverage; it may lead to unneeded failures in very unsuspecting places, and it may cause friction when intergrating code with external libraries that take advantage of the implicit type casting that PHP has always done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even in this little use case, &lt;a href=&#34;https://travis-ci.org/facile-it/paraunit/jobs/236293288&#34;&gt;it lead to discover a small issue&lt;/a&gt; with an outdated test code, were I was &lt;strong&gt;passing an empty string instead of a boolean&lt;/strong&gt;: that happened because I refactored a constructor some time ago, and I forgot to update the tests, and I missed it since the &lt;strong&gt;tests were not failing&lt;/strong&gt;. The error was even well highlighted by my IDE now, but before it was casted silently to a bool, and it matched the expected behavior by sheer luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/visual-debt-typehints/phpstorm-error-highlight.png&#34; alt=&#34;The error highlighted in PHPStorm&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Type hints and other new PHP language construct help writing more cohesive, rigid code, that may lead to some &amp;ldquo;pain&amp;rdquo; while writing code and (mostly) tests; but this effort is just &lt;strong&gt;paying in advance&lt;/strong&gt;: a lot of bugs get discovered earlier, and refactoring and changing code become easier, since pieces of code that doesn&amp;rsquo;t match anymore are more visible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the example PR, the amount of changed code that is not method signatures is trivial, but I drastically reduced the amount of possible deviations that my code could take if a wrong value is passed through it, and I fixed and tested a few additional cases that I was forgetting about. Also, the usage of the &lt;code&gt;declare(strict_types=1)&lt;/code&gt; enforces even further this approach, raising the confidence that I have in the codebase.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Facile.it devs @ phpDay 2017</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/php-day-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/php-day-2017/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Like clockwork, on May we head up to Verona to attend the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://2017.phpday.it/&#34;&gt;phpDay conference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;; this time it was on &lt;strong&gt;May 12th and 13th&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We met a lot of new people and known fellow PHP developers, and like &lt;a href=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/php-day-2015/&#34;&gt;previous&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/php-day-2016/&#34;&gt;years&lt;/a&gt;, we wanted to write down a light summary; like the previous ones, this won&amp;rsquo;t be a full &amp;ldquo;review&amp;rdquo; of the conference, but an highlight of the talks that captured most of our attention, or what we found more valuable for our everyday work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope to give a brief glimpse of what we experienced to fellow developers that hadn&amp;rsquo;t the opportunity to attend, and to tempt some of you to join conferences like this one or those in the PHP community at large, for your personal and professional growth. Like last year, we will later edit this article embedding the videos of the talks, when they will got released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;it&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Are you wondering how the first day of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/phpDay?src=hash&#34;&gt;#phpDay&lt;/a&gt; went? That was amazing! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/6630Zguq1Q&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/6630Zguq1Q&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; phpDay by GrUSP (@phpday) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/phpday/status/863314622656458753&#34;&gt;13 maggio 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talks are in chronological order, and we linked the slides when available. Enjoy your reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;technical-talks&#34;&gt;Technical Talks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;climbing-the-abstract-syntax-tree&#34;&gt;Climbing the Abstract Syntax Tree&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;James Titcumb (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/asgrim&#34;&gt;@asgrim&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1 - 11:00 â€“ 12:00 - track 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk started a bit complicated, since it tackles a very complex matter: the Abstract Syntax Tree that has been added to PHP since version 7, and it the implications of its use; following up a bit, it included some very easy, low level example of how the language works with the AST, and the fact that the example were in PHP itself helped a lot in increasing the understanding of the matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;managing-dependencies-is-more-than-running-composer-update&#34;&gt;Managing dependencies is more than running &amp;ldquo;composer update&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nils Adermann (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/naderman&#34;&gt;@naderman&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1 - 15:30 â€“ 16:30 - track 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nils is one of the co-authors of Composer, but this talk was about &amp;ldquo;dependencies&amp;rdquo; in general, not just about the literal, software ones: every software project has a lot of dependecies apart from the libs that we install in the vendor folder, and he explained how we should approach them, and how we should mitigate the risks that they can add to our work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-science-of-code-reviews&#34;&gt;The Science of Code Reviews&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rick Kuipers (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rskuipers&#34;&gt;@rskuipers&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - 12:00 â€“ 13:00 - track 2 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/rskuipers/the-science-of-code-reviews&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code reviews and pair programming are two very valuable tools that we can leverage in our work as developers. This talk was really interesting, and it started from reasons behind why do them, up to suggestions and tips on how to improve them if you already do in your team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;extremely-defensive-php&#34;&gt;Extremely defensive PHP&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marco Pivetta (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ocramius&#34;&gt;@ocramius&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - 15:30 â€“ 16:30 - track 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marco gave this talk already a lot of times on some conferences and some user groups, but it&amp;rsquo;s great! He suggests how to write code in a &amp;ldquo;defensive&amp;rdquo; way, to avoid that others are able to do mistakes with it and create problems down the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;keynotes&#34;&gt;Keynotes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-manifesto&#34;&gt;Code Manifesto&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graham Daniels (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/greydnls&#34;&gt;@greydnls&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1 - 09:45 â€“ 10:45&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first keynote wasn&amp;rsquo;t strictly technical, but it was still more than interesting: Graham guided us through how much inequality and hidden problems minorities (and especially women) have to face everyday in our line of work; Graham is also the author behind the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/greydnls/code-manifesto&#34;&gt;Code Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;, a basic list of principles to be followed on OSS and workplaces to actively fight this issues and encourage diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;noestimates-the-10-new-principles-for-software-projects-predicting-without-estimating&#34;&gt;NoEstimates: The 10 new principles for Software Projects - predicting without estimating&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vasco Duarte (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/duarte_vasco&#34;&gt;@duarte_vasco&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - 09:45 â€“ 10:45&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vasco is the famous author of the #NoEstimate strategy, and his keynote was aimed at explaining the wrong things the foundation of the issues of our industry, where estimates are always wrong and are often used to &amp;ldquo;bet&amp;rdquo; the future of our companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-open-source-for-fun-and-profit&#34;&gt;Using Open Source for Fun and Profit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gary Hockin (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/geeh&#34;&gt;@geeh&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - 17:30 â€“ 18:30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his keynote, Gary told us his story of how, from a simple developer, he became a Zend contributor first, and the JetBrains Developer Advocate now; the basic lessons that we can take from his experience is that open source contributions (no matter how small) are good for your career, and that when you give to the community, the community will give back to you very soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/phpday-2017/facile-engineering-team-phpday-2017.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;The Facile.it engineering team at PHPDay 2017&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>#FacileHack 2017, 10 days later</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/facilehack-2017-10-days-later/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/facilehack-2017-10-days-later/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Ten days ago &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackathon.facile.it/2017.html&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;#FacileHack 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; came to its conclusion; this was the second edition of the hackathon organized by Facile.it. Holding an event of this kind has allowed us to see, work and discuss with many very diverse teams, made up of programmers, designers and marketers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hackathon&amp;rsquo;s theme for this year was &lt;strong&gt;connectivity&lt;/strong&gt;: our site offers the comparation between internet access services, and we have decided to put this at the center of the competition. The teams have then faced each other on this theme, searching new ways to improve Facile.it&amp;rsquo;s business and the customers&amp;rsquo; user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;continuous-improvement&#34;&gt;Continuous improvement&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience we gained from the first edition allowed us to easily organize this event, and as we like to apply ourselves in our everyday work, we wanted to aim for a continuous and progressive improvement in organizing this hackathon, and this proved to be a winning approach.
Â Â 
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/X-OdVcH7CMs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the improving point of this edition was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackathon.facile.it/2017.html#giuria&#34;&gt;external jury&lt;/a&gt; composed by very experienced professionals of different expertise. Despite the very few minutes available (only seven) to the various teams to present their ideas, the jurors were very good at analyzing the various proposals and to offer the right questions to dissect the critical points of each proposed approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-winning-team&#34;&gt;The winning team&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team that won the competition was &lt;strong&gt;Orange Smile&lt;/strong&gt;, proposing Facilino, a virtual assistant: the team&amp;rsquo;s merit was especially in the overall completeness of the proposed solution, which started from identifying the problems and proposing a solution up to its application and its launch to the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/facilehack-2017-10-giorni-dopo/orange-smile.jpg&#34; title=&#34;I vincitori di #FacileHack 2017: team Orange Smile&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winners were awarded a â‚¬ 500 voucher, for each team member, to be spent on high-level professional training courses made available by our partners &lt;a href=&#34;https: //www.enter .com / en / ecosystem / education /&#34;&gt;LOG.ED&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ninjacademy.it/&#34;&gt;Ninja Academy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fluentify.com/&#34;&gt;Fluentify&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;The focus on training&lt;/strong&gt; seemed like an important decision for us and in line with the spirit of our engineering division.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you to the next edition!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center; margin-bottom: 2em&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/facilehack-2017-10-giorni-dopo/facile-engineering-team.jpg&#34; title=&#34;FacileHack engineering team&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>#FacileHack 2017, 10 giorni dopo</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/facilehack-2017-10-giorni-dopo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/facilehack-2017-10-giorni-dopo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Dieci giorni fa Ã¨ terminato &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackathon.facile.it/2017.html&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;#FacileHack 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, la seconda edizione dell&amp;rsquo;hackathon organizzato da Facile.it. Tenere un evento di questo genere ci ha permesso di vedere all&amp;rsquo;opera e di confrontarci con tanti team molto eterogenei, composti da programmatori, designer e specialisti del marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il tema dell&amp;rsquo;hackathon di quest&amp;rsquo;anno Ã¨ stata la &lt;strong&gt;connettivitÃ &lt;/strong&gt;: il nostro portale propone la comparazione dei servizi di connessione ad internet, e ha deciso di porre questo al centro della competizione. I diversi team si sono quindi affrontati su questo tema, per trovare modi per migliorare il business di Facile.it e l&amp;rsquo;esperienza utente degli utilizzatori del servizio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;miglioramento-continuo&#34;&gt;Miglioramento continuo&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;L&amp;rsquo;esperienza accumulata dalla prima edizione ci ha permesso di realizzare con facilitÃ  questo evento: cosÃ¬ come ci piace applicarci nel nostro lavoro di tutti i giorni, abbiamo voluto ricercare un miglioramento continuo e progressivo anche nell&amp;rsquo;organizzare un hackathon, e questo si Ã¨ rivelato un approccio vincente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/X-OdVcH7CMs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uno dei punti che piÃ¹ ci ha convinto di questa edizione Ã¨ stata la &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackathon.facile.it/2017.html#giuria&#34;&gt;giuria esterna&lt;/a&gt; composta da professionisti molto esperti di diversi settori. Nonostante i pochi minuti (soltanto sette) a disposizione dei vari team per presentare la propria idea, Ã¨ stata molto brava ad analizzare le varie soluzioni ed a proporre le giuste domande per sviscerare i punti critici di ogni approccio presentato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;il-team-vincente&#34;&gt;Il team vincente&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il team che ha vinto la competizione Ã¨ stato &lt;strong&gt;Orange Smile&lt;/strong&gt;, con la proposta dell&amp;rsquo;assistente virtuale Facilino: la vittoria del team Ã¨ stata decretata soprattutto dalla completezza della soluzione proposta, che andava dall&amp;rsquo;individuazione dei problemi, alla proposta di una soluzione, fino all&amp;rsquo;applicazione e al lancio sul mercato della stessa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/facilehack-2017-10-giorni-dopo/orange-smile.jpg&#34; title=&#34;I vincitori di #FacileHack 2017: team Orange Smile&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I vincitori si sono aggiudicati come premio un voucher del valore di 500 euro, per ogni componente della squadra, da spendere in formazione professionale attraverso i corsi di alto livello messi a disposizione dai partner &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.enter.it/it/ecosystem/education/&#34;&gt;LOG.ED&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ninjacademy.it/&#34;&gt;Ninja Academy&lt;/a&gt; e &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fluentify.com/&#34;&gt;Fluentify&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Puntare sulla formazione&lt;/strong&gt; ci Ã¨ sembrata una scelta importante e in linea con lo spirito della nostra divisione engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E alla fine non possiamo che salutarvi e aspettarvi per la prossima edizione!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center; margin-bottom: 2em&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/facilehack-2017-10-giorni-dopo/facile-engineering-team.jpg&#34; title=&#34;FacileHack engineering team&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>#FacileHack 2017 ci siamo quasi</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/facilehack-2017-ci-siamo-quasi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/facilehack-2017-ci-siamo-quasi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/facilehack-2017-ci-siamo-quasi/share.png&#34; alt=&#34;FacileHack&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mancano meno di 4 giorni alla seconda edizione di &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackathon.facile.it/2017.html&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;#FacileHack&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, la maratona dedicata a coders, creativi e marketing specialist organizzata dalla nostra azienda che si svolgerÃ  a Milano presso il Talent Garden di via Arcivescovo Calabiana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attesa grande partecipazione all&amp;rsquo;evento anche da fuori Italia, le registrazioni sono state chiuse per sold-out all&amp;rsquo;inizio di questo mese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In meno di 24 ore gli &lt;em&gt;hackers&lt;/em&gt; partecipanti dovranno confrontarsi, mettendo a dura prova le proprie capacitÃ  fisiche e creative, per presentare un&amp;rsquo;idea o un prototipo in grado di ottenere il punteggio massimo della &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackathon.facile.it/2017.html#giuria&#34;&gt;giuria&lt;/a&gt; di qualitÃ .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saranno &lt;strong&gt;Cristina Bianchini&lt;/strong&gt; (Vodafone Italia), &lt;strong&gt;Fabio Lalli&lt;/strong&gt; (IQUII), &lt;strong&gt;Deborah Raccagni&lt;/strong&gt; (UniversitÃ  Bocconi), &lt;strong&gt;Moreno Soppelsa&lt;/strong&gt; (Giornalista) e il nostro &lt;strong&gt;Mauro Giacobbe&lt;/strong&gt; (Facile.it), i componenti della giuria che avrÃ  l&amp;rsquo;arduo compito di valutare il lavoro dei partecipanti all&amp;rsquo;hackathon sulla base di quattro criteri: attinenza alla sfida proposta, fattibilitÃ  tecnica, UI/UX e creativitÃ .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il team proclamato vincitore di #FacileHack 2017 riceverÃ  in premio un voucher del valore di 500 euro, per ogni componente della squadra, da spendere in formazione professionale attraverso i corsi di alto livello messi a disposizione dai partner &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.enter.it/it/ecosystem/education/&#34;&gt;LOG.ED&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ninjacademy.it/&#34;&gt;Ninja Academy&lt;/a&gt; e &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fluentify.com/&#34;&gt;Fluentify&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non ci rimane che augurare buon #FacileHack da tutti noi!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Kotlin type-safe builders to create a DSL for Forms</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/kotlin-dsl/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/kotlin-dsl/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Here at Facile.it we are constantly dealing with a lot of &lt;strong&gt;forms&lt;/strong&gt;: we use them to collect various information and data needed to feed our in-house comparing algorithms. These forms could be &lt;strong&gt;really complex&lt;/strong&gt;, having multiple rules and dependencies between fields, and they are likely to be &lt;strong&gt;changed and tuned frequently&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I joined Facile.it, a lot of forms within the Android app needed to be updated or modified and sticking with the existing strategy would have required me to do &lt;strong&gt;a lot of work&lt;/strong&gt; just to add or remove a simple field. So I took a step back and I started thinking about a strategy that would have allowed me to define and structure a form in a more &lt;em&gt;flexible&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;declarative&lt;/em&gt; way. I wanted to be able to declare the &lt;strong&gt;relationships&lt;/strong&gt; between fields, their &lt;strong&gt;validation rules&lt;/strong&gt; and their &lt;strong&gt;serialized representation&lt;/strong&gt; (how they are sent to the server).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I firstly thought about defining it using some configuration file, maybe written in JSON or YAML. The &lt;em&gt;problem&lt;/em&gt; with this strategy was that it would also have required me to write a lot code to parse and validate those files to be able to create some sort of representation of the form in Java&amp;hellip;but don&amp;rsquo;t we already have the compiler for this kind of jobs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still wanted to be able to have both a &lt;strong&gt;human readable representation&lt;/strong&gt; of the form and the right degree of &lt;strong&gt;flexibility&lt;/strong&gt; to integrate the form definition into the app code.
So I thought that creating a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Domain-specific_language&#34;&gt;Domain-Specific Language&lt;/a&gt; would have been a perfect strategy to solve the problem in an elegant and efficient way.
Writing a DSL in Java could have ended up into something like that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34;&gt;Form.create()
    .openSection(sectionId)
    .field(key1, &amp;quot;label1&amp;quot;, style, ...) 
    .field(key2, &amp;quot;label2&amp;quot;, style, ...) 
    .field(key3, &amp;quot;label3&amp;quot;, style, ...) 
    .closeSection()
    ...
    .build()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think the previous code is readable nor flexible and it requires a lot of boilerplate to be written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;kotlin-to-the-rescue&#34;&gt;Kotlin to the rescue!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike Java, Kotlin (take a look at my &lt;a href=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/kotlin-intro/&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; about it) has a lot of features that makes it really powerful when it comes to write internal DSLs. The results are very similar to Groovy (think about a Gradle file) but thanks to its type system they could be &lt;a href=&#34;https://kotlinlang.org/docs/reference/type-safe-builders.html#type-safe-builders&#34;&gt;Type-Safe&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The builders you can write with Kotlin are extremely readable and easy to understand even for people that don&amp;rsquo;t know either the language or the DSL itself. Here&amp;rsquo;s how a form built using my final DSL looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-kotlin&#34;&gt;val FORM = form {
    page(&amp;quot;Page 1 Title&amp;quot;) {
        section(&amp;quot;Section 1 Title&amp;quot;) {
            field(key = &amp;quot;fieldKey1&amp;quot;) {
                checkbox(&amp;quot;Checkbox Field Label&amp;quot;) {
                    boolToStringConverter = { if (it == true) &amp;quot;Yes&amp;quot; else &amp;quot;No&amp;quot; }
                    rules = { listOf(NotMissing()) }
                }
            }
            field(key = &amp;quot;fieldKey2&amp;quot;) {
                picker(&amp;quot;Picker Field Label&amp;quot;) {
                    placeHolder = &amp;quot;Select a value&amp;quot;
                    possibleValues = Available(listOf(
                            1 keyTo &amp;quot;Value1&amp;quot;,
                            2 keyTo &amp;quot;Value2&amp;quot;,
                            3 keyTo &amp;quot;Value3&amp;quot;))
                    representation = IF_VISIBLE representAs SIMPLE_KEY_TO_VALUE
                }
            }
        }
        section(&amp;quot;Section 2 Title&amp;quot;) {
            field(key = &amp;quot;fieldKey3&amp;quot;) {
                picker(&amp;quot;Picker Field Label&amp;quot;) {
                    placeHolder = &amp;quot;Select a value&amp;quot;
                    possibleValues = ToBeRetrieved(someWebService.getValues())
                    representation = IF_VISIBLE representAs SIMPLE_KEY_TO_VALUE
                }
            }
            field(key = &amp;quot;fieldKey4&amp;quot;) {
                input(&amp;quot;Input Text Field Label&amp;quot;) {
                    inputTextType = InputTextType.EMAIL
                    rules = { listOf(IsEmail()) }
                }
            }
            field(key = &amp;quot;fieldKey&amp;quot;) {
				        empty(&amp;quot;Empty Field&amp;quot;)
            }
        }
		    section(&amp;quot;Section 3 Title&amp;quot;) {
            field(key = &amp;quot;fieldKey6&amp;quot;) {
                toggle(&amp;quot;Toggle Field Label&amp;quot;) {
                    boolToStringConverter = { if (it == true) &amp;quot;OK&amp;quot; else &amp;quot;KO&amp;quot; }
                    rules = { listOf(NotMissing()) }
                    representation = ALWAYS representAs SIMPLE_KEY_TO_VALUE
                }
            }
        }
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is the result on Android using my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/brescia123/forms&#34;&gt;Form library&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/kotlin-dsl/form_screen.png&#34; alt=&#34;Form screenshot&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cool, isn&amp;rsquo;t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;type-safe-builders&#34;&gt;Type-safe builders&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-kotlin-important-features&#34;&gt;Some Kotlin important features&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To grasp how Type-safe builders work in Kotlin we need to understand some key Kotlin features and how they can be combined together:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Higher-Order Functions and Lambdas&lt;/strong&gt;: in Kotlin we are allowed to write functions that have &lt;em&gt;functions as parameters or return type&lt;/em&gt; (higher-order functions) and functions that are &lt;em&gt;not declared&lt;/em&gt;, but are passed immediately as an expression (lambdas). Because of this, we can write things like:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-kotlin&#34;&gt;// Higher-Order Function
fun transformWith(path: String, function: (String) -&amp;gt; List&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;): List&amp;lt;String&amp;gt; {
    return function(this)
}

// Lambda
{ path: String -&amp;gt; path.split(&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;) }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Kotlin syntactic sugar we can use them in these ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-kotlin&#34;&gt;transformWith(&amp;quot;some/path/to&amp;quot;, { path: String -&amp;gt; path.split(&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;) }) // -&amp;gt; [some, path, to]

// Functions which have a function as the last parameter can be written as follow
transformWith(&amp;quot;some/path/to&amp;quot;) { path -&amp;gt; path.split(&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;) } // -&amp;gt; [some, path, to]

// If the lambda has only one parameter it can be ommitted and referenced as &amp;quot;it&amp;quot;
transformWith(&amp;quot;some/path/to&amp;quot;) { it.split(&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;) } // -&amp;gt; [some, path, to]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extension Functions&lt;/strong&gt;: they allow us to &lt;em&gt;extend&lt;/em&gt; a type with functions without modifying the original class. They are useful to add functionalities to classes we don&amp;rsquo;t have control on or to create utility methods without the need to create &amp;ldquo;Utils classes&amp;rdquo; that contains static methods, as we are used to as Java developers. To continue the previous example we can write:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-kotlin&#34;&gt;// Extension function
fun String.transformWith(function: (String) -&amp;gt; List&amp;lt;String&amp;gt;) {
    return function(this)
}

&amp;quot;some/path/to&amp;quot;.transformWith { receiverString: String -&amp;gt; receiverString(&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;) } // -&amp;gt; [some, path, to]

// or more concisely 
&amp;quot;some/path/to&amp;quot;.transformWith { it.split(&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;) } // -&amp;gt; [some, path, to]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that we are referring to the string inside the closure of the extension function using &lt;code&gt;this&lt;/code&gt; as it will be the String object on which the method will be called.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Function Literals with Receiver&lt;/strong&gt;: similarly to extension functions you are also allowed to define functions with a receiver that will be referred to as &lt;code&gt;this&lt;/code&gt; inside the literal closure:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;val transformWith: String.() -&amp;gt; List&amp;lt;String&amp;gt; = { this.split(&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;) }

&amp;quot;some/path/to&amp;quot;.transformWith() // -&amp;gt; [some, path, to]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To better understand function literals with receiver you should think of them as follow: &lt;em&gt;lambda is to normal function as function literal with receiver is to extension function&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-kotlin&#34;&gt;// lambda
{ s: String -&amp;gt; s.split(&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;) }
// is to
fun function(s: String): List&amp;lt;String&amp;gt; { return s.split(&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;) }
// as
val functionLiteralWithReceiver = String.() -&amp;gt; List&amp;lt;String&amp;gt; = { this.split(&amp;quot;/&amp;quot;) }
// is to
fun String.extensionFunction(): List&amp;lt;String&amp;gt; { return function(this) }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically function literals with receiver are extension functions that can be passed to other functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;wrapping-up&#34;&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have all the elements required to understand and write a Type-safe builder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combining the above mentioned Kotlin features we can now write a function and name it &lt;code&gt;form&lt;/code&gt;. This function will take as parameter a function literal with receiver usually called &lt;code&gt;init()&lt;/code&gt; and will do the follow:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;create a new Form object&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;call &lt;code&gt;init()&lt;/code&gt; on it (that is using it as the receiver of the function literal)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;return the built object to the caller&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-kotlin&#34;&gt;fun form(init: Form.() -&amp;gt; Unit): Form {
    val form = Form() 
    form.init()
    return form
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let&amp;rsquo;s imagine that our Form class defines a function &lt;code&gt;field()&lt;/code&gt; that actually creates a field object and adds it to the list of fields contained within the form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-kotlin&#34;&gt;class Form() {
    val fields: List&amp;lt;Field&amp;gt;
    ...
    fun field(key: String) { ... }
    ...
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking advantage of Kotlin syntactic sugar we can use &lt;code&gt;form()&lt;/code&gt; passing it the &lt;code&gt;init()&lt;/code&gt; function as a lambda and call methods on the Form object to build it as follow:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-kotlin&#34;&gt;val builtForm = form() {
    // Here we can take advantage of the compiler and, as a result, of the IDE code completion
    field(&amp;quot;key1&amp;quot;) // == this.field(&amp;quot;key1&amp;quot;) where this is the object create by form()
    field(&amp;quot;key2&amp;quot;)
}
builtForm.getFields() // -&amp;gt; [Field(&amp;quot;key1&amp;quot;), Field(&amp;quot;key2&amp;quot;)]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see Type-Safe builders are an &lt;strong&gt;extremely powerful&lt;/strong&gt; and useful feature of Kotlin and they allow you to write very complex DSLs with a &lt;strong&gt;really readable and clear syntax&lt;/strong&gt;. They give you a lot of &lt;strong&gt;flexibility&lt;/strong&gt; letting you combine multiple builders to create a domain language that can meet your requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to learn more about this subject check out the official &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Kotlin/kotlinx.html&#34;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt; or, for example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Kotlin/kotlinx.html&#34;&gt;kotlinx&lt;/a&gt;, an official project from the Kotlin team that allows you to create HTML documents with a custom DSL entirely written with Type-safe builders.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Angular Components: from AngularJS to &#34;just Angular&#34;</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/angular-components-from-angularjs-to-just-angular/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/angular-components-from-angularjs-to-just-angular/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p align=&#34;center&#34;&gt; &lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/web-components-a-path-to-angular-2/angular.png&#34;&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With version 1.5 and newer, AngularJS (which for clarity we&amp;rsquo;ll call &lt;a href=&#34;http://angularjs.blogspot.it/2016/12/ok-let-me-explain-its-going-to-be.html#Its_just_Angular_39&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;just Angular&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from now on, even though the naming convention was &lt;a href=&#34;http://angularjs.blogspot.it/2017/01/branding-guidelines-for-angular-and.html&#34;&gt;recently updated&lt;/a&gt;) introduced their own interpretation of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.webcomponents.org/&#34;&gt;Web Components&lt;/a&gt;, back-porting &lt;em&gt;Components&lt;/em&gt; from Angular 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;em&gt;Components&lt;/em&gt; with Angular today not only means writing code much more easily upgradeable to future framework versions (especially using ES6), but it also allows you to modularize and reuse code more easily, in line with the modern frontend programming style that will be more and more modular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as with anything new, there are open questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When should you use it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why should you use it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whatâ€™s the difference between &lt;code&gt;.component()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;.directive()&lt;/code&gt; APIs?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the official documentation, a &lt;em&gt;Component&lt;/em&gt; is like a &lt;em&gt;Directive&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip; but easier to use!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;directive-vs-component&#34;&gt;Directive vs Component&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Directive:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;was the main API to access the DOM in Angular 1.x;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;isolates parts of the DOM to create reusable building blocks;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can be both a &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Element&#34;&gt;DOM element&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;and/or&lt;/strong&gt; a &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Attr&#34;&gt;DOM attribute&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;uses link and compile functions to operate on the DOM and the  model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Component:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;is an higher level abstraction of &lt;em&gt;directives&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;can only be a DOM element (and aggregate others)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has an isolated scope by default&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;automatically uses &lt;code&gt;controllerAs&lt;/code&gt; syntax&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;uses controllers instead of link functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;has &lt;code&gt;bindToController&lt;/code&gt; option on by default&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;coding-comparison&#34;&gt;Coding comparison&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;
app.directive(&#39;list&#39;, function() {
  return {
    scope: {
      items: &#39;=&#39;
    },
    restrict: â€œEâ€,
    templateUrl: &#39;list.html&#39;,
    controller: function ListCtrl() {},
    controllerAs: &#39;$ctrl&#39;,
    bindToController: true
  }
});

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Itâ€™s a simple component directive, with an isolated scope, binding, and a controller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hereâ€™s how youâ€™ll write it with &lt;code&gt;.component()&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;
app.component(&#39;list&#39;, {
  bindings: {
    items: &#39;=&#39;
  },
  templateUrl: &#39;list.html&#39;,
  controller: function ListCtrl() {}
});

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see not much has changed, but things are a little simpler:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;bindToController&lt;/code&gt; is the default and with the &lt;code&gt;bindings&lt;/code&gt; property the scope is always isolated; &lt;code&gt;controllerAs&lt;/code&gt; is on and defaults set to &lt;code&gt;$ctrl&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Components so donâ€™t manipulate the DOM or data that are outside their scope, but they receive inputs and produce outputs through the interaction with the view.
Another nice point is that we donâ€™t need to write a &lt;strong&gt;dumb&lt;/strong&gt; function that always returns the same object, we just define that object right here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;comparison-between-directive-definition-and-component-definition&#34;&gt;Comparison between Directive definition and Component definition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;property&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Directive&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Component&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;

&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;bindings&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes (binds to controller)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;bindToController&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes (default: &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No (use bindings instead)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;compile()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;controller&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes (defaults to &lt;code&gt;function() {}&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;controllerAs&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes (default: &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes (default &lt;code&gt;$ctrl&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;link()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;multiElement&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;priority&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;require&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;scope&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes (default: &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No (scope is always isolate)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;template&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes, injectable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;templateNamespace&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;templateUrl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes, injectable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;terminal&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;

&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;transclude&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes (default: &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Yes (default: &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-other-goodies&#34;&gt;New other goodies:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;one-way-data-bindings&#34;&gt;One way data bindings&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previously, we could pass objects to child directives/components with the &lt;code&gt;=&lt;/code&gt; binding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;
app.component(&#39;bar&#39;, {
  templateUrl: &#39;bar.html&#39;,
  bindings: {
    foo: &#39;=&#39;
  },
  controller: function() {}
});

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would have created a &lt;strong&gt;two-way data binding&lt;/strong&gt; with the componentâ€™s parent. Whenever the parent would assign a new value to &lt;code&gt;foo&lt;/code&gt;, or change the existing one, this would be propagated to the child too, and vice-versa; this is how two-way data binding operates by design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While helpful, this isnâ€™t a very common scenario in my experience, because it has its drawbacks: mostly, in complex applications it may become more difficult to reason about, and it can have heavy performance implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thatâ€™s why Angular has introduced one-way data bindings: these create just a single &lt;em&gt;watcher&lt;/em&gt;, watching for changes on the parent and propagating them to the child. As a result we gain performance (by cutting in half the amount of watchers created) and things become less &amp;ldquo;error friendly&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The syntax is similar to the code below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;
app.component(&#39;bar&#39;, {
  templateUrl: &#39;bar.html&#39;,
  bindings: {
    foo: &#39;&amp;lt;&#39;
  },
  controller: function() {}
});

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, we just changed &lt;code&gt;=&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other data binding parameters are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt;: interpolation bindings (input parameter), also used in the directives for values â€‹â€‹coming from the DOM as strings;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/code&gt;: expression bindings, often used to pass a function to a component to provide a callback event (to generate an output) to the caller.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;lifecycle-hook-oninit-onchanges-ondestroy-and-postlink&#34;&gt;Lifecycle hook: &lt;code&gt;$onInit&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;$onChanges&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;$onDestroy&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$postLink&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lifecycle hooks provides us with an easy way of invoking operation based on the lifecycle of our components. The usage of these hooks lets us provide our users with relevant information or action at the appropriate time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;$onInit()&lt;/code&gt; is executed when all controllers on the element have been constructed and after their bindings are initialized.
This hook is meant to be used for any kind of initialization work for the controller.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;
app.component(&#39;MyCtrlComp&#39;, {
  templateUrl: &#39;user.html&#39;,
  controller: function() {
    this.$onInit = function() {
        this.username = &#39;John.Doe&#39;;
        console.log(&#39;User component initialized&#39;);
    };
  }
});

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very simple example, but imagine weâ€™d need to do some HTTP requests during initialization of this component or controller: now we have a better place for these kind of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;$onDestroy()&lt;/code&gt; is called when its containing scope is destroyed. We can use this hook to release external resources, watches and event handlers.
In a scenario where you have attached non-native Angular event listeners or logic, we can use this hook to clean it up when the component is destroyed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;$onChanges()&lt;/code&gt; is a particular type of â€œwatchâ€ called  when changes occur in one way bindings on the input component interface.
It gets called with an object that holds the changes of all one-way bindings with the current Value and the previous Value.
With &lt;code&gt;$onChanges&lt;/code&gt; we can react to this changes and update the child component data effectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose that we make the name property of our myUserCmp configurable from the outside using a one-way binding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;
mod.component(&#39;myUserCmp&#39;, {
  template: &#39;&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;{{$ctrl.user}}&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;&#39;,
  bindings: {
    name: &#39;&amp;lt;&#39;
  },
  controller: MyCtrlComp
});

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;in the markup we can now bind an expression to the componentâ€™s user property like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;
&amp;lt;my-cmp user=&amp;quot;JohnDoe&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/my-cmp&amp;gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we want to prepend the user with â€œHiâ€ when the user is JohnDoe and otherwise put â€œHelloâ€. We can do that using the &lt;code&gt;$onChanges()&lt;/code&gt; lifecycle hook.
It gets called with an object that holds the changes of all one-way bindings along with the currentValue and the previousValue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;
function MyCtrlComp() {
  this.$onChanges = function (changesObj) {
    if (changesObj.user) {
      var prfx;
      (changesObj.user.currentValue === &#39;JohnDoe&#39;) ?
        prfx = &#39;Hi &#39; : prfx = &#39;Hello &#39;;
      this.user = prfx + this.user;
    }
  };
}

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;$postLink()&lt;/code&gt; is called after the controller&amp;rsquo;s element and its children have been linked. When the component elements have been compiled and are ready to go, this hook will be fired;&lt;br /&gt;
It can help us to implement some functionality that depends on the component elements to be fully compiled.
Itâ€™s important to note that this is not a complete replacement for DOM manipulation, this functionality should be handled by decorator directives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adopting &lt;em&gt;Components&lt;/em&gt; allows you to write code that is more easily portable to future Angular versions and introduces a modular architecture of the DOM that is more maintainable compared to the usual guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;em&gt;Component&lt;/em&gt; based architecture, an application becomes a tree structure of elements, with well-defined inputs and outputs, a clear data-flow, and predictable behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this structure, the root elements are usually called &amp;ldquo;smart components&amp;rdquo; because these are the ones who manage the data, while those closest to the leaves are called &amp;ldquo;dumb components&amp;rdquo; instead, because they are more UI focused and are highly reusable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, &lt;code&gt;.component()&lt;/code&gt; is a great addition to Angular. Itâ€™s a real upgrade for code quality and helps you prepare for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, upgrade to 1.5 and start using &lt;code&gt;.component()&lt;/code&gt;: you have unlocked a new skill!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more details refer to understanding components &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.angularjs.org/guide/component&#34;&gt;docs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Please mutate responsibly: 3 ways to improve your mutable objects</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/please-mutate-responsibly-3-ways-to-improve-your-mutable-objects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/please-mutate-responsibly-3-ways-to-improve-your-mutable-objects/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Maintaining &lt;strong&gt;state&lt;/strong&gt; is the main cause of complexity and headaches in software development: without a careful consideration of state, our projects will inevitably become impossible to understand. In fact, various development techniques and programming styles are mainly there to handle state in a responsible way: for example, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monad_(functional_programming)&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;monads&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, as used in functional programming, are often employed for this very task. A good general way of managing state is trying to make it &lt;strong&gt;immutable&lt;/strong&gt;, either through the use &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Value_type&#34;&gt;value types&lt;/a&gt;, that is, types which instances are passed around with &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Object_copying#Deep_copy&#34;&gt;deep copy&lt;/a&gt; semantics, or simple &lt;em&gt;immutable objects&lt;/em&gt;, which have reference semantics but because they&amp;rsquo;re immutable their state is fixed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the &lt;em&gt;processes&lt;/em&gt; we usually represent in code are all but immutable: the state of any running software is probably going to change as time passes, as a result of &lt;em&gt;foreign interactions&lt;/em&gt;, a.k.a., &lt;em&gt;side effects&lt;/em&gt;. This means that something, somewhere has to mutate, and to be more precise we can say that the information stored in a certain object is going to change: actually, an &lt;strong&gt;information&lt;/strong&gt; by itself is a &lt;strong&gt;constant&lt;/strong&gt; value, but from time to time that object is going to store different pieces of information, some are going to be new, others are going to be outdated. So there&amp;rsquo;s no escape from mutation: the point is to mutate &lt;strong&gt;responsibly&lt;/strong&gt;, that is, to not be reckless with our mutable objects, and treat them in a special way so that we can still reason about our code and easily understand the state of our system at any given moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The already cited techniques based on monads represent a good way to solve the problem, but monads only really work in a functional programming context, something that&amp;rsquo;s not everyone&amp;rsquo;s cup of tea, and to be really productive while using them you need to &lt;em&gt;think in terms of monads&lt;/em&gt;, and treat them as primitive objects. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to talk about monads or functional programming in general, my focus for this article is analyzing mutability in software, while identifying common techniques that can be leveraged in any programming language/paradigm to improve our code. In particular I want to talk about 3 specific problems that arise while working with mutable objects, and 3 solutions to address them. To quickly summarize, my suggestions will be the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;be idempotent;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;react to change;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;proceed one-way only.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s see each one of them in detail by developing a concrete example: an object that represents a &lt;em&gt;payment process&lt;/em&gt;, which at any moment can be in various states, like &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;started&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;working&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;succeeded&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;failed&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;be-idempotent&#34;&gt;Be idempotent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To mutate an object from the outside we usually &lt;em&gt;tell&lt;/em&gt; the object to &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; something. If we truly want to respect the object-oriented paradigm, and in particular if we don&amp;rsquo;t want to violate &lt;strong&gt;encapsulation&lt;/strong&gt;, we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t make assumptions about the internal state of a certain object after a certain method call; still, we cannot help but making assumptions about the way our entire &lt;em&gt;system&lt;/em&gt; is going to work after a method call, otherwise it would be impossible to reason about code. But if our changes are &lt;em&gt;incremental&lt;/em&gt;, it&amp;rsquo;s going to be really hard to understand the system even after a simple method call. Not all changes are created equal: if the resulting system&amp;rsquo;s state is affected by the previous one, before the change takes place, then it&amp;rsquo;s going to be basically impossible to reason about the system after the change, because in our reasoning we should take into account all the possible conditions the system was in. An incremental change, for example a method call to &lt;em&gt;increase a counter&lt;/em&gt;, will overload our mind of conditional paths and will cause bugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, for our &lt;code&gt;PaymentProcess&lt;/code&gt; we don&amp;rsquo;t want to be able to generically &lt;em&gt;advance&lt;/em&gt; the payment state: we want to advance it to a particular stage, with a clean method call that should be &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Idempotence&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;idempotent&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, that is, calling it 1 time, 2 times or 100 times &lt;strong&gt;has to be the same&lt;/strong&gt;. This also means that if more objects call the same method, it will be like if only one object called it, and this will completely remove a running cause of bugs: multiple, uncoordinated interactions of the same type with an object. Idempotence is a simple concept, but it&amp;rsquo;s extremely powerful: with it, we don&amp;rsquo;t need to keep track if a particular operation has already occurred (thus saving some state), but to properly implement it we need the correct semantics: while &lt;em&gt;delta&lt;/em&gt; operations are very frequent in real life (think about increasing the volume of a TV set) and are usually harmless, they can be dangerous in software development, an in general it&amp;rsquo;s important to understand the what &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; natural in real life is not necessarily a good thing in software engineering, or engineering in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, notice that while an idempotent method call will always have the same result on a particular instance, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that will have the same result on &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; instances - more on this later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;react-to-change&#34;&gt;React to change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reactivemanifesto.org&#34;&gt;Reactive programming&lt;/a&gt; has been big the last few years, and that&amp;rsquo;s mostly thanks both to the popularity achieved by functional programming in OOP circles, and to the diffusion of architectures based on microservices. But the idea of &lt;em&gt;being reactive&lt;/em&gt; in software development has been around for much more than that: for example, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Observer_pattern&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;observer pattern&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has been there for decades, and the basic underlying idea is that of &lt;em&gt;connecting&lt;/em&gt; objects by establishing relations between them in which a state change is automatically propagated to a collection of &lt;em&gt;observers&lt;/em&gt;. It is responsibility of an observer to react to what just happened, while the &lt;em&gt;observable&lt;/em&gt; object doesn&amp;rsquo;t really care about what the others will do. This will allow us to achieve the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a nice &lt;em&gt;decoupling&lt;/em&gt; between a mutable object and other objects that for any reason are interested in its mutation; no custom interface will be needed, just a simple fixed method (like &lt;code&gt;next&lt;/code&gt;) to pass around the new information;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a more &lt;em&gt;declarative&lt;/em&gt; code style, in which our method calls will only describe the intent of connecting one or more objects to a chain of reactions (and &lt;a href=&#34;https://gist.github.com/staltz/868e7e9bc2a7b8c1f754&#34;&gt;functional reactive programming&lt;/a&gt; is particularly good a that).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About our payment example, whatever object is interested in a change of state, like for example UI objects the will show different views to the user based on the current payment stage, should really subscribe to our payment object to receive &lt;em&gt;signals&lt;/em&gt; about its mutation: the payment object itself should then send these changes to the observers. Notice that I used the  word &lt;em&gt;send&lt;/em&gt; and not &lt;em&gt;broadcast&lt;/em&gt;: the change of state of a particular object should usually not be treated as an all-encompassing &lt;em&gt;event&lt;/em&gt;. Events are really about application wide changes (like a phone call during the execution of a mobile application): there are many ways to implement our observables and observers, the point is simply to have a clean, fixed API to &lt;em&gt;emit&lt;/em&gt; an information, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://reactivex.io&#34;&gt;ReactiveX&lt;/a&gt; could be a nice starting point to get an idea about the possible APIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;proceed-one-way-only&#34;&gt;Proceed one-way only&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might be controversial but it&amp;rsquo;s extremely important. Consider the following case: our payment process object has idempotent methods and a reactive API, so a view controller object can keep a UI updated and send back user interactions to advance the process. But while the process is in &amp;ldquo;working&amp;rdquo; stage something goes wrong and the process fails: not a problem, we actually considered the &amp;ldquo;failed&amp;rdquo; stage, so the &lt;code&gt;PaymentProcess&lt;/code&gt; is updated accordingly. But we would actually like to retry the payment, and of course update everything accordingly in our reactive chain. What should we do? Set our &lt;code&gt;PaymentProcess&lt;/code&gt; back to &amp;ldquo;working&amp;rdquo;? That would be possible, but it&amp;rsquo;s going to make everything more complex, because all the observers should in theory take into account the fact the this is not the first attempt to pay (the UI for example could show a &amp;ldquo;retry&amp;rdquo; message instead of the usual one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, we want to &lt;em&gt;solve&lt;/em&gt; a state problem, we don&amp;rsquo;t want to distribute it to multiple objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another case could be a complete stop of the payment process (the user could cancel it, for example, or the session could expire): we don&amp;rsquo;t want to bring back the &lt;code&gt;PaymentProcess&lt;/code&gt; instance, forcing all observer to do some kind of cleanup. In any case, a process that goes back and forth makes reasoning about code really hard, because &lt;strong&gt;it makes the future more complex&lt;/strong&gt;: all the objects that depend on a mutable object are going to be easier to implement if we can assume that the mutability will only proceed in one direction. Of course this is not easy to implement, but in this case it&amp;rsquo;s really natural to think about it: if the milk is running out in the evening, I cannot expect the bottle to magically refill for the morning, so I should start thinking about a different breakfast. Processes that are invertible usually require some form of external, high-level coordination, and from an architectural standpoint the idea of an object that mutates in any possible way might seem harmless: but at the implementation level this will cause problems, and bugs are in the implementation, not in the architecture. While implementing new features, refactoring, debugging or simply studying a codebase we reason about the code, not the architecture, and &lt;em&gt;coordinator&lt;/em&gt; objects are classic jack-of-all-trades at the architecture level: but unfortunately, an implementation that requires external coordination is going to be more complex and error-prone, so it&amp;rsquo;s better to be clear about the mutation path for an object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our particular case, we could consider one or more &amp;ldquo;retry&amp;rdquo; stages, or a single &amp;ldquo;retry&amp;rdquo; stage with an associated object that represents the number of retries. And about the possibility of going back to the beginning, in that case we should really &lt;strong&gt;discard the whole process&lt;/strong&gt;: the process owner, that would have likely activated the various accessory objects (like the ones for the UI) should &lt;em&gt;listen&lt;/em&gt; for an &amp;ldquo;abort&amp;rdquo; stage, that would make it kill everything and start the process anew. There might be performance concerns: to mutate objects is usually faster than recreating them, but again, it can be managed and it&amp;rsquo;s better to have cleaner, more understandable code from the beginning, so that it&amp;rsquo;s going to be easier to make fine calibrations in later stages, than to create a mess in the name of early optimizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final question: if the process is one-way only, what happens if some object tries to set it to a previous stage with a method call? &lt;strong&gt;Absolutely nothing&lt;/strong&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;ignore-if-impossible&lt;/em&gt; semantics is actually clean and reasonable, and we don&amp;rsquo;t need errors or exceptions to handle: even if this has to be taken into account at every method call, the important thing is to be &lt;strong&gt;clear&lt;/strong&gt; about it, and the alternative is much worse. This whole article could be summarized in the phrase &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;clear semantics are what makes mutability bearable&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;. In this particular case, the fact that a method call is ignored or not doesn&amp;rsquo;t change our reasoning: I&amp;rsquo;m not going to make assumptions about the state of &lt;code&gt;PaymentProcess&lt;/code&gt; after the call, because I&amp;rsquo;m actually reacting to its changes in a separate context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We considered a bunch of possible problems to think about when implementing mutable objects, and some options to confront them. Of course these ideas are purposely very general: every problem is different, every codebase is unique. But applying even just one of these techniques will most likely result in more clear and understandable code. I also didn&amp;rsquo;t talk about application-wide mutation, because that&amp;rsquo;s really an architectural thing; my goal is to raise awareness about the concept of mutation and variable instance properties in every single class. We should always &lt;strong&gt;avoid&lt;/strong&gt; mutation when possible, and concentrate our variable state in a few, carefully controlled places; but if we&amp;rsquo;re not careful, even a single mutating class in a multiple class project could wreak havoc, and force use to debug and fix a system that we thought was clean and well structured.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Codemotion Milan 2016 in review</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/codemotion-milan-2016-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/codemotion-milan-2016-in-review/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Â«Learn or dieÂ»&lt;/em&gt;. These are the words with which &lt;a href=&#34;http://milan2016.codemotionworld.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Codemotion Milan 2016&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; started on the 25th of November. Most of our development team attended this tech conference like the &lt;a href=&#34;http://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/facile-it-devs-codemotion-milan-2015/&#34;&gt;previous year&lt;/a&gt;. Moreover &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facile.it&#34;&gt;Facile.it&lt;/a&gt; was present at the event as a sponsor with his stand looking for new talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the event we also officially &lt;strong&gt;announced the second &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackathon.facile.it/&#34;&gt;#FacileHack&lt;/a&gt; hackathon&lt;/strong&gt;, which is planned for &lt;strong&gt;march 2017&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post would be a short recap of some talks in chronological order. The choice of the talks is based on the personal taste of the various members of the editorial staff of Facile.it Engineering blog. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/codemotion-2016-in-review/codemotion_2016.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A part of Facile Dev Team&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;day-1&#34;&gt;Day 1&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-new-features-of-php-7&#34;&gt;The new features of PHP 7&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enrico Zimuel (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ezimuel&#34;&gt;@ezimuel&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:30 â€“ 12:10 #programming (&lt;a href=&#34;http://zimuel.it/slides/codemotion2016/&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enrico Zimuel, Software Engineer at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zend.com/&#34;&gt;Zend Technologies&lt;/a&gt;, the company behind the PHP engine, talks about some of the new features of PHP 7: the scalar type and return type declarations, the spaceship and null coalescing operators, the anonymous classes, the consistent 64-bit support, etc. Furthermore he explains why PHP 7 is twice as fast compared to the previous version and it has 30% lower memory consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;kubernetes-and-lastminute-com-our-course-towards-better-scalability-and-processes&#34;&gt;Kubernetes and lastminute.com: our course towards better scalability and processes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Michele Orsi (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/micheleorsi&#34;&gt;@micheleorsi&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:30 â€“ 12:10 #devops (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/micheleorsi/kubernetes-and-lastminutecom-our-course-towards-better-scalability-and-processes&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastminute.com recently started a migration from a monolithic app to a microservice approach, leveraging the power of Kubernetes, the open source project lead by Google for container orchestration. This was quite the effort, and it unveiled a great deal of advantages and challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;continuous-budgeting&#34;&gt;Continuous budgeting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Francesco Fullone (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/fullo&#34;&gt;@fullo&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;14:10 - 15:50 #inspirational&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk is about being agile in the entrepeneur side of our profession: how to plan and adapt to change when deciding how and how much to spend in our coding ventures; re-evaluating is key, and the only way to success is a delicate balance between maintenance and improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;to-65k-and-beyond&#34;&gt;To âˆž (~65K) and beyond!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sebastiano Gottardo (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rotxed&#34;&gt;@rotxed&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;16:10 - 16:50 #mobile (&lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/dextor/to-65k-and-beyond&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of old -but still widely used- Android devices are natively limited to run apps with less than 65K method references (due to the Dalvik JVM). For many apps this could be a serious problem. During the talk Sebastiano, an Android engineer at Musixmatch, gave a very comprehensive and clear explanation of the problem and went through all the possible solutions showing some really useful tips to deal or better &lt;em&gt;avoid&lt;/em&gt; it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;functional-reactive-programming-with-kotlin-on-android&#34;&gt;Functional Reactive Programming with Kotlin on Android&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giorgio Natili (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/giorgionatili&#34;&gt;@giorgionatili&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;17:10 - 17:50 #mobile (&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0BxCm4NRlzb3PWjNNaG1KS0Utckk/view&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of this talk was very interesting considering the fact that both the functional paradigm and the Kotlin language are used within the Facile.it Android app. But actually I have to say that I found a 40 minutes talk not suitable as a format to address these two large topics together (72 slides!). I would have preferred two separate talks, but it was nevertheless an interesting presentation full of useful tips and advices about Kotlin and FRP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;day-2&#34;&gt;Day 2&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;coding-culture&#34;&gt;Coding Culture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sven Peters (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/svenpet&#34;&gt;@svenpet&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:30 - 11:10 #inspirational (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/svenpeters/coding-culture&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his keynote Sven Peters, Evangelist for &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.atlassian.com/&#34;&gt;Atlassian&lt;/a&gt;, explains - in a very geek style - what is &lt;em&gt;company culture&lt;/em&gt;, referring in particular to his company. He says that when people work in a great coding culture they are motivated and they are mostly very productive, but also they will have more responsibility and investment in the features they are developing. Developers will have more freedom to change their roles and try out new stuff, this is the right way to make better products with happier developers. He concluded his speech with these words: &lt;em&gt;Â«Products may change, but never forget values, cultivate your culture!Â»&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;micromonolith-top-anti-patterns-of-adopting-distributed-system&#34;&gt;MicroMonolith - Top anti-patterns of adopting distributed system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Michal Franc (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/francmichal&#34;&gt;@francmichal&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12:30 â€“ 13:10 #architectures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this talk, Michal reports his (and his team) experience in the infamous transistion from a monolithic app to a microservice oriented architecture. Michal works at &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/JustGiving&#34;&gt;@JustGiving&lt;/a&gt;, which mainly uses .NET, but he didn&amp;rsquo;t focus on the specific technology, but rather on the generic problems and pitfalls that this kind of transition brings to the table. During his tale, he laid to us a lot of useful suggestions and common issues to look for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;develop-applications-in-big-data-era-with-scala-and-spark&#34;&gt;Develop applications in Big Data Era with Scala and Spark&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mario Cartia (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mariocartia&#34;&gt;@mariocartia&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12:30 â€“ 13:10 #cloud #bigdata&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large amount of data are produced everyday and Big Data is a concept increasingly trendy. In his talk Mario Cartia presented Scala and Spark,two powerful tools suitable to Big Data Processing.  Scala is a General purpose programming language that combines the benefits of OOP and functional programming. Apache Spark is an open source framework and it&amp;rsquo;s a fast engine for big data processing, based on Scala language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gang-of-four-patterns-in-a-functional-light&#34;&gt;Gang of Four Patterns in a Functional Light&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mario Fusco (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mariofusco&#34;&gt;@mariofusco&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;14:10 â€“ 14:50 #programming (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mariofusco/from-gof-to-lambda&#34;&gt;code&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this live-coding talk, Mario Fusco uses Java (and new Java 1.8 features) to translate the wide-known GoF design patterns into functional programming, making the code a lot less verbose, reducing the noise of boilerplate over the really important code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, kittens:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-cards=&#34;hidden&#34; data-lang=&#34;it&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;it&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;&amp;quot;In programmazione funzionale, quando lanci un&amp;#39;eccezione muore un gattino, se ritorni null muore la mamma&amp;quot; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mariofusco&#34;&gt;@mariofusco&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/CodemotionIT&#34;&gt;@CodemotionIT&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/40XErlWFbX&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/40XErlWFbX&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Giulio Santoli (@gjuljo) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/gjuljo/status/802507849494654976&#34;&gt;26 novembre 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking back at Symfony Day Rome 2016</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/looking-back-at-symfony-day-rome-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/looking-back-at-symfony-day-rome-2016/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Every year the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grusp.org/&#34;&gt;GrUSP&lt;/a&gt;, in cooperation with one of the italian PHP user groups, organizes the italian &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://symfony.com/&#34;&gt;Symfony&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; conference. This year the &lt;a href=&#34;http://2016.symfonyday.it/&#34;&gt;event&lt;/a&gt; was organized in the Capital on 28th October with the help of &lt;a href=&#34;http://roma.grusp.org/&#34;&gt;PHP User Group Roma&lt;/a&gt;, and a part of Facile Dev Team was there for the occasion. In Facile we believe attending to events like this is a good way to learn new things, share practical experiences and improve our network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post would be a short recap of all the talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/looking-back-at-symfony-day-rome-2016/faciledev_symfonyday_2016.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A part of Facile Dev Team&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;schedule&#34;&gt;Schedule&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;symfony-and-micro-not-so-much-service&#34;&gt;Symfony and micro (not so much) service&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk by: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/_orso_&#34;&gt;Michele Orselli&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;Duration: 30 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michele Orselli presented a case study of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monolithic_application&#34;&gt;monolithic application&lt;/a&gt; broken down into many smaller microservices. How many ways can we split a webapp? Why smaller is better? How services can interact each other? In his talk Michele answered all those questions focusing on all the advantages of the proposed architecture and a few common pitfalls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;View slides &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/MicheleOrselli/symfony-e-micro-non-cosi-tanto-services&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;scaling-symfony-apps&#34;&gt;Scaling Symfony apps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk by: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mat_teo8&#34;&gt;Matteo Moretti&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;Duration: 45 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A scalable application must support an increasing amount of data or a growing number of users. In his talk, Matteo Moretti described the architecture needed to scale. He divided the overall architecture into 4 main components: web server, sessions, database and the filesystem. He explained the right configuration to his main purpose: improving performance of a webapp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;View slides &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/matteomoro8/scaling-symfony-apps&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;e-commerce-with-symfony-from-case-study-to-reality&#34;&gt;E-commerce with Symfony: from case study to reality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk by: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/dymissy&#34;&gt;Simone D&amp;rsquo;Amico&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;Duration: 30 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sylius, Elcodi, Thelia, Sonata Project, Well Commerce, Shop Plus, Aimeos: these are the most popular results you can find if you google  &amp;ldquo;e-commerce solution with Symfony&amp;rdquo;. But which one is the final winner? Why choosing one or another? Simone D&amp;rsquo;Amico reviewed all of these frameworks and libraries comparing strengths and drawbacks. Moreover he clarified the stack he used to build an e-commerce platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;View slides &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/dymissy/ecommerce-con-sf-dal-case-study-alla-realt&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-journey-into-symfony-form-component&#34;&gt;A journey into Symfony form component&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk by: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/SamueleLilli&#34;&gt;Samuele Lilli&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;Duration: 45 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://symfony.com/doc/current/forms.html&#34;&gt;Symfony form component&lt;/a&gt; is the main obstacle for beginners and newbies in the Symfony world. Samuele Lilli gave a talk with the purpose to clarify this hot topic with a lot of examples and code snippets. He started from the simplest form examples to more advanced ones. He revealed a lot of tips and explanations for several scenarios in order to make this powerful component understandable and manageable by everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;View slides &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/SamueleLilli/symfony-day-2016&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/looking-back-at-symfony-day-rome-2016/symfonyday_collage.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Symfony Day 2016&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;php7-and-rich-domain-model&#34;&gt;PHP7 and Rich Domain Model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk by: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/garakkio&#34;&gt;Massimiliano Arione&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;Duration: 30 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this talk Massimiliano Arione told about his experience in the migration to PHP7 of a Symfony based project. Particularly he focused on the usage of type hinting and return types and the issues encountered with an &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anemic_domain_model&#34;&gt;Anemic Domain Model&lt;/a&gt; approach suggested by the framework official documentation. He showed how to combine a Rich Domain Model without giving up new language features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;View slides &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/garak/php7-e-rich-domain-model&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;relevance-sorting-with-elasticsearch-and-a-bit-of-maths&#34;&gt;Relevance sorting with Elasticsearch &amp;amp; a bit of maths&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk by: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mattbit_&#34;&gt;Matteo Dora&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;Duration: 45 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main topic of the talk was &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.elastic.co/products/elasticsearch&#34;&gt;Elasticsearch&lt;/a&gt;. Elasticsearch is a distributed, RESTful search and analytics engine with a great Symfony integration. Matteo Dora, the speaker of this talk, explained how to deal when the sorting by relevance becomes hard using the right amount of math and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/FriendsOfSymfony/FOSElasticaBundle&#34;&gt;FOSElasticaBundle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;View slides &lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/mattbit/elasticsearch-and-a-bit-of-maths&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;command-the-easy-way&#34;&gt;Command: the easy way&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk by: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/aczepod&#34;&gt;Antonio Carella&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;Duration: 30 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antonio Carella illustrated a real case how to create command-line commands using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://symfony.com/doc/current/console.html&#34;&gt;Symfony console component&lt;/a&gt;. He showed how console commands can be used for any recurring task, such as cronjobs, imports, or other batch jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;View slides &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/antoninocarella1/command-the-easy-way&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;orm-hero&#34;&gt;ORM hero&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk by: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/toretto460&#34;&gt;Simone Di Maulo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;Duration: 45 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk was a journey in the &lt;em&gt;magical world&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.doctrine-project.org/&#34;&gt;Doctrine&lt;/a&gt;, the most known ORM for Symfony and not only. Simone Di Maulo described how Doctrine works under the hood to better understand when and why to use its features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;View slides &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/SimoneDiMaulo/orm-hero&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MessagePack: an alternative to JSON?</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/message-pack-an-alternative-to-json/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/message-pack-an-alternative-to-json/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;When we talk about data interchange in web applications, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.json.org/&#34;&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is the de-facto standard, especially in developing RESTful web services. JSON won against its antagonist &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.w3.org/XML/&#34;&gt;XML&lt;/a&gt; (SOAP) without a battle, but it didn&amp;rsquo;t prevent the development of alternatives like &lt;a href=&#34;https://developers.google.com/protocol-buffers/&#34;&gt;Googleâ€™s &lt;strong&gt;Protocol Buffers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://avro.apache.org/&#34;&gt;Apache &lt;strong&gt;Avro&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://msgpack.org/&#34;&gt;MessagePack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. In being thorough, we should also mention &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gzip.org/&#34;&gt;gzip&lt;/a&gt; JSON compression (sometimes called &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;JSONC&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;), and &lt;a href=&#34;http://bsonspec.org/&#34;&gt;BSON&lt;/a&gt;, a binÂ­ary-enÂ­coded seriÂ­alÂ­izÂ­aÂ­tion of JSON-like docÂ­uÂ­ments, both derived directly from JSON. In this article we&amp;rsquo;ll discuss MessagePack in depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/message-pack-an-alternative-to-json/msgpack.png&#34; alt=&#34;MessagePack&#34; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;JSON Vs MessagePack (source: &lt;a href=&#34;http://msgpack.org/&#34;&gt;msgpack.org&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-is-messagepack&#34;&gt;What is MessagePack?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Â« &lt;em&gt;MessagePack is an efficient binary serialization format. It lets you exchange data among multiple languages like JSON. But it&amp;rsquo;s faster and smaller&lt;/em&gt; Â». To start using MessagePack we need to convert our application objects into MessagePack format: this process is called &lt;em&gt;serialization&lt;/em&gt;, while the reverse process is called &lt;em&gt;deserialization&lt;/em&gt;. The following example can help us better understand what we&amp;rsquo;re talking about. Consider this simple JSON:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;{
	&amp;quot;id&amp;quot;: 4,                    // integer
	&amp;quot;isActive&amp;quot;: true,           // boolean
	&amp;quot;fullname&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Homer Simpson&amp;quot; // string
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JSON requires 56 bytes to represent a very simple user object, while MessagePack only needs 38 bytes (compression ratio 1.47, yielding a 32% saving in size). See below the output of the serialization process for the above JSON:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;83 a2 69 64 04 a8 69 73 41 63 74 69 76 65 c3 a8 66 75 6c 6c 6e 61 6d 65 ad 48 6f 6d 65 72 20 53 69 6d 70 73 6f 6e
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see how MessagePack serialization works by reading the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/msgpack/msgpack/blob/master/spec.md&#34;&gt;official specification&lt;/a&gt;. Also, we can split the previous hexadecimal representation to emphasize and explain data types as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sql&#34;&gt;83                                          // 3-element map
a2 69 64                                    // 2-byte string &amp;quot;id&amp;quot;
04                                          // integer 4
a8 69 73 41 63 74 69 76 65                  // 8-byte string &amp;quot;isActive&amp;quot; 
c3                                          // boolean true
a8 66 75 6c 6c 6e 61 6d 65                  // 8-byte string &amp;quot;fullname&amp;quot;
ad 48 6f 6d 65 72 20 53 69 6d 70 73 6f 6e   // 13-byte string &amp;quot;Homer Simpson&amp;quot;
                                            // total 38 bytes
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it&amp;rsquo;s very simple to figure out the meaning of the sentence Â« &lt;em&gt;Small integers are encoded into a single byte, and typical short strings require only one extra byte in addition to the strings themselves&lt;/em&gt; Â» reported in the headline of MessagePack website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main features of MessagePack are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s designed for network communication and to be transparently converted from and to JSON;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it supports in-place updating, so it&amp;rsquo;s possible to modify part of a stored object without reserializing it as a whole;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it has a flexible &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Remote_procedure_call&#34;&gt;Remote Procedure Call (RPC)&lt;/a&gt; and streaming API implementation;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it supports &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Type_system#Static_type_checking&#34;&gt;static-type-checking&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;supported-data-types&#34;&gt;Supported data types&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data types listed by the specification are very similar to those in JSON, that is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integer&lt;/strong&gt; represents an &lt;code&gt;integer&lt;/code&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Boolean&lt;/strong&gt; represents &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nil&lt;/strong&gt; represents &lt;code&gt;nil&lt;/code&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Float&lt;/strong&gt; represents a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IEEE_floating_point&#34;&gt;IEEE 754&lt;/a&gt; double precision floating point numbers including &lt;code&gt;NaN&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Infinity&lt;/code&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;String&lt;/strong&gt; is a &lt;code&gt;raw type&lt;/code&gt; and it represents a UTF-8 string;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Binary&lt;/strong&gt; is a &lt;code&gt;raw type&lt;/code&gt; and it represents a binary data using byte array;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Array&lt;/strong&gt; represents a sequence of objects;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Map&lt;/strong&gt; represents a dictionary (key-value pairs of objects);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Extension&lt;/strong&gt; represents a tuple of data whose meaning is defined by applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-naive-benchmark&#34;&gt;A naive benchmark&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to this point our reasoning was focused on &lt;strong&gt;space efficiency&lt;/strong&gt;, but a good theoretical computing scientist would have criticized us since we didn&amp;rsquo;t mention &lt;strong&gt;time complexity&lt;/strong&gt;. In fact, the process of data &lt;em&gt;compression&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;decompression&lt;/em&gt; is not negligible. We can analyze and compare, for example, the time required to parse a JSON document and to unpack a MessagePack document: that&amp;rsquo;s not completely scientific, but it&amp;rsquo;s a start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wrote two &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://nodejs.org/en/&#34;&gt;Node.js&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; scripts to execute 1 million JSON parsing and 1 million MessagePack unpacking operations of a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/salvatorecordiano/facile-it-message-pack-benchmark/blob/master/document.json&#34;&gt;sample document&lt;/a&gt; containing the same data in the two formats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simplified version of the code could be something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-javascript&#34;&gt;// inside script &amp;quot;test_parse_json.js&amp;quot;
for (var i = 0;i&amp;lt;1000000;i++) {
    JSON.parse(jsonDocument); // JSON document parsing
}

// inside script &amp;quot;test_unpack_msgpack.js&amp;quot;
for (var i = 0;i&amp;lt;1000000;i++) {
    msgpack.unpack(msgPackDocument); // MessagePack document unpacking
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To easily profile our scripts we can run them as below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sql&#34;&gt;aiace:msgpack parallel$ time node test_parse_json.js

real	0m47.296s
user	0m47.202s
sys	0m0.059s

aiace:msgpack parallel$ time node test_unpack_msgpack.js

real	1m47.244s
user	1m47.050s
sys	0m0.120s
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numbers are self-explanatory: the MessagePack binary is &lt;em&gt;smaller&lt;/em&gt; than the minified JSON, but MessagePack deserialization is clearly &lt;em&gt;slower&lt;/em&gt; than JSON parsing process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before going on, we also need to say that all tests are executed in the following described environment and the full code of this benchmark is free available &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/salvatorecordiano/facile-it-message-pack-benchmark/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;// Machine
OS : Darwin 15.6 (x64)
RAM: 16.384 MB
CPU: 2.200 MHz Intel(R) Core(TM) i7-4770HQ CPU @ 2.20GHz

// Runtime versions
aiace:msgpack parallel$ node -v
v6.8.1
aiace:msgpack parallel$ npm -v
3.10.9

// Module versions
aiace:msgpack parallel$ npm list msgpack
benchmark-msgpack@1.0.0 /Users/parallel/Facile/msgpack
â””â”€â”€ msgpack@1.0.2

aiace:msgpack parallel$ npm list fs
benchmark-msgpack@1.0.0 /Users/parallel/Facile/msgpack
â””â”€â”€ fs@0.0.1-security

aiace:msgpack parallel$ npm list assert
benchmark-msgpack@1.0.0 /Users/parallel/Facile/msgpack
â””â”€â”€ assert@1.4.1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MessagePack allows to save more than 40% of network bandwidth consumption with little more than one line of code. A smaller payload means that less data are transmitted, and that&amp;rsquo;s very useful in &lt;strong&gt;mobile&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_of_things&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internet of Things (IoT)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; applications, where there&amp;rsquo;s special care in power efficiency; but we should also pay attention to the overall size of each request, to avoid the absurd situation in which the &lt;em&gt;header&lt;/em&gt; is larger than the &lt;em&gt;payload&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overhead_(computing)&#34;&gt;overhead&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to underline that, while MessagePack is supported by over &lt;a href=&#34;http://msgpack.org/#languages&#34;&gt;50 programming languages&lt;/a&gt;, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to be particularly efficient from a computational perspective, and can be hard to debug due to being non human-readable.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new hope for the JVM: Kotlin</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/kotlin-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/kotlin-intro/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/kotlin-intro/logo_Kotlin.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Kotlin&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;premise&#34;&gt;Premise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Java is an &lt;strong&gt;old&lt;/strong&gt; programming language. Version 1.0 was released in 1996 by Sun Microsystems and  even though it has evolved and grown a lot over the past twenty years it is still carrying on some bad design choices such as &lt;em&gt;null&lt;/em&gt; (ask &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tony_Hoare?section=3#Apologies_and_retractions&#34;&gt;Tony Hoare&lt;/a&gt;), primitive types or lack of a proper function type. With the last version of the language (Java 8) Java tried to address some of these problems introducing concepts such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.oracle.com/javase/8/docs/api/java/util/Optional.html&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/java/javaOO/lambdaexpressions.html&#34;&gt;lambda expression&lt;/a&gt;. Although these additions clearly represent a step forward for the language I still have the feeling that they are just &lt;em&gt;patches&lt;/em&gt; applied to &lt;strong&gt;mitigate problems&lt;/strong&gt; and not to solve them at their very source. For example &lt;code&gt;Optional&lt;/code&gt; could be used to reduce NPE (Null Pointer Exception) but it is clearly not designed for &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mariofusco/status/780770300178956289&#34;&gt;this purpose&lt;/a&gt; and lambda expressions, implemented in Java 8 with SAM types, still force you to write an interface only to define a &lt;em&gt;function&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-android-world&#34;&gt;The Android world&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the above concerns about Java are even more problematic within the Android world where, due to the notorious &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.android.com/about/dashboards/index.html&#34;&gt;fragmentation&lt;/a&gt; (a huge amount of devices are stuck with an &lt;strong&gt;outdated VM&lt;/strong&gt;), you are forced to target lower Java versions (6 and 7).
Google is addressing the problem with its new compiler &lt;a href=&#34;https://source.android.com/source/jack.html&#34;&gt;Jack&lt;/a&gt; that enables &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; of the features of Java 8 maintaining backward compatibility with older OS versions. But still it lets us deal with the verbosity of the language and it doesnâ€™t truly solve the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-new-hope&#34;&gt;A new hope&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/kotlin-intro/kotlin_helloworld.png&#34; alt=&#34;Kotlin Hello World!&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2011 the JetBrains team (the guys behind IntelliJ and so Android Studio) unveiled &lt;a href=&#34;https://kotlinlang.org/&#34;&gt;Kotlin&lt;/a&gt;, a new programming language that targets the JVM (and can also be compiled to JavaScript).
Kotlin is a statically-typed language that combines Object Oriented and functional features enforcing no particular philosophy of programming, and it introduces a whole new set of concepts and tools that helps making the code &lt;strong&gt;safer, cleaner and much more readable&lt;/strong&gt;.
Thanks to its nature it works everywhere Java do and it is also &lt;strong&gt;interoperable&lt;/strong&gt; with it, meaning it will not force you to rewrite the entire codebase to taste it: you can add it to your project a little at a time (&lt;a href=&#34;https://medium.com/@sergii/using-kotlin-for-tests-in-android-6d4a0c818776#.lyvd3h43x&#34;&gt;maybe starting with tests&lt;/a&gt; ðŸ˜‰). It also features a REPL &lt;code&gt;kotlinc-jvm&lt;/code&gt; that allows you to test language features with no effort (see the &lt;a href=&#34;https://kotlinlang.org/docs/tutorials/command-line.html#running-the-repl&#34;&gt;doc&lt;/a&gt; form more info).
I am going to rapidly cover some features of Kotlin that address the previously mentioned Java limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;null-safety&#34;&gt;Null-safety&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Kotlin &lt;strong&gt;a variable cannot be null&lt;/strong&gt;. If you want or need a variable to be &lt;em&gt;nullable&lt;/em&gt; you have to add &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; to the variable type:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-kotlin&#34;&gt;val x: Int = null // compile error
val y: Int? = null // ok
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to this information the compiler sees &lt;code&gt;Int&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Int?&lt;/code&gt; as two completely different types and can therefore enforce the &lt;a href=&#34;http://kotlinlang.org/docs/reference/null-safety.html&#34;&gt;null-safety&lt;/a&gt; of your variables.
The &lt;code&gt;?.&lt;/code&gt; allows you to safe call methods on nullable variables without throwing NPE but simply returning null at the end of the  call chain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-kotlin&#34;&gt;val x: Int? = null
x?.toString()?.substring(2) // no NPE, returns null
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;?:&lt;/code&gt; operator (Elvis operator) allows you to provide a â€œdefaultâ€ value when the variable is &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-kotlin&#34;&gt;// The two expressions are semantically equivalent:
text?.length ?: -1
(text.length != null) ? text.length  : -1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;higher-order-functions-and-lambdas&#34;&gt;Higher-Order Functions and Lambdas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Kotlin is possible to declare a method (or more generally a function) that returns or takes another &lt;strong&gt;function as parameter&lt;/strong&gt;. The syntax to define the &lt;a href=&#34;https://kotlinlang.org/docs/reference/lambdas.html&#34;&gt;function type&lt;/a&gt; is similar to other languages such as Scala or Swift and is very &lt;strong&gt;intuitive&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-kotlin&#34;&gt;val function: (T1, T2) -&amp;gt; R = {t1, t2 -&amp;gt; r}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;data-classes&#34;&gt;Data classes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-kotlin&#34;&gt;data class City(val name: String, val state: String)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kotlinlang.org/docs/reference/data-classes.html&#34;&gt;Data classes&lt;/a&gt; address the verbosity of Java when dealing with classes that have the only purpose to hold data. With a single line you get &lt;code&gt;equals()/hashCode()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;toString()&lt;/code&gt; and getters/setters for free (and if you are a Java developer you already knows the benefits!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Java has to maintain backward compatibility with previous versions and still has to support the huge amount of developers and codebases present all around the world; therefore it is natural that every new feature and design change is to be considered, weighted and reasoned really carefully, inevitably &lt;strong&gt;slowing down its evolution&lt;/strong&gt;. But this does not have to mean that us, as Android developers, â€œtiedâ€ to the JVM, should not try more modern and advanced languages such as Kotlin. At bottom, a part of our job (one of the best!) is to try and &lt;strong&gt;experiment&lt;/strong&gt; new technologies and to &lt;strong&gt;learn&lt;/strong&gt; new concepts and techniques that improve our ability to address problems in the best possible way (and of course, to have some fun ðŸ˜„).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that it is fundamental for a software engineer to be &lt;strong&gt;exposed to more than a single programming language&lt;/strong&gt;: learning new patterns, exploring other programming paradigms or simply using and understanding a never-seen syntax has an immeasurable value for our growth and most of the times it turns out to be unexpectedly useful even when coding with â€ourâ€ language.
So why not do it with a language that allows us to continue working on projects targeting our beloved JVM?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Event-driven serverless applications</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/event-driven-serverless-applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/event-driven-serverless-applications/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;If we think about computing in the Cloud Era, our mind is immediately drawn towards virtual machines and containers. Therefore, for example, when building a production environment with both approaches we think about the need of patching the operating system and/or upgrading the container. At the end of 2014 &lt;strong&gt;Amazon Web Services&lt;/strong&gt; (AWS) announced a new service called &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/lambda/&#34;&gt;Lambda&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;, that allows us to focus on business logic and not on infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-is-lambda&#34;&gt;What is Lambda?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As reported on their website: Â« &lt;em&gt;AWS Lambda is a serverless compute service that runs your code highly-available in the cloud in response to events and it automatically performs all the administration of the compute resources for you&lt;/em&gt; Â». In the previous sentence is condensed all the power of Lambda, that we can summarize with the following key concepts: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#serverless-architecture&#34;&gt;serverless architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#high-availability&#34;&gt;high-availability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#event-driven&#34;&gt;event-driven&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#zero-administration&#34;&gt;zero administration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/event-driven-serverless-applications/aws-lambda-key-concepts.png&#34; alt=&#34;AWS Lambda key concepts&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;serverless-architecture&#34;&gt;Serverless architecture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lambda is completely &amp;ldquo;serverless&amp;rdquo;, a term that can be considered misleading: obviously Lambda uses physical servers to run your code, but we, as the service&amp;rsquo;s users, donâ€™t take care of everything required to do it. We just need to upload our code on AWS console and it handles capacity, scaling, monitoring, logging and security without any server to manage.
Strictly speaking, functions are executed in containers, and kernel-based virtualization is very useful in this context, because it allows to build multiple isolated environments in short time.
A more detailed explanation of serverless architectures can be found &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.martinfowler.com/articles/serverless.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;high-availability&#34;&gt;High-availability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AWS Lambda maintains compute capacity across multiple availability zones in each region - at the moment there are 8 regions distributed among Americas, EMEA and Asia Pacific - in this way Lambda is able to protect your code against data center failures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;event-driven&#34;&gt;Event-driven&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Event-driven&amp;rdquo; means that a Lambda function is triggered when an event occurs, so the flow of the application is mainly driven by events. In this kind of architecture all Lambda functions are event consumers, because they are invoked by an event and they have the responsibility to process it.
An event comes to life, for example, whenever:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a new item is created on an Amazon DynamoDB table;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a file is deleted on an Amazon S3 bucket;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an Amazon API Gateway is called;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;et cetera&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but we can also use AWS SDK to invoke a function directly on a mobile or web app back-end.
This is a good way to write application logic without designing and maintaining a centralized workflow.
More about event-driven programming &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Event-driven_programming&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;zero-administration&#34;&gt;Zero administration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the work you usually need to do in order to assure that your application works in a scalable, reliable and durable way is taken care by the service itself.  Behind the scenes the system performs all the needed administration for the compute resources, including server and operating system maintenance, code and security patch deployment, code monitoring and logging, and automatically matches the incoming rate of functions invocation for us, to assure capacity provisioning and automatic scaling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;lambda-functions&#34;&gt;Lambda functions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code we run on AWS Lambda is called a &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;lambda function&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;rdquo;. The name &amp;ldquo;lambda&amp;rdquo; derives from the 11th letter of the Greek alphabet. In general a &lt;em&gt;lambda&lt;/em&gt;, also called &lt;em&gt;anonymous function&lt;/em&gt;, is a function that&amp;rsquo;s defined inline (sometimes called &lt;em&gt;closure&lt;/em&gt;) and passed to some other function, method or procedure, to be stored or executed: the &lt;em&gt;anonymity&lt;/em&gt; is given by the fact that we don&amp;rsquo;t give a name to the function, but we just define it at the moment of need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;supported-languages&#34;&gt;Supported languages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now Lambda functions natively support code written in &lt;strong&gt;Java&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Node.js&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Python&lt;/strong&gt;, but we can run C, Go and PHP using a Node.js wrapper. Hopefully Amazon will add official support for other languages such as PHP, Go, C, Swift and many more. We can also include libraries, even native ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;stateless-code&#34;&gt;Stateless code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we write a function our code must be &lt;strong&gt;stateless&lt;/strong&gt;, thus everything begins and ends in the same request, and any persistent state is stored in a storage service (not necessarily within Amazon world). Keeping functions stateless is the keystone to enable the system to instantly launch new instances when needed, to serve the incoming events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the code, each Lambda function has many configuration informations, such as name, description, runtime, handler, memory, max execution time and execution role. A detailed explanation is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/lambda/latest/dg/lambda-introduction-function.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;invocation-types&#34;&gt;Invocation types&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can invoke a Lambda function directly, for example using the Invoke API, or indirectly, for example using the Amazon API Gateway. A function invocation needs to specify the &lt;code&gt;InvocationType&lt;/code&gt;. There are three invocation types allowed: &lt;code&gt;RequestResponse&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Event&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;DryRun&lt;/code&gt;. Each one of them has different purposes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;RequestResponse&lt;/code&gt;: in this case we expect a &lt;strong&gt;synchronous&lt;/strong&gt; behavior. The function receives input parameters as an event, and returns a result;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;Event&lt;/code&gt;: in this case we expect an &lt;strong&gt;asynchronous&lt;/strong&gt; behavior. The function receives input parameters as an event, returns immediately no value, but continues its execution asynchronously;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;DryRun&lt;/code&gt;: it&amp;rsquo;s used to verify the access to a function without running it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/event-driven-serverless-applications/synchronous-vs-asynchronous-behaviour.png&#34; alt=&#34;Synchronous vs asynchronous behaviour&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;lambda-alternatives&#34;&gt;Lambda alternatives&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serverless is a new cloud computing trend, and accordingly many cloud providers â€“ in addition to Amazon - started offering their own &lt;em&gt;Function as a Service&lt;/em&gt; (FaaS), for example &lt;strong&gt;Google&lt;/strong&gt; with its &lt;a href=&#34;https://cloud.google.com/functions/&#34;&gt;Cloud Functions&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;IBM&lt;/strong&gt; with its &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.ibm.com/openwhisk/&#34;&gt;OpenWhisk&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Auth0&lt;/strong&gt; with its &lt;a href=&#34;https://webtask.io/&#34;&gt;WebTasks&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Microsoft&lt;/strong&gt; with its &lt;a href=&#34;https://functions.azure.com/&#34;&gt;Azure Functions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Functions are very useful when we want to build lightweight applications based on &lt;em&gt;microservices&lt;/em&gt; with no server. Their approach could be considered a way to achieve fine-grained microservices, in which there is a relation one-to-one between functions and endpoints instead of one service per one resource: for this reason they are often referred to as &lt;em&gt;nanoservices&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They could help developers in focusing on the code, while only charging for code really running in an infrastructure that&amp;rsquo;s able to autonomously grow upon demand, without lots of efforts in managing it. With functions, we can see our code as a series of small and independent building blocks, that can be easily replaced or connected with other blocks using events. Also, Lamba could help small team in reusing existing skills while adopting different languages, in order to develop software that better matches business&amp;rsquo; requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How PHP 7 &amp; TDD helped me sleep better</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/how-php-7-tdd-helped-me-sleep-better/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/how-php-7-tdd-helped-me-sleep-better/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-enemies-of-programming&#34;&gt;The enemies of programming&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many of you will agree with me, &lt;strong&gt;sleep deprivation&lt;/strong&gt; is the enemy of programming.&lt;br /&gt;
Maybe we fear only one thing more than that: &lt;strong&gt;being interrupted&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;http://heeris.id.au/2013/this-is-why-you-shouldnt-interrupt-a-programmer/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/how-php-7-tdd-helped-me-sleep-better/interruption.png&#34; alt=&#34;Why you shouldn&#39;t interrupt a programmer (by Jason Heeris)&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While writing code we have to think really hard, we use complex abstractions, we go through long business workflows and so on&amp;hellip; fatigue and interruptions are the main enemies of those in this line of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-experience&#34;&gt;My experience&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my day job, I do all this mental juggling on a pretty big project, which is based on PHP 5.5, Symfony 2.8, Doctrine etc.; luckily, in this project we use a good deal of &lt;strong&gt;good practices&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;automated software testing&lt;/strong&gt; is one of those. I actually switched to this job to learn about doing automatic testing, continuous integration and other best practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost half a year ago &lt;strong&gt;I became a dad&lt;/strong&gt;. It has been great, and you also get some unexpected perks! For example, my colleagues got me this gift for my son:
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/how-php-7-tdd-helped-me-sleep-better/blue-elephpant.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A blue elePHPant!&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we can say that his future is pretty clear&amp;hellip; But don&amp;rsquo;t say this to my wife!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the pregnancy, many of my friends and fellow parents warned me half jokingly about one thing: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;sleep now, you&amp;rsquo;ll be deadly tired after!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. Now I can say that they were a bit exaggerating, but I can&amp;rsquo;t deny that, having a child takes a toll on your sleep schedule&amp;hellip; Even if, as in my case having a 9 to 6 office job, my wonderful wife does all the parenting heavy lifting (and I consider myself pretty lucky for having her!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months after my son was born I also had the opportunity to start &lt;strong&gt;a new, fresh project&lt;/strong&gt;. To be completely honest, it was not actually fresh: it was a &lt;strong&gt;complete rewrite&lt;/strong&gt; of an internal service that&amp;rsquo;s used to manage the invoices for multiple business units inside our company. I knew pretty well that the old system had to be replaced, so I was put in charge of redoing it from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the issue with the old system (and the main reason behind the rewrite) was &lt;strong&gt;maintainability&lt;/strong&gt;: we had no tests, we had no proper development environment, and its design wasn&amp;rsquo;t that great; also, bureaucracy and invoicing are the core domain of the system, so it was inherently complex. It was the perfect environment to witness the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broken_windows_theory&#34;&gt;broken windows theory&lt;/a&gt; in action: the code base got worse over time, one patch, copy paste or quick fix at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, as anyone that&amp;rsquo;s passionate in technology would do, I took the opportunity to use a lot of new shiny tools: I picked &lt;strong&gt;PHP 7&lt;/strong&gt;, which had just been released, and started the project with something familiar to me but still pretty new and cool, &lt;strong&gt;Symfony 3.0&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-i-found-to-be-useful&#34;&gt;What I found to be useful&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rambled and thought about this project a lot in the past months with my colleagues, because the old system was costing us a lot of overhead in usage and maintenance, and we had a pretty clear idea of what its problems were, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t need to study a lot before starting to write the first classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, I had to spend &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; time thinking about an object oriented design for my project, but I was rapidly able to start writing code with confidence. In the end, most of this confidence came from a few choices that I pursued during the development of this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tdd-and-high-coverage&#34;&gt;TDD and high coverage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first choice that I am pretty satisfied about is &lt;strong&gt;automatic testing&lt;/strong&gt;: I already knew the advantages of doing tests and Test Driven Development, but in the previous project that practice was not introduced from the start, so not all the codebase was covered, and we couldn&amp;rsquo;t (or wouldn&amp;rsquo;t?) do TDD 100% of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case instead &lt;strong&gt;I wanted to write nearly everything with TDD&lt;/strong&gt;, and keep a &lt;strong&gt;very high threshold for the minimum coverage&lt;/strong&gt; achieved through automatic testing. Right now I&amp;rsquo;m sitting on a ~92% test coverage, and I feel proud about it. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t a mere &amp;ldquo;let&amp;rsquo;s hit 100%!&amp;rdquo; mindless goal (&lt;a href=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/software-testing-coverage-vs-efficacia/&#34;&gt;since it&amp;rsquo;s pointless&lt;/a&gt;), but it fueled &lt;strong&gt;a positive feedback cycle&lt;/strong&gt; instead: the more I used TDD in writing new classes, the more the coverage rose and stayed high; at the same time, I found myself inspecting the coverage reports to find missing spots, and that allowed me to discover many edge-cases that I didn&amp;rsquo;t test and should have been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I still left some parts without coverage or specific tests, since it was pointless to test them (e.g. Doctrine entities), while I covered some parts multiple times, since they were &lt;strong&gt;critical paths&lt;/strong&gt; inside my application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-tests-to-the-rescue&#34;&gt;Unit tests to the rescue!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, the main critical advantage that TDD gave me was &lt;strong&gt;focus even on strained days&lt;/strong&gt;: I wrote the classes starting from unit tests, giving all my effort to one piece of code at a time, without having to keep in mind the entire project with its complexities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then wrote some functional tests to assure that the &lt;strong&gt;collaboration between my unit-tested objects&lt;/strong&gt; was fine, and this later step was also useful in delaying the definition of the classes as services inside the Symfony DI container. I was also &lt;strong&gt;able to change my mind&lt;/strong&gt; a few times on some details of the design without having to suffer mental confusion or rewrite too much code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;php-7-scalar-and-return-types-declarations&#34;&gt;PHP 7: scalar and return types declarations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second good choice was &lt;strong&gt;PHP 7&lt;/strong&gt;: among the reasons behind it as the language version of choice for this project were the &lt;a href=&#34;http://php.net/manual/en/migration70.new-features.php&#34;&gt;two main new features&lt;/a&gt; introduced: &lt;strong&gt;scalar types&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;return type declarations&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/how-php-7-tdd-helped-me-sleep-better/return-types-everywhere-meme.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Return types, return types everywhere!&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Facile.it, I worked as C++ developer, and oh boy! did I miss scalars and return types!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I came onboard of the PHP community right on time&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, I thought&amp;hellip; So I took advantage of the situation to start using all these new features. I enjoyed having again the possibility to typehint strings and integers; I discovered how return types declaration enforces the cohesion of your objects really well, making it &lt;strong&gt;rightly painful to return different things&lt;/strong&gt;: it became impossible to return &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; OR &lt;em&gt;null&lt;/em&gt;, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, in my tests I found myself writing a lot of this kind of code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$result = $testClass-&amp;gt;method();
$this-&amp;gt;assertInstanceOf(SomeClass::class, $result);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did this more than once, just to realize that I was wasting my time! This was normally the first TDD step on PHP 5.x code, but now this kinds of assertion were futile, because the return type was already checked at a language level! Great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Return types also proved themselves to be a &lt;strong&gt;double-edged sword&lt;/strong&gt; in some cases, especially on Doctrine entities: they are really useful to enforce consistency in your values, since they trigger a &lt;code&gt;\TypeError&lt;/code&gt; each time you call a getter method on a erroneously empty property, but &lt;strong&gt;you can&amp;rsquo;t use them on nullable fields&lt;/strong&gt;, since it will break your application at any time during execution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, having return types declared on your business-logic classes it&amp;rsquo;s pretty useful, even more when used in conjunction with TDD: every time you define a mock you are forced to declare expectations and predictions with the right types, so it &lt;strong&gt;indirectly helps maintaining the collaboration contract between objects&lt;/strong&gt;, without too much hassle. If I changed a method&amp;rsquo;s signature that was mocked somewhere, the mock would break the test, &lt;strong&gt;highlighting the issue and making the tests&lt;/strong&gt; (and an high coverage) &lt;strong&gt;even more valuable&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, these and other &lt;strong&gt;good practices are helpful&lt;/strong&gt; for both your job and your personal life: you can go a long way in being fit and in the best shape while working, but stressful and (good) distracting events are unavoidable: you&amp;rsquo;ll often have to fight stress, fatigue or distractions, and there will be days where you can&amp;rsquo;t be at the top of your game, for any number of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since programming is a mental job, I think that having instruments and good practices in your toolset is invaluable, being them the &lt;strong&gt;essential tools of our craft&lt;/strong&gt;. Thus, I hope that those little life/programming lessons I learned in these months will be useful to other people like me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>