<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>jean on Facile.it Engineering</title>
    <link>https://engineering.facile.it/authors/jean/</link>
    <description>Recent content in jean on Facile.it Engineering</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://engineering.facile.it/authors/jean/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How to gradually upgrade toward PHPUnit 6 with namespaced classes</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/phpunit-upgrade-namespace/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/phpunit-upgrade-namespace/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In the latest months I wrote multiple times, in different projects, code migrating &lt;strong&gt;PHPUnit&lt;/strong&gt; toward major &lt;strong&gt;version 6&lt;/strong&gt;. This upgrade is harder than the previous one, since in this version it was introduced a big breaking change: &lt;strong&gt;all classes got (finally!) namespaced&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that any usage of those classes in your project needs to be updated. It may seem a simple find &amp;amp; replace job, but since you need to introduce at least one &lt;code&gt;use PHPUnit\Framework\TestCase&lt;/code&gt; line at the top of each one of your test classes, it&amp;rsquo;s a boring and a little more than trivial task; also, &lt;strong&gt;upgrading it in a single big jump may not be feasible or prudent&lt;/strong&gt;, especially in the case of open source or distributed libraries, where backward compatibility and support for old PHP versions must be ensured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article I will explain which steps I applied during those migrations, highlighting the most frequent hiccups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-easy-one-only-tests&#34;&gt;The easy one: only tests&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start with, you have to find all the &lt;strong&gt;usages of PHPUnit classes&lt;/strong&gt; in your project: a simple search for every occurrence of the string &lt;code&gt;PHPUnit_&lt;/code&gt; should be enough at the beginning. You should know that, in some recent versions previous to 6, PHPUnit delivers a &lt;strong&gt;forward compatibility&lt;/strong&gt; layer; this means that some of the most extended classes in the library are present also in the namespaced version, so they can be used before upgrading to the fully namespaced version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to update a simple project, where the only usage of PHPUnit classes is to create tests, you are very lucky. You need to require at &lt;strong&gt;minimum PHPUnit 4.8.35 or 5.4.3&lt;/strong&gt;, which includes the FC class &lt;code&gt;PHPUnit\Framework\TestCase&lt;/code&gt; as an alias for &lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit_Framework_TestCase&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should choose the &lt;strong&gt;newest version as possible&lt;/strong&gt;, and that depends on which minimum version of PHP you want to support: if you work with (at least) PHP 5.6, you can use PHPUnit 5, otherwise you&amp;rsquo;re forced to use version 4.8.35. If you&amp;rsquo;re working on a (open source) library that needs to support both, you can do this in your &lt;code&gt;composer.json&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;{
  &amp;quot;require-dev&amp;quot;: {
    &amp;quot;phpunit/phpunit&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;^4.8.35|^5.4.0&amp;quot;  
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way you can use both, and Composer will choose the most updated one, depending on which PHP version you are using; this is &lt;strong&gt;pretty useful for testing with a CI tool&lt;/strong&gt; like Travis, since you should run your tests at least on the lowest and highest versions of PHP that you want to support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have required and installed the right version, the only modification that you need to do in your code is this one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;?php

class MyTest extends \PHPUnit_Framework_TestCase
{
    // ...
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;?php

use PHPUnit\Framework\TestCase;

class MyTest extends TestCase
{
    // ...
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;deprecations-of-phpunit-4&#34;&gt;Deprecations of PHPUnit 4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on your codebase, you may be forced to do one last step: your tests may be &lt;strong&gt;using deprecated methods from PHPUnit 4&lt;/strong&gt;, so you will need to fix those. Those issues are pretty easy to be found and fixed, because they will make your test fail when executed with PHPUnit 5. The full list of changes that may impact you are in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sebastianbergmann/phpunit/blob/5.7/ChangeLog-5.0.md#500---2015-10-02&#34;&gt;changelog for version 5.0.0&lt;/a&gt;, but the most notable ones are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you need to declare a whitelist in your &lt;code&gt;phpunit.xml&lt;/code&gt; configuration file to collect tests coverage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you must drop any usage of the &lt;code&gt;assertSelectCount()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;assertSelectRegExp()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;assertSelectEquals()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;assertTag()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;assertNotTag()&lt;/code&gt; assertions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bumpy-one-implementing-a-testlistener&#34;&gt;The bumpy one: implementing a TestListener&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If in your project you extend other classes or interfaces from PHPUnit, you need to check which one. If we are talking about one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit_Framework_Assert&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit_Framework_AssertionFailedError&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit_Framework_Test&lt;/code&gt; (interface)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit_Framework_TestSuite&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; then your only requirement is to &lt;strong&gt;use at least PHPUnit 5.7.21&lt;/strong&gt;. This means that you have to drop support to any PHP version older than 5.6, if you still support it (and you should!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, instead, you implement a &lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit_Framework_TestListener&lt;/code&gt;, that may be a little trickier. The FC layer for that class is &lt;strong&gt;problematic&lt;/strong&gt;, since it&amp;rsquo;s an interface that has a lot of types applied to the methods&amp;rsquo; arguments; this, combined with the fact that in PHP you cannot change the type of an argument when extending (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Covariance_and_contravariance_(computer_science)&#34;&gt;covariance and contravariance&lt;/a&gt;), means that the FC class is nearly useless: &lt;strong&gt;you cannot be compatible with both&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit_Framework_TestListener&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;\PHPUnit\Framework\TestListener&lt;/code&gt; with the same class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are working on a &lt;strong&gt;single project&lt;/strong&gt;, you may just restrict the supported PHPUnit version and jump to the newest one while upgrading the listener too. But if you are working on a library, and you do not want to apply that restriction to your end users, it gets a little complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, while upgrading &lt;code&gt;facile-it/paraunit&lt;/code&gt;, I preferred &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/issues/54#issuecomment-302906556&#34;&gt;jumping from supporting 4.x/5.x directly to 6.x&lt;/a&gt;; Paraunit works directly on top of PHPUnit, and it works the same before and after this update (apart from new features), so &lt;strong&gt;dropping the old versions altogether&lt;/strong&gt; seemed a good enough approach for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other cases, the listener is just provided as an additional help of the main library, so &lt;strong&gt;forcing the end user&lt;/strong&gt; to update his version of PHPUnit alongside with our library could be &lt;strong&gt;too harsh&lt;/strong&gt; or slow down the adoption of the new release. I tried doing this on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/FriendsOfSymfony/FOSHttpCache/pull/365&#34;&gt;with a pull reques on &lt;code&gt;friendsofsymfony/http-cache&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, where I had to solve this specific issue. The &lt;strong&gt;only feasible solution&lt;/strong&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;ve found is this &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/symfony/phpunit-bridge/blob/3c0efb8609a32890a767bbbd39198a0e92572694/SymfonyTestsListener.php#L19&#34;&gt;specific snippet of code&lt;/a&gt;, that it was used in &lt;code&gt;symfony/phpunit-bridge&lt;/code&gt; to overcome the same problem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;if (
    class_exists(&#39;PHPUnit_Runner_Version&#39;) 
    &amp;amp;&amp;amp; version_compare(\PHPUnit_Runner_Version::id(), &#39;6.0.0&#39;, &#39;&amp;lt;&#39;)
) {
    class_alias(&#39;Legacy\MyTestListener&#39;, &#39;MyTestListener&#39;);
// Using an early return instead of a else does not work 
// when using the PHPUnit phar due to some weird PHP behavior 
// (the class gets defined without executing the code before it 
// and so the definition is not properly conditional)
} else {
    class MyTestListener extends BaseTestListener
    {
        // ...
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach is based on writing two versions of the listener, one (inside a &lt;code&gt;legacy&lt;/code&gt; subfolder) which implements the old interface, the other that implements the new, namespaced one. With the above snippet, PHP is tricked into loading the right one, after checking if the loaded version of PHPUnit is lower than 6.0. In this way &lt;strong&gt;the end user can ignore the difference between the two classes&lt;/strong&gt;, use only the new class name and go on, since they will be switched in a hidden and automatic way.
Once support for the old PHP and PHPUnit versions is dropped, this trick can be dropped too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-next-step-from-5-to-6&#34;&gt;The next step: from 5 to 6&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once all this migration is completed, and all the tests are green under all needed conditions, we can plan for the next step, &lt;strong&gt;upgrading to PHPUnit 6&lt;/strong&gt;. In reality, this step depends on a bigger, previous step: &lt;strong&gt;migrate to PHP 7&lt;/strong&gt;, because lower versions are no longer supported with PHPUnit 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When your project is ready for PHP 7, you can require the installation of PHPUnit 6; if you are working on a library that wants to support PHP 5.6 too, you can use the same trick as above in your &lt;code&gt;composer.json&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-json&#34;&gt;{
  &amp;quot;require-dev&amp;quot;: {
    &amp;quot;phpunit/phpunit&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;^5.4.0|^6.0&amp;quot;  
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; so you&amp;rsquo;ll be using PHPUnit 5 under PHP 5.6, and 6 with PHP 7.0+. As before, you need to check that your tests are still passing, and avoid using any functionality that is deprecated in PHPUnit 5. You can find the full list in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sebastianbergmann/phpunit/blob/6.0/ChangeLog-6.0.md#600---2017-02-03&#34;&gt;PHPUnit changelog for 6.0.0&lt;/a&gt;, but the most notable are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;getMock()&lt;/code&gt; must be replaced with &lt;code&gt;createMock()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;usages of &lt;code&gt;getMockWithoutInvokingTheOriginalConstructor()&lt;/code&gt; are no longer needed, it&amp;rsquo;s the default behavior now&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if you intervene on global variables, it&amp;rsquo;s better to enable the &lt;code&gt;--globals-backup&lt;/code&gt; option, to save and restore them between tests (previously it was the default behavior)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;setExpectedException()&lt;/code&gt; must be replaced:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;// before
$this-&amp;gt;setExpectedException(Exception::class, $message);
// after
$this-&amp;gt;expectException(Exception::class);
$this-&amp;gt;expectExceptionMessage($message);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s all! I hope to make you save enough time and migraines with this little guide. Happy coding!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why type hints and interfaces are not visual debt</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/visual-debt-typehints/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/visual-debt-typehints/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago I stumbled on a strange tweet that was highlighting a controversy about scalar type hints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;it&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Scalar type hints &amp;amp; return types vs no scalar type hints &amp;amp; return types is &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/PHP?src=hash&#34;&gt;#PHP&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s new spaces vs tabs&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Cees-Jan 🔊 Kiewiet (@WyriHaximus) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/WyriHaximus/status/865524687257862144&#34;&gt;19 maggio 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After asking references about this, someone alluded to this very short video: &lt;a href=&#34;https://laracasts.com/series/php-bits/episodes/1&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;PHP Bits: Visual Debt&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (it&amp;rsquo;s only 3 minutes, please watch it before continue reading). After that, the author of the video was dragged into the conversation, and it blew up into a big tweetstorm in the following few hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core of the controversy was the fact that the author of the video classified as &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;visual debt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; a lot of stuff in his PHP example, like interfaces, scalar type hints and the final keyword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-opinion-on-the-matter&#34;&gt;My opinion on the matter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can agree with the bottom line of the video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am I necessarily getting a benefit [&amp;hellip;] ?  Question everything&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every choice in our line of work is always a &lt;strong&gt;trade-off&lt;/strong&gt; between benefits and cons, and every new introduction in a projects should be evaluated and agreed upon between team members. But my personal preference leans a lot towards the opposite side in this specific matter: as I stated in a &lt;a href=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/how-php-7-tdd-helped-me-sleep-better/&#34;&gt;previous blog post here&lt;/a&gt;, I love the new additions that PHP 7 brought to us like scalar and return type hints, and I use them as often as I can, because I discovered that &lt;strong&gt;they bring a lot of benefits&lt;/strong&gt; to the code that I write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably this was influenced by the fact that previously I worked with C++, where types are a lot more intrusive compared with PHP 5; but over time and with usage, I learned the great benefits that we can achieve with this addition to our PHP 7 codebases. In general, I think that type hints, and other language features that create a more &amp;ldquo;rigid&amp;rdquo; code, are &lt;strong&gt;helpful during the evolution of a codebase&lt;/strong&gt;, and so they are really needed in long-running projects, where the maintainability of code is crucial. It may be less true in a &amp;ldquo;release and forget&amp;rdquo; type of project, but I think that it would still be like betting againt oneself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post I would like to explain myself and the reasons behind my arguments, recounting them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;scalar-type-hints-as-safeguards&#34;&gt;Scalar type hints as safeguards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the video, the example had all along this class:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;class Event implements EventInterface
{
    protected $events = [];
    
    public function listen(string $name, callable $handler): void
    {
        $this-&amp;gt;events[$name][] = $handler;
    }

    public function fire(string $name): bool
    {
        if (! array_key_exists($name, $this-&amp;gt;events)) {
            return false;
        }
        
        foreach($this-&amp;gt;events[$name] as $event) {
            $event();
        }

        return true;
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author suggests to remove all type hints, since the code should still work and you could get rid of a lot of additional, not needed complications. I disagree completely with this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Type hints are safeguards&lt;/strong&gt; here, because they let you reduce to the bare minimum all the checks that you should do here before accepting the input arguments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;because it&amp;rsquo;s used as a key for an array, &lt;code&gt;$name&lt;/code&gt; can only be a string (or an int, but it would not make sense)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;code&gt;events&lt;/code&gt; property can only accept callables, because its elements are invoked inside the foreach of the &lt;code&gt;fire()&lt;/code&gt; method&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;because we don&amp;rsquo;t need to insert additional &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt;s in our methods, we &lt;strong&gt;reduce the number of possible paths of execution&lt;/strong&gt;, hence reducing the number of cases that we need to check in our tests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;type-hints-and-interfaces-as-contracts&#34;&gt;Type hints and interfaces as contracts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the video, it was suggested to also get rid of the interface:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;interface EventInterface
{
    public function listen(string $name, callable $handler): void;

    public function fire(string $name): bool;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree that &lt;strong&gt;an interface should be written only if needed&lt;/strong&gt;, like if you want to write multiple concrete implementation of it with different inheritance hierarchy. But this doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that we will not have any interface at all: we still have the concrete implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not the same of having a pure interface, but we will still be able to determine a &lt;strong&gt;contract&lt;/strong&gt;, a list of method signatures that tells us what that object will accept as valid method calls. This kind of contracts are a must in object oriented programming, because they dictate how your object will interconnect, communicate and cooperate, and they are especially useful in combination with stricter type hints and &lt;strong&gt;unit testing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we write unit test, we use the real instance of the class which is under test, and everything else should be mocked. That means that we will use some test mocking library (i.e. I prefer &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/phpspec/prophecy&#34;&gt;Prophecy&lt;/a&gt;, which is included in PHPUnit) to mimick the behavior of nearby objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How type hints would help us in this case? If we would have to mock the &lt;code&gt;EventInterface&lt;/code&gt; (or the concrete class, it&amp;rsquo;s unimportant here), having the return type hints for example would help us in &lt;strong&gt;writing good mocks&lt;/strong&gt;, and not wrong ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how? Nearly every mocking library creates a mock extending at runtime the original class, since the mock needs to pass every check and type hint as if it was the original class; this means that it can&amp;rsquo;t change the method signature, hence preserving the original return type hint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will translate in errors and test failures if we would write a mock that doesn&amp;rsquo;t return the proper type, like in this example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;class Person
{
    public function shout(): bool
    {
        $event = new Event();
        if ($event-&amp;gt;fire(&#39;shout&#39;)) {
            // someone was listening!
            return true;
        }
        // ...
    }
}

class PersonTest extends PHPUnit\Framework\TestCase
{
    public function testShout()
    {
        $event = $this-&amp;gt;prophesize(EventInterface::class);
        $event-&amp;gt;fire(&#39;shout&#39;)
            -&amp;gt;shouldBeCalled();
        // ...
        
        $person = new Person();
        $person-&amp;gt;shout();
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34;&gt;$ phpunit
# ...
1) PersonTest::testShout
TypeError: Return value of Double\EventInterface\P2118::fire() must be a string, null returned
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mock, once used, &lt;strong&gt;will make the test fail&lt;/strong&gt;. Why? Because the &lt;code&gt;fire()&lt;/code&gt; method can only return a boolean, and by default (if not instructed differently) Prophecy&amp;rsquo;s mocks will return &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt;. Without the &lt;code&gt;: bool&lt;/code&gt; return type hint, the mock would return &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt; but the test would not fail, and the class under test would silently cast or interpret the return value as &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;, possibly causing an unintended behavior or a false positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that having complete type hints in your interfaces and method signatures only &lt;strong&gt;makes your code more cohesive and your unit test more robust&lt;/strong&gt;; this kind of enforcing helps a lot also with refactoring, since changing a method&amp;rsquo;s signature would cause failures in all the related tests that include a mock of that interface, as it could become inconsistent and unreliable after this change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;use-interfaces-as-behavior-checks&#34;&gt;Use interfaces as behavior checks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the counter example that popped up during the discussion on Twitter was this one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;class Fireman
{
    // ...
}

class Building
{
    public function putOutFire(Fireman $fireman);
}

$building-&amp;gt;putOutFire(new StrongAndAblePerson()); // type error!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was cited to show how sometimes type hints can be a hindrance more that something helpful in your code: why a strong, capable person shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to put out a fire? Who&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;code&gt;Building&lt;/code&gt; class to decide that? Are we maybe violating the Single Responsibility Principle?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that this is misguided for a simple reason: it was &lt;strong&gt;wrong to check against a concrete implementation&lt;/strong&gt; instead of an interface; and that&amp;rsquo;s not evident because, in my opinion, the example was &lt;strong&gt;cut too short&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s speculate on the content of the &lt;code&gt;putOutFire()&lt;/code&gt; method:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;class Building
{
    public function putOutFire(Fireman $fireman)
    {
        $fireman-&amp;gt;wearProtectiveGear();
        $fireman-&amp;gt;shootWaterAtFlames();
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why we have a type hint in the &lt;code&gt;putOutFire()&lt;/code&gt; method? Surely because we want to rely on some method that a &lt;code&gt;Fireman&lt;/code&gt; instance would give to us in the method body (i.e. the &lt;code&gt;wearProtectiveGear()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;shootWaterAtFlames()&lt;/code&gt;); if we remove the type hint, we would have no guarantees that those methods exists on the argument, and we would have to either use a &lt;code&gt;method_exists()&lt;/code&gt; call twice (oh, the horror!) or expose our &lt;code&gt;Building&lt;/code&gt; class to a possible fatal error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take the example further, we can make the &lt;code&gt;StrongAndAblePerson&lt;/code&gt; capable of put out a fire if we &lt;strong&gt;extract the needed methods in an interface&lt;/strong&gt;, defining a contract of what our &lt;code&gt;putOutFire()&lt;/code&gt; needs to know and use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;interface TrainedFireFighter
{
    public function wearProtectiveGear(): void;
    public function shootWaterAtFlames(): void;
}

class StrongAndAblePerson implements TrainedFireFighter { ... }
class Fireman implements TrainedFireFighter { ... }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; now we can have the &lt;code&gt;putOutFire()&lt;/code&gt; method with a broader type hint, that would accept both a &lt;code&gt;Fireman&lt;/code&gt; and any other class that implements the &lt;code&gt;TrainedFireFighter&lt;/code&gt; interface:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-php&#34;&gt;class Building
{
    public function putOutFire(TrainedFireFighter $firefighter)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-final-keyword&#34;&gt;The final keyword&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only point of the video which I find relatable is the remark on the &lt;code&gt;final&lt;/code&gt; keyword.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the funny joke (&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m not your daddy!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;), I find the final keyword &lt;strong&gt;not very usable in closed projects&lt;/strong&gt;, since its only usefulness is to impede the extension of some object. When the persons that could work on a codebase are well known and they can be coordinated, I think it&amp;rsquo;s better to leave that liberty to the coders, and just have an agreement on what can and cannot be done with that class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, this keyword becomes useful when we are talking about &lt;strong&gt;open sourced code&lt;/strong&gt;: using it is a clear statement that reduces the surface of the API that the library is exposing to end users, in the same way &lt;code&gt;private&lt;/code&gt; is limiting access to properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Straightforwardly, the maintainer of the code is saying that this class is not extensible, because it may change internally without notice; this concept is also well explained by Marco Pivetta in his signature &amp;ldquo;Extremely defensive PHP&amp;rdquo; talk (which we cited also in our &lt;a href=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/php-day-2017/&#34;&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ocramius.github.io/extremely-defensive-php/#/90&#34;&gt;see related slide here&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://ocramius.github.io/blog/when-to-declare-classes-final/&#34;&gt;in his blog post about it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-practical-example&#34;&gt;A practical example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to conclude this blog post with a practical example. I maintain &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/&#34;&gt;facile-it/paraunit&lt;/a&gt;, a parallelization tool that works on top of PHPUnit. In the past few days I was working on supporting PHPUnit v6, and that lead to bumping the minimum PHP supported version of the package to 7.0: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/pull/93&#34;&gt;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/pull/93&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since previously the minimum supported version was PHP 5.3, I took the opportunity to go over the whole codebase and clean it up, using all the new language features that I could now take for granted: &lt;code&gt;::class&lt;/code&gt; shortcuts, array short syntax, but more importantly the aforementioned &lt;strong&gt;scalar and return type hints&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the perfect example to show that adding those type hints on already working code made a &lt;strong&gt;non-trivial difference&lt;/strong&gt; even if I wasn&amp;rsquo;t changing the objects&amp;rsquo; behavior, and it forced me to fix some of this stuff:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it forced me &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/pull/93/files#diff-049f05e192bb0dcb9cf59ad2bbd43ceaR79&#34;&gt;to define more explicitly a default behavior&lt;/a&gt;, since a &lt;code&gt;null&lt;/code&gt; was no longer accepted in place of a string&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this also lead me to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/pull/93/commits/6aa9286256ed47c7b4500b990e030588b18b7770&#34;&gt;write an additional test&lt;/a&gt; for an uncovered, very common case&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it made me realize that I had &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/pull/93/files#diff-f3225dfaa1d4e63e21a7e51880c63bbbR40&#34;&gt;a regex silently failing&lt;/a&gt; returning a bad result, and I had to take better care of it, leading to a simpler and more robust approach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this lead to &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/pull/93/commits/b5463b122e87f14dbaf6fa2ff78ba53f14ae737a#diff-59b76fc4702a8549daa568e542d71498R42&#34;&gt;additional tests too&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it made me discover a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit/pull/93/commits/61c786c6faa0020465abd8243ee1415883193a94#diff-4fd831bf7fb1767a7a49e0954a98fb05R98&#34;&gt;specific behavior of the SPL file iterator classes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;strict-types-enforcing&#34;&gt;Strict types enforcing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last part of this PR, I also added the &lt;code&gt;declare(strict_types=1)&lt;/code&gt; directive everywhere in my code. This directive changes the behavior of type hints: with it, passed values are no longer silently casted (if possible) to the type-hinted, required type, but instead they &lt;strong&gt;trigger an immediate error if the type doesn&amp;rsquo;t match&lt;/strong&gt;; for example, passing a &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;10&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; string into a &lt;code&gt;int&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;float&lt;/code&gt; type hint will no longer trigger an automatic conversion to &lt;code&gt;10&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;10.0&lt;/code&gt;, but trigger an error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would admit that this is a matter of personal preference, and I would not suggest to use this everywhere, especially if there isn&amp;rsquo;t a very thorough test coverage; it may lead to unneeded failures in very unsuspecting places, and it may cause friction when intergrating code with external libraries that take advantage of the implicit type casting that PHP has always done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even in this little use case, &lt;a href=&#34;https://travis-ci.org/facile-it/paraunit/jobs/236293288&#34;&gt;it lead to discover a small issue&lt;/a&gt; with an outdated test code, were I was &lt;strong&gt;passing an empty string instead of a boolean&lt;/strong&gt;: that happened because I refactored a constructor some time ago, and I forgot to update the tests, and I missed it since the &lt;strong&gt;tests were not failing&lt;/strong&gt;. The error was even well highlighted by my IDE now, but before it was casted silently to a bool, and it matched the expected behavior by sheer luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/visual-debt-typehints/phpstorm-error-highlight.png&#34; alt=&#34;The error highlighted in PHPStorm&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Type hints and other new PHP language construct help writing more cohesive, rigid code, that may lead to some &amp;ldquo;pain&amp;rdquo; while writing code and (mostly) tests; but this effort is just &lt;strong&gt;paying in advance&lt;/strong&gt;: a lot of bugs get discovered earlier, and refactoring and changing code become easier, since pieces of code that doesn&amp;rsquo;t match anymore are more visible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the example PR, the amount of changed code that is not method signatures is trivial, but I drastically reduced the amount of possible deviations that my code could take if a wrong value is passed through it, and I fixed and tested a few additional cases that I was forgetting about. Also, the usage of the &lt;code&gt;declare(strict_types=1)&lt;/code&gt; enforces even further this approach, raising the confidence that I have in the codebase.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Facile.it devs @ phpDay 2017</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/php-day-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/php-day-2017/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Like clockwork, on May we head up to Verona to attend the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://2017.phpday.it/&#34;&gt;phpDay conference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;; this time it was on &lt;strong&gt;May 12th and 13th&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We met a lot of new people and known fellow PHP developers, and like &lt;a href=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/php-day-2015/&#34;&gt;previous&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/php-day-2016/&#34;&gt;years&lt;/a&gt;, we wanted to write down a light summary; like the previous ones, this won&amp;rsquo;t be a full &amp;ldquo;review&amp;rdquo; of the conference, but an highlight of the talks that captured most of our attention, or what we found more valuable for our everyday work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope to give a brief glimpse of what we experienced to fellow developers that hadn&amp;rsquo;t the opportunity to attend, and to tempt some of you to join conferences like this one or those in the PHP community at large, for your personal and professional growth. Like last year, we will later edit this article embedding the videos of the talks, when they will got released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;it&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Are you wondering how the first day of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/phpDay?src=hash&#34;&gt;#phpDay&lt;/a&gt; went? That was amazing! &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/6630Zguq1Q&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/6630Zguq1Q&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; phpDay by GrUSP (@phpday) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/phpday/status/863314622656458753&#34;&gt;13 maggio 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talks are in chronological order, and we linked the slides when available. Enjoy your reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;technical-talks&#34;&gt;Technical Talks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;climbing-the-abstract-syntax-tree&#34;&gt;Climbing the Abstract Syntax Tree&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;James Titcumb (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/asgrim&#34;&gt;@asgrim&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1 - 11:00 – 12:00 - track 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk started a bit complicated, since it tackles a very complex matter: the Abstract Syntax Tree that has been added to PHP since version 7, and it the implications of its use; following up a bit, it included some very easy, low level example of how the language works with the AST, and the fact that the example were in PHP itself helped a lot in increasing the understanding of the matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;managing-dependencies-is-more-than-running-composer-update&#34;&gt;Managing dependencies is more than running &amp;ldquo;composer update&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nils Adermann (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/naderman&#34;&gt;@naderman&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1 - 15:30 – 16:30 - track 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nils is one of the co-authors of Composer, but this talk was about &amp;ldquo;dependencies&amp;rdquo; in general, not just about the literal, software ones: every software project has a lot of dependecies apart from the libs that we install in the vendor folder, and he explained how we should approach them, and how we should mitigate the risks that they can add to our work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-science-of-code-reviews&#34;&gt;The Science of Code Reviews&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rick Kuipers (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rskuipers&#34;&gt;@rskuipers&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - 12:00 – 13:00 - track 2 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/rskuipers/the-science-of-code-reviews&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Code reviews and pair programming are two very valuable tools that we can leverage in our work as developers. This talk was really interesting, and it started from reasons behind why do them, up to suggestions and tips on how to improve them if you already do in your team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;extremely-defensive-php&#34;&gt;Extremely defensive PHP&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marco Pivetta (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ocramius&#34;&gt;@ocramius&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - 15:30 – 16:30 - track 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marco gave this talk already a lot of times on some conferences and some user groups, but it&amp;rsquo;s great! He suggests how to write code in a &amp;ldquo;defensive&amp;rdquo; way, to avoid that others are able to do mistakes with it and create problems down the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;keynotes&#34;&gt;Keynotes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-manifesto&#34;&gt;Code Manifesto&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graham Daniels (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/greydnls&#34;&gt;@greydnls&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1 - 09:45 – 10:45&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first keynote wasn&amp;rsquo;t strictly technical, but it was still more than interesting: Graham guided us through how much inequality and hidden problems minorities (and especially women) have to face everyday in our line of work; Graham is also the author behind the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/greydnls/code-manifesto&#34;&gt;Code Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;, a basic list of principles to be followed on OSS and workplaces to actively fight this issues and encourage diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;noestimates-the-10-new-principles-for-software-projects-predicting-without-estimating&#34;&gt;NoEstimates: The 10 new principles for Software Projects - predicting without estimating&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vasco Duarte (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/duarte_vasco&#34;&gt;@duarte_vasco&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - 09:45 – 10:45&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vasco is the famous author of the #NoEstimate strategy, and his keynote was aimed at explaining the wrong things the foundation of the issues of our industry, where estimates are always wrong and are often used to &amp;ldquo;bet&amp;rdquo; the future of our companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-open-source-for-fun-and-profit&#34;&gt;Using Open Source for Fun and Profit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gary Hockin (&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/geeh&#34;&gt;@geeh&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - 17:30 – 18:30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his keynote, Gary told us his story of how, from a simple developer, he became a Zend contributor first, and the JetBrains Developer Advocate now; the basic lessons that we can take from his experience is that open source contributions (no matter how small) are good for your career, and that when you give to the community, the community will give back to you very soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/phpday-2017/facile-engineering-team-phpday-2017.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;The Facile.it engineering team at PHPDay 2017&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>#FacileHack 2017, 10 days later</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/facilehack-2017-10-days-later/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/facilehack-2017-10-days-later/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Ten days ago &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackathon.facile.it/2017.html&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;#FacileHack 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; came to its conclusion; this was the second edition of the hackathon organized by Facile.it. Holding an event of this kind has allowed us to see, work and discuss with many very diverse teams, made up of programmers, designers and marketers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hackathon&amp;rsquo;s theme for this year was &lt;strong&gt;connectivity&lt;/strong&gt;: our site offers the comparation between internet access services, and we have decided to put this at the center of the competition. The teams have then faced each other on this theme, searching new ways to improve Facile.it&amp;rsquo;s business and the customers&amp;rsquo; user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;continuous-improvement&#34;&gt;Continuous improvement&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience we gained from the first edition allowed us to easily organize this event, and as we like to apply ourselves in our everyday work, we wanted to aim for a continuous and progressive improvement in organizing this hackathon, and this proved to be a winning approach.
  
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/X-OdVcH7CMs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the improving point of this edition was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackathon.facile.it/2017.html#giuria&#34;&gt;external jury&lt;/a&gt; composed by very experienced professionals of different expertise. Despite the very few minutes available (only seven) to the various teams to present their ideas, the jurors were very good at analyzing the various proposals and to offer the right questions to dissect the critical points of each proposed approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-winning-team&#34;&gt;The winning team&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team that won the competition was &lt;strong&gt;Orange Smile&lt;/strong&gt;, proposing Facilino, a virtual assistant: the team&amp;rsquo;s merit was especially in the overall completeness of the proposed solution, which started from identifying the problems and proposing a solution up to its application and its launch to the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/facilehack-2017-10-giorni-dopo/orange-smile.jpg&#34; title=&#34;I vincitori di #FacileHack 2017: team Orange Smile&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winners were awarded a € 500 voucher, for each team member, to be spent on high-level professional training courses made available by our partners &lt;a href=&#34;https: //www.enter .com / en / ecosystem / education /&#34;&gt;LOG.ED&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ninjacademy.it/&#34;&gt;Ninja Academy&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fluentify.com/&#34;&gt;Fluentify&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;The focus on training&lt;/strong&gt; seemed like an important decision for us and in line with the spirit of our engineering division.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you to the next edition!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center; margin-bottom: 2em&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/facilehack-2017-10-giorni-dopo/facile-engineering-team.jpg&#34; title=&#34;FacileHack engineering team&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>#FacileHack 2017, 10 giorni dopo</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/facilehack-2017-10-giorni-dopo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/facilehack-2017-10-giorni-dopo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Dieci giorni fa è terminato &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackathon.facile.it/2017.html&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;#FacileHack 2017&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, la seconda edizione dell&amp;rsquo;hackathon organizzato da Facile.it. Tenere un evento di questo genere ci ha permesso di vedere all&amp;rsquo;opera e di confrontarci con tanti team molto eterogenei, composti da programmatori, designer e specialisti del marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il tema dell&amp;rsquo;hackathon di quest&amp;rsquo;anno è stata la &lt;strong&gt;connettività&lt;/strong&gt;: il nostro portale propone la comparazione dei servizi di connessione ad internet, e ha deciso di porre questo al centro della competizione. I diversi team si sono quindi affrontati su questo tema, per trovare modi per migliorare il business di Facile.it e l&amp;rsquo;esperienza utente degli utilizzatori del servizio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;miglioramento-continuo&#34;&gt;Miglioramento continuo&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;L&amp;rsquo;esperienza accumulata dalla prima edizione ci ha permesso di realizzare con facilità questo evento: così come ci piace applicarci nel nostro lavoro di tutti i giorni, abbiamo voluto ricercare un miglioramento continuo e progressivo anche nell&amp;rsquo;organizzare un hackathon, e questo si è rivelato un approccio vincente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/X-OdVcH7CMs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uno dei punti che più ci ha convinto di questa edizione è stata la &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackathon.facile.it/2017.html#giuria&#34;&gt;giuria esterna&lt;/a&gt; composta da professionisti molto esperti di diversi settori. Nonostante i pochi minuti (soltanto sette) a disposizione dei vari team per presentare la propria idea, è stata molto brava ad analizzare le varie soluzioni ed a proporre le giuste domande per sviscerare i punti critici di ogni approccio presentato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;il-team-vincente&#34;&gt;Il team vincente&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il team che ha vinto la competizione è stato &lt;strong&gt;Orange Smile&lt;/strong&gt;, con la proposta dell&amp;rsquo;assistente virtuale Facilino: la vittoria del team è stata decretata soprattutto dalla completezza della soluzione proposta, che andava dall&amp;rsquo;individuazione dei problemi, alla proposta di una soluzione, fino all&amp;rsquo;applicazione e al lancio sul mercato della stessa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/facilehack-2017-10-giorni-dopo/orange-smile.jpg&#34; title=&#34;I vincitori di #FacileHack 2017: team Orange Smile&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I vincitori si sono aggiudicati come premio un voucher del valore di 500 euro, per ogni componente della squadra, da spendere in formazione professionale attraverso i corsi di alto livello messi a disposizione dai partner &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.enter.it/it/ecosystem/education/&#34;&gt;LOG.ED&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ninjacademy.it/&#34;&gt;Ninja Academy&lt;/a&gt; e &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fluentify.com/&#34;&gt;Fluentify&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Puntare sulla formazione&lt;/strong&gt; ci è sembrata una scelta importante e in linea con lo spirito della nostra divisione engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E alla fine non possiamo che salutarvi e aspettarvi per la prossima edizione!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center; margin-bottom: 2em&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/facilehack-2017-10-giorni-dopo/facile-engineering-team.jpg&#34; title=&#34;FacileHack engineering team&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How PHP 7 &amp; TDD helped me sleep better</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/how-php-7-tdd-helped-me-sleep-better/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/how-php-7-tdd-helped-me-sleep-better/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-enemies-of-programming&#34;&gt;The enemies of programming&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many of you will agree with me, &lt;strong&gt;sleep deprivation&lt;/strong&gt; is the enemy of programming.&lt;br /&gt;
Maybe we fear only one thing more than that: &lt;strong&gt;being interrupted&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;http://heeris.id.au/2013/this-is-why-you-shouldnt-interrupt-a-programmer/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/how-php-7-tdd-helped-me-sleep-better/interruption.png&#34; alt=&#34;Why you shouldn&#39;t interrupt a programmer (by Jason Heeris)&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While writing code we have to think really hard, we use complex abstractions, we go through long business workflows and so on&amp;hellip; fatigue and interruptions are the main enemies of those in this line of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-experience&#34;&gt;My experience&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my day job, I do all this mental juggling on a pretty big project, which is based on PHP 5.5, Symfony 2.8, Doctrine etc.; luckily, in this project we use a good deal of &lt;strong&gt;good practices&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;automated software testing&lt;/strong&gt; is one of those. I actually switched to this job to learn about doing automatic testing, continuous integration and other best practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost half a year ago &lt;strong&gt;I became a dad&lt;/strong&gt;. It has been great, and you also get some unexpected perks! For example, my colleagues got me this gift for my son:
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/how-php-7-tdd-helped-me-sleep-better/blue-elephpant.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A blue elePHPant!&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we can say that his future is pretty clear&amp;hellip; But don&amp;rsquo;t say this to my wife!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the pregnancy, many of my friends and fellow parents warned me half jokingly about one thing: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;sleep now, you&amp;rsquo;ll be deadly tired after!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. Now I can say that they were a bit exaggerating, but I can&amp;rsquo;t deny that, having a child takes a toll on your sleep schedule&amp;hellip; Even if, as in my case having a 9 to 6 office job, my wonderful wife does all the parenting heavy lifting (and I consider myself pretty lucky for having her!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months after my son was born I also had the opportunity to start &lt;strong&gt;a new, fresh project&lt;/strong&gt;. To be completely honest, it was not actually fresh: it was a &lt;strong&gt;complete rewrite&lt;/strong&gt; of an internal service that&amp;rsquo;s used to manage the invoices for multiple business units inside our company. I knew pretty well that the old system had to be replaced, so I was put in charge of redoing it from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the issue with the old system (and the main reason behind the rewrite) was &lt;strong&gt;maintainability&lt;/strong&gt;: we had no tests, we had no proper development environment, and its design wasn&amp;rsquo;t that great; also, bureaucracy and invoicing are the core domain of the system, so it was inherently complex. It was the perfect environment to witness the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broken_windows_theory&#34;&gt;broken windows theory&lt;/a&gt; in action: the code base got worse over time, one patch, copy paste or quick fix at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, as anyone that&amp;rsquo;s passionate in technology would do, I took the opportunity to use a lot of new shiny tools: I picked &lt;strong&gt;PHP 7&lt;/strong&gt;, which had just been released, and started the project with something familiar to me but still pretty new and cool, &lt;strong&gt;Symfony 3.0&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-i-found-to-be-useful&#34;&gt;What I found to be useful&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rambled and thought about this project a lot in the past months with my colleagues, because the old system was costing us a lot of overhead in usage and maintenance, and we had a pretty clear idea of what its problems were, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t need to study a lot before starting to write the first classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, I had to spend &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; time thinking about an object oriented design for my project, but I was rapidly able to start writing code with confidence. In the end, most of this confidence came from a few choices that I pursued during the development of this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tdd-and-high-coverage&#34;&gt;TDD and high coverage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first choice that I am pretty satisfied about is &lt;strong&gt;automatic testing&lt;/strong&gt;: I already knew the advantages of doing tests and Test Driven Development, but in the previous project that practice was not introduced from the start, so not all the codebase was covered, and we couldn&amp;rsquo;t (or wouldn&amp;rsquo;t?) do TDD 100% of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case instead &lt;strong&gt;I wanted to write nearly everything with TDD&lt;/strong&gt;, and keep a &lt;strong&gt;very high threshold for the minimum coverage&lt;/strong&gt; achieved through automatic testing. Right now I&amp;rsquo;m sitting on a ~92% test coverage, and I feel proud about it. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t a mere &amp;ldquo;let&amp;rsquo;s hit 100%!&amp;rdquo; mindless goal (&lt;a href=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/software-testing-coverage-vs-efficacia/&#34;&gt;since it&amp;rsquo;s pointless&lt;/a&gt;), but it fueled &lt;strong&gt;a positive feedback cycle&lt;/strong&gt; instead: the more I used TDD in writing new classes, the more the coverage rose and stayed high; at the same time, I found myself inspecting the coverage reports to find missing spots, and that allowed me to discover many edge-cases that I didn&amp;rsquo;t test and should have been.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I still left some parts without coverage or specific tests, since it was pointless to test them (e.g. Doctrine entities), while I covered some parts multiple times, since they were &lt;strong&gt;critical paths&lt;/strong&gt; inside my application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;unit-tests-to-the-rescue&#34;&gt;Unit tests to the rescue!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, the main critical advantage that TDD gave me was &lt;strong&gt;focus even on strained days&lt;/strong&gt;: I wrote the classes starting from unit tests, giving all my effort to one piece of code at a time, without having to keep in mind the entire project with its complexities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then wrote some functional tests to assure that the &lt;strong&gt;collaboration between my unit-tested objects&lt;/strong&gt; was fine, and this later step was also useful in delaying the definition of the classes as services inside the Symfony DI container. I was also &lt;strong&gt;able to change my mind&lt;/strong&gt; a few times on some details of the design without having to suffer mental confusion or rewrite too much code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;php-7-scalar-and-return-types-declarations&#34;&gt;PHP 7: scalar and return types declarations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second good choice was &lt;strong&gt;PHP 7&lt;/strong&gt;: among the reasons behind it as the language version of choice for this project were the &lt;a href=&#34;http://php.net/manual/en/migration70.new-features.php&#34;&gt;two main new features&lt;/a&gt; introduced: &lt;strong&gt;scalar types&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;return type declarations&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;p style=&#34;text-align: center;&#34;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/how-php-7-tdd-helped-me-sleep-better/return-types-everywhere-meme.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Return types, return types everywhere!&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Facile.it, I worked as C++ developer, and oh boy! did I miss scalars and return types!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I came onboard of the PHP community right on time&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;, I thought&amp;hellip; So I took advantage of the situation to start using all these new features. I enjoyed having again the possibility to typehint strings and integers; I discovered how return types declaration enforces the cohesion of your objects really well, making it &lt;strong&gt;rightly painful to return different things&lt;/strong&gt;: it became impossible to return &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; OR &lt;em&gt;null&lt;/em&gt;, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, in my tests I found myself writing a lot of this kind of code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$result = $testClass-&amp;gt;method();
$this-&amp;gt;assertInstanceOf(SomeClass::class, $result);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did this more than once, just to realize that I was wasting my time! This was normally the first TDD step on PHP 5.x code, but now this kinds of assertion were futile, because the return type was already checked at a language level! Great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Return types also proved themselves to be a &lt;strong&gt;double-edged sword&lt;/strong&gt; in some cases, especially on Doctrine entities: they are really useful to enforce consistency in your values, since they trigger a &lt;code&gt;\TypeError&lt;/code&gt; each time you call a getter method on a erroneously empty property, but &lt;strong&gt;you can&amp;rsquo;t use them on nullable fields&lt;/strong&gt;, since it will break your application at any time during execution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, having return types declared on your business-logic classes it&amp;rsquo;s pretty useful, even more when used in conjunction with TDD: every time you define a mock you are forced to declare expectations and predictions with the right types, so it &lt;strong&gt;indirectly helps maintaining the collaboration contract between objects&lt;/strong&gt;, without too much hassle. If I changed a method&amp;rsquo;s signature that was mocked somewhere, the mock would break the test, &lt;strong&gt;highlighting the issue and making the tests&lt;/strong&gt; (and an high coverage) &lt;strong&gt;even more valuable&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, these and other &lt;strong&gt;good practices are helpful&lt;/strong&gt; for both your job and your personal life: you can go a long way in being fit and in the best shape while working, but stressful and (good) distracting events are unavoidable: you&amp;rsquo;ll often have to fight stress, fatigue or distractions, and there will be days where you can&amp;rsquo;t be at the top of your game, for any number of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since programming is a mental job, I think that having instruments and good practices in your toolset is invaluable, being them the &lt;strong&gt;essential tools of our craft&lt;/strong&gt;. Thus, I hope that those little life/programming lessons I learned in these months will be useful to other people like me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Facile.it devs @ PhpDay 2016</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/php-day-2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/php-day-2016/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Almost like a nice tradition, we went to the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://2016.phpday.it/&#34;&gt;PHP Day conference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; this year as well; this time too it was held in Verona, on &lt;strong&gt;May 13th and 14th&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We participated and attended numerous talks and, &lt;a href=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/php-day-2015/&#34;&gt;as last year&lt;/a&gt;, we wanted to write a light summary; this won&amp;rsquo;t be a full &amp;ldquo;review&amp;rdquo;, but our intent instead is to highlight what captured our interest most, or what we found more valuable for our everyday work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this way, we hope to give a brief glimpse of what we experienced to fellow developers that hadn&amp;rsquo;t the opportunity to attend, and to tempt some of you to join conferences like this one or those in the PHP community at large, for your personal and professional growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talks are in chronological order, and we linked the slides when available. Enjoy your reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;technical-talks&#34;&gt;Technical Talks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;your-api-is-a-ui&#34;&gt;Your API is a UI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Christopher Hoult (&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/choult&#34;&gt;@choult&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1 - 11:00 – 12:00 - track 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an interesting and very smooth talk. It stayed pretty general with nice advices about &lt;strong&gt;API development&lt;/strong&gt;, but showed some reasoning about a pyramidal &amp;ldquo;scheme of priorities&amp;rdquo; that we should follow, deriving from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maslow%27s_hierarchy_of_needs&#34;&gt;Maslow&amp;rsquo;s hierarchy of needs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dip-your-toes-in-the-sea-of-security&#34;&gt;Dip Your Toes in the Sea of Security&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;James Titcumb (&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/asgrim&#34;&gt;@asgrim&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1 - 14:30 – 15:30 - track 1 (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/asgrim1/dip-your-toes-in-the-sea-of-security-phpday-2016&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this talk we saw an interesting overview of &lt;strong&gt;security issues&lt;/strong&gt; that a web application can encounter. It ranged from basic SQL injection, to timing attacks (that were explained pretty well!), to CSRF protection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-learned-to-stop-worrying-and-love-regular-expressions&#34;&gt;How I learned to stop worrying and love Regular Expressions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jordi Boggiano (&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/seldaek&#34;&gt;@seldaek&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1 - 15:30 – 16:30 - track 1 (&lt;a href=&#34;http://slides.seld.be/?file=2016-05-13+How+I+learned+to+stop+worrying+and+love+Regular+Expressions.html&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this talk we went from basic &lt;strong&gt;regular expressions&lt;/strong&gt;, to basic pattern recognition, to advanced usage; the speaker took also the time to explain to us how the regex engine works, through thorough examples of pattern matching advancement and backtracking. Also, bonus points for the slides! They were pretty neat, and everything was themed to the &lt;em&gt;Dr. Strangelove&lt;/em&gt; movie, from images to phrases used in the examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dockerizing-your-php-ci-pipelines&#34;&gt;Dockerizing your PHP CI Pipelines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paul Dragoonis (&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/dr4goonis&#34;&gt;@dr4goonis&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1 - 17:00 – 17:30 - track 2 (&lt;a href=&#34;http://dragoonis.com/talks/phpday-may-2016/#/&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk was about &lt;strong&gt;using Jenkins with Docker&lt;/strong&gt; and having optimized pipelines for fast builds and short commit-to-deploy times. It should have been a 1-hour-long talk, so the speaker had to cut short on a lot of things, but I took a lot of useful advice from it nonetheless. Fortunately, he was kind enough to give the extra bits of his talk in the unconference track the day after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;drinking-beer-with-a-raspberry-pi-and-php&#34;&gt;Drinking Beer with a Raspberry Pi and PHP&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andrew Carter (&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/AndrewCarterUK&#34;&gt;@AndrewCarterUK&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - 15:30 – 16:30 - track 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk was uncommon but really funny. The speaker explained that programming the Raspberry Pi is possible even with PHP! He showed us a working example of an AaaS (Alcohol as a Service) machine. It was a simple tool with a liquid pump and a flow detector that is used to fill up glasses with any kind of drink. It can be activated via API as any regular service. The speaker also explained how it is possible to communicate with external devices via the powerful IO pins using Unix device files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;evolution-of-web-application-architecture&#34;&gt;Evolution of Web Application Architecture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kore Nordmann (&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/koredn&#34;&gt;@koredn&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - 15:30 – 16:30 - track 2 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://qafoo.com/resources/presentations/phpday_2016_2016/evolution_of_web_application_architecture.html&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk covered the &lt;strong&gt;evolution of the technological stack&lt;/strong&gt; behind a normal web application, from single-server to multi-server architecture. Each addition to the stack was discussed and weighted, without taking for granted any single step: from adding a master-slave database configuration, to caching session and\or query results. This gave us a pretty clear idea of &lt;strong&gt;when and why&lt;/strong&gt; such steps should be taken while adding new functionalities to a project, or overcoming technical challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;being-functional-in-php&#34;&gt;Being functional in PHP&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David de Boer (&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/ddeboer_nl&#34;&gt;@ddeboer_nl&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - 16:30 – 17:00 - track 1 (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/boerdedavid/being-functional-in-php-php-day-italy-2016&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This talk was an &lt;strong&gt;introduction to functional programming&lt;/strong&gt;. The speaker compared highly declarative languages such as Erlang with PHP. He demonstrated the options we have to adopt functional programming in PHP. Basic concepts were covered in a clear and simple way: mapping, reduction, function composition and higher-order functions. Particular focus was given to the use of pure functions and their main advantage: the absence of side effects. Finally, the speaker went through an interesting comparison between OOP and functional programming, showing their strengths and weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;keynotes&#34;&gt;Keynotes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;deploying-php-7&#34;&gt;Deploying PHP 7&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rasmus Lerdorf (&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/rasmus&#34;&gt;@rasmus&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1 - 09:45 – 10:45 (&lt;a href=&#34;http://talks.php.net/phpday16#/&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rasmus is a veteran at PHPDay, and he gives opening keynotes here almost every two years. This year&amp;rsquo;s was obviously about PHP 7, and it was more a technical talk than else. It went from &lt;strong&gt;benchmark data&lt;/strong&gt; to technical tips on how to smooth the transition to this new major version of PHP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-badoo-saved-1m-switching-to-php7&#34;&gt;How Badoo Saved $1M Switching to PHP7&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nikolay Krapivnyy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - 09:45 – 10:45 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/216377/verona_php_2.pdf&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://techblog.badoo.com/blog/2016/03/14/how-badoo-saved-one-million-dollars-switching-to-php7/&#34;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; about this technological switch made the rounds on a lot on PHP-related websites some months ago; this talk was very technical too, and it showed us how big is Badoo&amp;rsquo;s technological stack, with 3000 servers, 1000 of which running PHP. It gave us a nice overview of the &lt;strong&gt;technical challenges&lt;/strong&gt; that their tech team endured to do this upgrade, and how it gave them the possibility to save more than a half of their hardware resources; also&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-lang=&#34;it&#34;&gt;&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;Badoo put PHP 7 in production on Friday&amp;hellip; &lt;br&gt;/cc &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/agilegigi&#34;&gt;@agilegigi&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/poiluned%C3%ACcepensiamo?src=hash&#34;&gt;#poilunedìcepensiamo&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/hashtag/phpday?src=hash&#34;&gt;#phpday&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/OEj3Emxxee&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/OEj3Emxxee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Alessandro Lai (@AlessandroLai) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AlessandroLai/status/731403882321063936&#34;&gt;14 maggio 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blog restyling: switching to Hugo and GitHub Pages</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/switching-to-hugo-and-github-pages/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/eng/switching-to-hugo-and-github-pages/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;As you may have noticed, we went through a bit of a restyling in the last few days, and our blog changed a lot in terms of appearance and structure.
We are very happy with those changes, but the reason behind this transition is not just a simple template change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-we-were-searching-for&#34;&gt;What we were searching for&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before, we were using an hosted CMS to run the blog, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ghost.org/&#34;&gt;Ghost&lt;/a&gt;. We were happy with the results, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t our concern to administrate the server or bother about other hosting stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, as many other developers, we were &lt;strong&gt;hitching for something&lt;/strong&gt; more aligned with our inclinations: we wanted a tool that was closer to our daily jobs and our skills. We were also having &lt;strong&gt;problems during the revision phase&lt;/strong&gt; of the articles, since multiple persons couldn&amp;rsquo;t review and edit an article at the same time, fearing the risk of overwriting each other&amp;rsquo;s work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then came down with a list of requirements for our blog; we wanted:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;easy review of articles&lt;/strong&gt;: parallels reviews are a must&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;an easy workflow&lt;/strong&gt;: no major overhead, since the blog contributions are voluntary amongs us; we want to dedicate all the time to writing the articles, not wrestling with technical difficulties&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;no security flaws&lt;/strong&gt;: this point disqualified Wordpress and other famous CMS solutions; we wouldn&amp;rsquo;t like to spend time staying ahead of possible security risks, or have to worry over the hosting and installation problems that a widespread used CMS has&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;easy image hosting&lt;/strong&gt; and embedding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;easy management and modifications of the &lt;strong&gt;template&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;easy integrations of previously used &lt;a href=&#34;https://disqus.com/&#34;&gt;Disqus comments&lt;/a&gt; and Google Analytics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;preferably &lt;strong&gt;markdown content format&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;support for &lt;strong&gt;multilanguage articles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;git-and-the-github-pages&#34;&gt;Git and the GitHub pages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first solution that came to us was obviously &lt;strong&gt;Git&lt;/strong&gt;, the everyday tool for a team of developers working on the same piece of code (or text, in this case). We obviously then thought of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://pages.github.com/&#34;&gt;GitHub pages&lt;/a&gt; as an hosting solution: that is ideal, since we already have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it&#34;&gt;Github organization&lt;/a&gt; in place, so an organization homepage/site would perfectly fit the bill for our blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;hugo&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we set our eyes to that hosting solution, we started to search for a solution for building our blog. The proposed solution was &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;: it&amp;rsquo;s a static site generator, developed in Go, which fitted almost all of our requisites; also:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it generates the static HMTL site live, with a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/extras/livereload/&#34;&gt;live reload&lt;/a&gt; functionality&lt;/strong&gt;: while you edit your markdown article, the site refresh itself on each save of the file(s), so you can see a live preview of what you&amp;rsquo;re writing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;there are many templates ready to be used, and we &lt;a href=&#34;http://themes.gohugo.io/future-imperfect/&#34;&gt;chose one&lt;/a&gt; to be modified to our needs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the templates are built with the Go Templating engine, and with some easy manual edits we obtained all the requested features: multi-author support, link between translated articles, recent articles and top categories in the sidebar&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;deploying&#34;&gt;Deploying&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last step needed to smooth out our workflow was to find a &lt;strong&gt;deploy strategy&lt;/strong&gt;. Github pages need to have the site content published onto the master branch, and we obviously wanted to separate the source code of the site from that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We needed an easy way to reproduce this steps, ideally with a script commited to the repo, ready for everyone to use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;generate&lt;/strong&gt; the static site with Hugo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;avoid mixing (and committing)&lt;/strong&gt; the static copy with the source files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;commit the files to the master branch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugo normally generates the static copy in the &lt;code&gt;./public&lt;/code&gt; directory; to achieve this we used &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/X1011/git-directory-deploy&#34;&gt;a script that I found on GitHub itself&lt;/a&gt; that solved this exact problem. We started an empty &lt;code&gt;source&lt;/code&gt; branch, &lt;strong&gt;detached&lt;/strong&gt; from master:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git checkout -b source --orphan
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started our Hugo site inside it, and we put the &lt;code&gt;./public&lt;/code&gt; in the &lt;code&gt;.gitIgnore&lt;/code&gt;, so each static generation would not be committed. We then prepared the deploy script that, after generating the static site, uses a Git subtree approach to commit its content to the master branch, with a commit message of &lt;code&gt;publish: &amp;lt;last commit message from source&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;et-voilà-here-we-are&#34;&gt;Et voilà, here we are!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we hope that you will enjoy our new blog at least as much as we enjoyed building it ! Happy reading!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paraunit: test paralleli, Doctrine e le fixture</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/paraunit/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/paraunit/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Questo articolo è la sintesi di un talk presentato al &lt;a href=&#34;http://2015.symfonyday.it/&#34;&gt;SymfonyDay 2015&lt;/a&gt;; potete trovare le slide &lt;a href=&#34;http://jean85.github.io/slides/2015-10-paraunit-symfonyday/index.html&#34;&gt;qui&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;i-test-e-la-loro-durata&#34;&gt;I test e la loro durata&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sviluppare applicazioni scrivendo &lt;strong&gt;test&lt;/strong&gt; e facendo &lt;a href=&#34;https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test_driven_development&#34;&gt;Test Driven Development&lt;/a&gt; è un&amp;rsquo;ottima pratica, e dà parecchie soddisfazioni. Con l&amp;rsquo;andare del tempo, si fa &lt;strong&gt;crescere la suite di test&lt;/strong&gt; del proprio progetto, cercando di aumentarne la copertura e l&amp;rsquo;efficacia e si scrivono nuovi test corrispondenti alle nuove funzionalità che vengono man mano sviluppate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;L&amp;rsquo;aumento della quantità di test però porta alla crescita (direttamente proporzionale) del &lt;strong&gt;tempo necessario&lt;/strong&gt; ad eseguire i test stessi.
Nel caso dei &lt;strong&gt;test unitari&lt;/strong&gt; questo aumento è spesso trascurabile, poiché &lt;strong&gt;si limitano a caricare una singola classe&lt;/strong&gt; e ad analizzarne il comportamento in completo isolamento, terminando la loro esecuzione nel giro di &lt;strong&gt;pochi millisecondi&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quando invece parliamo di &lt;strong&gt;test funzionali&lt;/strong&gt;, il tempo di esecuzione non è più così limitato: vengono caricate &lt;strong&gt;molte più classi&lt;/strong&gt;, spesso viene coinvolto anche il &lt;strong&gt;database&lt;/strong&gt;, deve essere messa alla prova l&amp;rsquo;interazione tra molti elementi; il tutto porta a test la cui durata è talvolta di &lt;strong&gt;quasi un secondo&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leggendo libri e blog sull&amp;rsquo;argomento, e con l&amp;rsquo;esperienza personale, ho imparato che c&amp;rsquo;è una &lt;strong&gt;soglia critica&lt;/strong&gt; che rappresenta il limite ideale oltre il quale una test suite diventa troppo lenta, e questa soglia è di &lt;strong&gt;circa dieci minuti&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ma perché proprio dieci minuti? Il motivo è molto semplice, e pratico: in dieci minuti, il programmatore può fare una pausa, prendersi un caffè o decidere di discutere brevemente una questione tecnica con un collega, e al suo ritorno troverà la suite completata e potrà procedere col lavoro. In caso contrario, possono succedere due cose:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;il programmatore &lt;strong&gt;rimane a fissare lo schermo&lt;/strong&gt; mentre i test si eseguono, dando ragione ai detrattori dei test che affermano che fare TDD è una perdita di tempo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;si &lt;strong&gt;smette di eseguire la test suite&lt;/strong&gt;, o per lo meno di farla eseguire per intero.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La seconda opzione può sembrare fattibile: si fanno girare solo i &lt;strong&gt;test strettamente necessari&lt;/strong&gt; mentre si sviluppa, quelli che vengono scritti in quel momento o che coprono la parte di codice che si sta modificando, per poi eseguire il commit del proprio codice senza far girare l&amp;rsquo;intera suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In realtà &lt;strong&gt;questo approccio fa perdere valore ai test&lt;/strong&gt; stessi, perché i test sono codice che non andrà mai in produzione, e che quindi può dare valore ai nostri progetti solo se viene eseguito ogni volta. Inoltre questo approccio nasconde &lt;strong&gt;una trappola&lt;/strong&gt;, dato che i test, per essere davvero efficaci, vanno eseguiti tutti ogni volta: la loro forza sta proprio nell&amp;rsquo;&lt;strong&gt;individuare gli effetti collaterali&lt;/strong&gt; imprevisti delle nostre modifiche, i bug che possono presentarsi in punti inaspettati e apparentemente lontani del nostro progetto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;esecuzione-parallela-dei-test&#34;&gt;Esecuzione parallela dei test&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Facile.it lavoro in un progetto basato su Symfony2 e Doctrine e mi sono trovato proprio davanti a questa problematica: avevamo una &lt;strong&gt;suite di test che stava crescendo&lt;/strong&gt; a ritmo sostenuto e che a volte impiegava ad eseguirsi, tra build di preparazione ed esecuzione vera e propria, anche 25 minuti.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dopo aver ottimizzato le prestazioni del nostro ambiente di sviluppo (passando da Vagrant a Docker, ma questa è un&amp;rsquo;altra storia), ci siamo resi conto di aver bisogno di una soluzione più drastica al nostro problema, e abbiamo pensato di &lt;strong&gt;eseguire in parallelo i nostri test&lt;/strong&gt; per sfruttare al meglio le risorse hardware e ridurre così i tempi di esecuzione.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dopo un po&amp;rsquo; di ricerche, abbiamo individuato alcuni tool esistenti che permettevano questo approccio:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/brianium/paratest&#34;&gt;brianium/paratest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/liuggio/fastest&#34;&gt;liuggio/fastest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entrambi i tool sono ben sviluppati e semplici da utilizzare e le prime prove sui &lt;strong&gt;test unitari&lt;/strong&gt; sono state molto promettenti: grazie alla ridotta dimensione, la loro parallelizzazione è estremamente semplice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;i-problemi-di-concorrenza-nei-test-funzionali&#34;&gt;I problemi di concorrenza nei test funzionali&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quando siamo passati a provare Paratest sui &lt;strong&gt;test funzionali&lt;/strong&gt; abbiamo invece incontrato grossi problemi, che si concretizzavano in &lt;strong&gt;fallimenti casuali durante l&amp;rsquo;esecuzione parallela&lt;/strong&gt;. Questi fallimenti erano dati da un problema molto semplice: stavamo accedendo più volte e in parallelo al nostro database di test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ma perché il nostro codice, che è lo stesso che viene eseguito in produzione (dove elabora centinaia, migliaia di richieste al minuto) ha così tanti &lt;strong&gt;problemi di accesso concorrente&lt;/strong&gt; nell&amp;rsquo;ambiente di test? I motivi sono semplici:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;i dati di test sono pochi&lt;/strong&gt;, mentre in produzione abbiamo tabelle da milioni di righe;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;per questo motivo &lt;strong&gt;i test tentano di accedere sempre alle stesse righe&lt;/strong&gt; del database;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;la &lt;strong&gt;sequenza&lt;/strong&gt; di operazioni di ogni test in genere è &lt;strong&gt;lettura - elaborazione - scrittura&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;i test hanno una &lt;strong&gt;rapidità di esecuzione&lt;/strong&gt; superiore a quella di un utilizzatore umano.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tutti questi motivi contribuiscono a creare situazioni in cui &lt;strong&gt;si verificano dei &lt;a href=&#34;https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deadlock&#34;&gt;deadlock&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; e che il nostro database può risolvere solo bloccando uno dei due tentativi di accesso ai dati, facendo così fallire il test corrispondente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Un altro problema che può verificarsi è l&amp;rsquo;&lt;strong&gt;alterazione dei dati&lt;/strong&gt;: quando due test vengono eseguiti in contemporanea, uno dei due può modificare il database e, così facendo, può far mancare i giusti dati di partenza ad un altro test che si sta avviando nello stesso istante.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purtroppo &lt;strong&gt;Paratest non offre una soluzione&lt;/strong&gt; a questo genere di problemi, mentre Fastest propone come approccio la creazione di un database di test differente per ogni core del proprio processore, per poi eseguire tanti test in parallelo quanti sono i database a disposizione.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sfortunatamente anche questo approccio non ci ha soddisfatto, in quanto la costruzione del nostro database di test era piuttosto lenta (avevamo molte migration da eseguire e altrettante fixture da caricare ogni volta) e rischiavamo di guadagnare tempo da una parte per perderlo dall&amp;rsquo;altra, inoltre, avevamo avuto &lt;strong&gt;un&amp;rsquo;idea nuova&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;facile-it-paraunit&#34;&gt;facile-it/paraunit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://packagist.org/packages/facile-it/paraunit&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://poser.pugx.org/facile-it/paraunit/version.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Packagist&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://travis-ci.org/facile-it/paraunit&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://travis-ci.org/facile-it/paraunit.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Travis build&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://codeclimate.com/github/facile-it/paraunit&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://codeclimate.com/github/facile-it/paraunit/badges/gpa.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Codeclimate&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://coveralls.io/github/facile-it/paraunit?branch=master&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://coveralls.io/repos/facile-it/paraunit/badge.svg?branch=master&amp;amp;service=github&#34; alt=&#34;Coverage&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abbiamo così deciso di sviluppare la nostra soluzione: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit&#34;&gt;facile-it/paraunit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;è sviluppato con i &lt;strong&gt;componenti Symfony&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sa leggere la configurazione XML di PHPUnit&lt;/strong&gt; per individuare le test suite;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;esegue il &lt;strong&gt;parsing e l&amp;rsquo;aggregazione dei risultati&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;grazie ai processi separati, &lt;strong&gt;sa gestire i fatal error&lt;/strong&gt; senza far bloccare completamente l&amp;rsquo;esecuzione;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sempre grazie ai processi, riesce ad &lt;strong&gt;ottimizzare l&amp;rsquo;uso della memoria&lt;/strong&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;risulta &lt;strong&gt;affidabile&lt;/strong&gt; grazie al fatto che basa il suo responso sugli exit code dei singoli processi PHPUnit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La maggior parte di questi vantaggi sono ovviamente comuni a tutti gli approcci di parallelizzazione dei test, inoltre, grazie al parsing dei risultati, &lt;strong&gt;Paraunit sa riconoscere i casi di fallimento dovuti a deadlock&lt;/strong&gt; e riesegue i test che falliscono per questo motivo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questo però era solo un primo passo e ovviamente ci siamo concentrati sull&amp;rsquo;implementare una &lt;strong&gt;soluzione radicale ai problemi di concorrenza&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;facile-it-paraunit-testcase&#34;&gt;facile-it/paraunit-testcase&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://packagist.org/packages/facile-it/paraunit-testcase&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://poser.pugx.org/facile-it/paraunit-testcase/version.svg&#34; alt=&#34;Packagist&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La soluzione che abbiamo trovato è molto semplice: &lt;strong&gt;le transazioni&lt;/strong&gt;.
Per realizzarla nella sua totalità, abbiamo sviluppato un test-case per PHPUnit, rilasciato col pacchetto &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit-testcase&#34;&gt;facile-it/paraunit-testcase&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;; ovviamente il test-case è stato sviluppato in partenza per il nostro caso d&amp;rsquo;uso, ovvero per il &lt;strong&gt;test di un&amp;rsquo;applicazione basata su Symfony2 e Doctrine&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grazie a questo test-case, ogni test può accedere al database solo dentro una transazione e questa transazione non riceve mai il &lt;em&gt;commit&lt;/em&gt;, ma sempre il &lt;strong&gt;rollback&lt;/strong&gt; al termine. Questo significa che &lt;strong&gt;nulla verrà mai realmente scritto&lt;/strong&gt; sul nostro database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I vantaggi di questo approccio sono molteplici:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;nessun test può interferire&lt;/strong&gt; con gli altri, visto che non possono alterare i dati;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ogni test può permettersi di &lt;strong&gt;creare al volo un dato o di alterarne uno esistente&lt;/strong&gt;, senza doversi preoccupare di ripulire il database al termine, con grande risparmio di tempo nella scrittura dei test;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;il database di test rimane sempre pulito&lt;/strong&gt; e non dobbiamo più preoccuparci di prepararlo ogni volta che la suite deve essere eseguita, o che eseguiamo un test che può sporcare i dati;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;anche se non viene mai realmente scritto nulla, &lt;strong&gt;il database esegue comunque le verifiche di integrità&lt;/strong&gt;, quali vincoli di unicità o di chiavi esterne;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;diventa &lt;strong&gt;impossibile avere test interdipendenti&lt;/strong&gt;, ovvero test che possono funzionare solo se prima ne vengono eseguiti altri, che modificano in modo ideale i dati di fixture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;L&amp;rsquo;unico limite di questo approccio è che le transazioni sono disponibili solo con alcuni database e all&amp;rsquo;interno di Doctrine quindi solo con l&amp;rsquo;&lt;code&gt;EntityManager&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;la-rapidità-di-esecuzione&#34;&gt;La rapidità di esecuzione&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Per darvi un&amp;rsquo;idea di quanto possa essere veloce Paraunit rispetto alla normale esecuzione con PHPUnit, ho misurato il tempo di esecuzione della nostra test suite funzionale, che è sufficientemente ampia (261 classi, 1568 metodi):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://engineering.facile.it/images/paraunit/grafico.png&#34; alt=&#34;Grafico&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come potete vedere, Paraunit esegue l&amp;rsquo;intera test suite in soli &lt;strong&gt;6 minuti e 6 secondi&lt;/strong&gt;, mentre PHPUnit ci metterebbe &lt;strong&gt;oltre 40 minuti!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ho usato il condizionale per un motivo specifico: il tempo di esecuzione di PHPUnit è in realtà una stima (in proiezione lineare) perché, circa al 12% dell&amp;rsquo;esecuzione, il processo si è chiuso per &lt;strong&gt;esaurimento della memoria&lt;/strong&gt; a disposizione, a riprova di un altro dei vantaggi nell&amp;rsquo;uso di Paraunit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;test-coverage-in-parallelo&#34;&gt;Test coverage in parallelo&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Un&amp;rsquo;altra caratteristica di Paraunit, attualmente in sviluppo, è la possibilità di &lt;strong&gt;parallelizzare l&amp;rsquo;elaborazione della &lt;a href=&#34;https://phpunit.de/manual/current/en/code-coverage-analysis.html&#34;&gt;coverage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; dei test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questo è possibile grazie all&amp;rsquo;opzione &lt;code&gt;--coverage-php&lt;/code&gt; di PHPUnit che salva in un file .php il risultato parziale ottenuto; dopo aver lanciato i singoli test come processi separati, Paraunit esegue l&amp;rsquo;unione di tutti questi risultati.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;sviluppi-futuri&#34;&gt;Sviluppi futuri&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ovviamente questo è solo l&amp;rsquo;inizio, il primo &lt;strong&gt;rilascio in open source&lt;/strong&gt; della nostra soluzione.
Tra gli sviluppi futuri spero di poter realizzare:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;la &lt;strong&gt;prioritizzazione dei test lenti&lt;/strong&gt;, ovvero poter eseguire per primi i test noti per la loro lentezza, così da non rallentare l&amp;rsquo;esecuzione complessiva della test suite;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;l&amp;rsquo;aggiunta di &lt;strong&gt;altre opzioni&lt;/strong&gt; di selezione test, come p.e. l&amp;rsquo;opzione &lt;code&gt;--group&lt;/code&gt; di PHPUnit;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;il miglioramento delle &lt;strong&gt;prestazioni&lt;/strong&gt; all&amp;rsquo;avvio dei processi, cosa che pesa molto per i test unitari;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;il &lt;strong&gt;supporto per altri framework e ORM&lt;/strong&gt; oltre a Symfony e Doctrine, creando altri test-case appositi;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;il miglioramento della funzionalità di test coverage parallela;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;una soluzione per i database non transazionali, come MongoDB.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vi invito quindi a partecipare allo sviluppo di Paraunit su &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/facile-it/paraunit&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, proponendo pull request, aprendo issue per proporre nuove feature o anche semplicemente utilizzandolo per le vostre test suite, così da verificarne l&amp;rsquo;efficacia e la compatibilità!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Facile.it devs @ PHP Day 2015</title>
      <link>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/php-day-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 May 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://engineering.facile.it/blog/ita/php-day-2015/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Anche quest&amp;rsquo;anno si è svolto il &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://2015.phpday.it/&#34;&gt;PHP Day&lt;/a&gt; a Verona, il 15 e 16 maggio&lt;/strong&gt;. Noi sviluppatori di Facile.it abbiamo partecipato con un folto gruppo e seguito i vari talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In questo breve articolo vorremmo citare quelli che in qualche maniera &lt;strong&gt;ci hanno colpito&lt;/strong&gt;, per motivi tecnici e non, per dare l&amp;rsquo;opportunità a chi non ha potuto partecipare di sapere qualcosa di più, o per dare &lt;strong&gt;un assaggio della conferenza&lt;/strong&gt; a chi non ha mai partecipato a qualcosa del genere e, speriamo, invogliarlo a far parte della community!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ovviamente non pretendiamo di fare una recensione, né quanto meno una classifica&amp;hellip; I talk che abbiamo scelto di citare sono stati scelti per puro &lt;strong&gt;gusto personale&lt;/strong&gt;, o ci hanno semplicemente colpito perché si avvicinavano di più alla nostra esperienza di sviluppatori, o perché toccavano più da vicino lo &lt;strong&gt;stack tecnologico&lt;/strong&gt; da noi utilizzato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I talk sono in ordine cronologico. Buona lettura!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;indice&#34;&gt;Indice&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#prophecy&#34;&gt;PHP object mocking framework world: let&amp;rsquo;s compare Prophecy and PHPUnit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#containerize&#34;&gt;Containerize your PHP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#varnish&#34;&gt;Going crazy with Symfony2 and Varnish&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#psr-7&#34;&gt;Hello, PSR-7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#php7-data-structures&#34;&gt;PHP Data Structures (and the impact of PHP 7 on them)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#doctrine&#34;&gt;Doctrine ORM Good Practices and Tricks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&#34;keynotes&#34;&gt;Keynotes&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#coderabbi&#34;&gt;Talmudic Maxims to Maximize Your Growth as a Developer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#calevans&#34;&gt;Down the Rabbit Hole: Lessons Learned combining Career and Community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#seldaek&#34;&gt;Behind the Scenes of Maintaining an Open Source Project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;talk-tecnici&#34;&gt;Talk tecnici&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;prophecy&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;php-object-mocking-framework-world-let-s-compare-prophecy-and-phpunit&#34;&gt;PHP object mocking framework world: let&amp;rsquo;s compare Prophecy and PHPUnit&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sarah Khalil (&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/saro0h&#34;&gt;@saro0h&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1 - 14:30 – 15:30 - track 1 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/saro0h/php-day-verona-2015-php-object-mocking-framework-world&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/134728681&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Una buona esposizione su &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/phpspec/prophecy-phpunit&#34;&gt;prophecy&lt;/a&gt; la nuova tecnologia per effetuare mocking e stubbing. In questo talk sono state illustrate le API di prophecy e si è parlato di come questo strumento sarà sempre più integrato con phpunit (è già presente nella nuova versione 4.6) sino ad arrivare ad un completo rimpiazzo dei metodi nativi del famoso testing framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ricordatevi di aggiungere qualche altra parola (oltre a prophecy) chiave nelle vostre ricerche su google per evitare riferimenti biblici.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;containerize&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;containerize-your-php&#34;&gt;Containerize your PHP&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marek Jelen (&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/marek_jelen&#34;&gt;@marek_jelen&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1 - 15:30 – 16:30 - track 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/134728683&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si è parlato tanto nelle Conferences dell&amp;rsquo;ultimo anno di &lt;strong&gt;Docker e i container&lt;/strong&gt; come strumento di sviluppo, ma questo talk si è rivelato interessante, spiegando come fosse possibile utilizzare i container &lt;strong&gt;come strumento di deploy&lt;/strong&gt; e di creazione di immagini, in modo tale da contenere anche il sorgente del proprio progetto; abbiamo scoperto il tool &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/openshift/source-to-image&#34;&gt;Source to Image&lt;/a&gt;, che permette di creare queste immagini in maniera personalizzata e automatizzata partendo dal proprio codice (e dal &lt;code&gt;composer.json&lt;/code&gt;), e il progetto &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openshift.com/&#34;&gt;Openshift&lt;/a&gt;, portato avanti da RedHat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;varnish&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;going-crazy-with-symfony2-and-varnish&#34;&gt;Going crazy with Symfony2 and Varnish&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;David De Boer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1 - 17:30 – 18:00 - track 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/134814726&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prima di ascoltare questo talk, pensavamo che la &lt;strong&gt;cache HTTP&lt;/strong&gt; (e Varnish) fossero praticamente inutilizzabili in un &lt;strong&gt;ambito di sito non-pubblico&lt;/strong&gt;, dove i contenuti vanno serviti (e variano in base) ad utenti sempre autenticati.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abbiamo scoperto il &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/FriendsOfSymfony/FOSHttpCacheBundle&#34;&gt;FOSHttpCacheBundle&lt;/a&gt;, e il trucco che permette di fare caching anche di questo tipo di contenuti: Varnish prende il cookie e controlla la cache non in base a quello, ma in base ad un hash che viene fornito dall&amp;rsquo;applicazione stessa tramite un altra chiamata; questo permette di &lt;strong&gt;mappare i contenuti cachati&lt;/strong&gt; non sui singoli utenti, ma &lt;strong&gt;con logiche più ottimizzate&lt;/strong&gt; (gruppi di utenti? set di permessi?) ed eventualmente più legate alla business logic dell&amp;rsquo;applicazione stessa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;psr-7&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;hello-psr-7&#34;&gt;Hello, PSR-7&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Beau Simensen (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/beausimensen&#34;&gt;@beausimensen&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - 11:00 – 12:00 - track 2 (&lt;a href=&#34;https://beau.io/talks/2015/05/16/hello-psr-7-phpday-2015/&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/134281520&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In questo talk abbiamo potuto conoscere da vicino la genesi dello &lt;strong&gt;standard PSR-7&lt;/strong&gt; (di cui abbiamo già scritto in un &lt;a href=&#34;http://engineering.facile.it/php-fig-standard-psr-7-http-message-interfaces/&#34;&gt;altro articolo&lt;/a&gt;), raccontata da una delle persone che hanno seguito da vicino e contribuito alla scrittura della proposta stessa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lo standard sarà approvato a brevissimo (solo 3 giorni dopo il talk!) e molti aspettano di vedere cosa comporterà a livello di framework PHP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;php7-data-structures&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;php-data-structures-and-the-impact-of-php-7-on-them&#34;&gt;PHP Data Structures (and the impact of PHP 7 on them)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Patrick Allaert (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/patrick_allaert&#34;&gt;@patrick_allaert&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - 12:00 – 13:00 - track 1 (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/patrick.allaert/php-data-structures-and-the-impact-of-php-7-on-them-php-days-2015&#34;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/134070469&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questo talk, dal sapore molto tecnico, ci ha fatto addentrare negli internals degli &lt;strong&gt;array PHP&lt;/strong&gt;, e in quanto siano talmente specializzati a far tutto, da essere &lt;strong&gt;inefficienti&lt;/strong&gt; in moltissimi casi; abbiamo visto numerose &lt;strong&gt;alternative più specialistiche&lt;/strong&gt; per i vari casi d&amp;rsquo;uso (&lt;a href=&#34;http://php.net/manual/en/class.splfixedarray.php&#34;&gt;SplFixedArray&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://php.net/manual/en/class.splqueue.php&#34;&gt;SplQueue&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://php.net/manual/en/class.splstack.php&#34;&gt;SplStack&lt;/a&gt;&amp;hellip;); sfruttare gli uni piuttosto che gli altri impatta fortemente sulle &lt;strong&gt;prestazioni&lt;/strong&gt; nei tempi e nell&amp;rsquo;uso della memoria, e abbiamo visto nel dettaglio alcuni benchmark che mostrano come questi costi diminuiscono (spesso di gran lunga) &lt;strong&gt;tra PHP 5.6 e PHP 7&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;doctrine&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;doctrine-orm-good-practices-and-tricks&#34;&gt;Doctrine ORM Good Practices and Tricks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marco Pivetta (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/Ocramius&#34;&gt;@Ocramius&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - 15:30 – 16:30 - track 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://player.vimeo.com/video/134178140&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usiamo &lt;strong&gt;Doctrine&lt;/strong&gt; tutti i giorni, ma questo talk, sebbene marcato come di livello &lt;strong&gt;beginner&lt;/strong&gt;, si è rivelato molto interessante e fonte di numerose discussioni e &lt;strong&gt;riflessioni&lt;/strong&gt; tra colleghi. Lo speaker è uno dei principali contributors al progetto &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/doctrine/doctrine2&#34;&gt;doctrine-orm&lt;/a&gt;, e ci ha elencato una serie di &lt;strong&gt;best practices&lt;/strong&gt;, partendo dal chiedersi se e quando è il caso di usare un ORM, passando poi a problemi quali l&amp;rsquo;uso e l&amp;rsquo;implementazione di entità, la loro consistenza, l&amp;rsquo;evitare di usare setter brutali o di esporre le ArrayCollection che rappresentano le nostre relazioni.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;keynotes-1&#34;&gt;Keynotes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abbiamo voluto citare in questo articolo anche i &lt;strong&gt;3 keynote&lt;/strong&gt; della conferenza: sono stati tutti piuttosto interessanti, profondamente motivazionali e coinvolgenti.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;coderabbi&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;talmudic-maxims-to-maximize-your-growth-as-a-developer&#34;&gt;Talmudic Maxims to Maximize Your Growth as a Developer&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yitzchok Willroth (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/coderabbi&#34;&gt;@coderabbi&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 1 - keynote di apertura&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yitz, studente rabbinico poi passato alla programmazione, molto famoso nella community PHP, ci ha spinto a considerare alcuni suoi consigli su come poterci &lt;strong&gt;migliorare come sviluppatori&lt;/strong&gt; e come membri della community stessa: cercare e coltivare un mentore, essere pazienti ed accettare i consigli, aiutare gli altri per ripagare tutto questo, partecipare nell&amp;rsquo;open source&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personalmente, mi ha anche fatto scoprire tre siti piuttosto interessanti:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://phpmentoring.org/&#34;&gt;PHP Mentoring&lt;/a&gt; e &lt;a href=&#34;http://hackpledge.org&#34;&gt;Hackpledge&lt;/a&gt;, per chi è in cerca di un &lt;strong&gt;mentore&lt;/strong&gt; o vuole diventarlo per aiutare altri a diventare programmatori migliori&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://up-for-grabs.net/&#34;&gt;Up for grabs&lt;/a&gt;, un sito raccoglitore di &lt;strong&gt;issue su GitHub *semplici&lt;/strong&gt;*, un ottimo punto di inizio per chi vorrebbe partecipare a progetti open source, ma non sa da dove cominciare&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;calevans&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;down-the-rabbit-hole-lessons-learned-combining-career-and-community&#34;&gt;Down the Rabbit Hole: Lessons Learned combining Career and Community&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cal Evans (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twitter.com/calevans&#34;&gt;@CalEvans&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - keynote di apertura&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cal è il community manager (ma non chiamatelo così!) per Zend, e ci ha raccontato con estrema passione, qualche lacrima e in maniera molto divertente la sua storia, come è nata la sua carriera di programmatore e come il suo percorso si è intrecciato con la community PHP e il mondo dell&amp;rsquo;open source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tutto questo per spiegarci come &lt;strong&gt;far parte della community è un valore&lt;/strong&gt; importante per tutti ma soprattutto per noi stessi, e come la nostra sia così grande, forte e basata su uno &lt;strong&gt;spirito positivo&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&#34;seldaek&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;behind-the-scenes-of-maintaining-an-open-source-project&#34;&gt;Behind the Scenes of Maintaining an Open Source Project&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jordi Boggiano (&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/seldaek&#34;&gt;@seldaek&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Day 2 - keynote di chiusura&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jordi è il creatore e mantainer di &lt;a href=&#34;https://getcomposer.org/&#34;&gt;Composer&lt;/a&gt;, uno dei principali tool per un programmatore PHP. Nel suo keynote ci ha raccontato con franchezza la sua esperienza in prima persona nel &lt;strong&gt;gestire un progetto open source&lt;/strong&gt; così vasto e popolare, come spesso sia difficile accontentare tutti, e alcuni retroscena e dettagli di qualche curiosa pull request.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>